const arr = [{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017","4th-year/neuroscience/2019","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 25-year-old male presents to the emergency room with sudden urinary retention and lower limb weakness. The neurosurgeon is called, urgent surgery is recommended after relevant imaging studies. To establish a diagnosis of cauda equina syndrome, besides the aforementioned symptoms, what other clinical feature must be present?","answers":[{"option":"Saddle anesthesia","bool":true},{"option":"Bilateral foot drop","bool":false},{"option":"Brisk reflexes in lower limbs","bool":false},{"option":"Increased muscle tone","bool":false},{"option":"Increased bulk below knee joints","bool":false}],"id":0},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017","4th-year/neuroscience/2018","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"What is the antidote to benzodiazepine poisoning?","answers":[{"option":"N-acetylcysteine","bool":false},{"option":"Physostigmine","bool":false},{"option":"Deferoxamine","bool":false},{"option":"Activated charcoal","bool":false},{"option":"Flumazenil","bool":true}],"id":1},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017","4th-year/neuroscience/2018","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"According to the McDonald criteria for the diagnosis of multiple sclerosis, if a patient has 2 episodes separated in time and space, with clinical evidence of at least 2 lesions on MRI, what further investigations are required for the diagnosis of MS?","answers":[{"option":"Wait for another episode as further imaging needed","bool":false},{"option":"Wait 1 year to assess disease progression","bool":false},{"option":"No further requirement as clinical evidence alone suffices","bool":true},{"option":"Wait for seeing a rise in intracranial pressure to perform lumbar puncture","bool":false},{"option":"Wait for another lesion with additional attacks","bool":false}],"id":2},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017","4th-year/neuroscience/2018","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"What type of speech is observed in patients with mania?","answers":[{"option":"Sing-song","bool":false},{"option":"Disorganized (word salad)","bool":false},{"option":"Incoherent","bool":false},{"option":"Poverty of speech","bool":false},{"option":"Flight of ideas","bool":true}],"id":3},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017","4th-year/neuroscience/2018","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which cranial nerve carries sensory information in the corneal reflex?","answers":[{"option":"Cranial nerve IV","bool":false},{"option":"Cranial nerve VII","bool":false},{"option":"Cranial nerve V","bool":true},{"option":"Cranial nerve XI","bool":false},{"option":"Cranial nerve III","bool":false}],"id":4},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 45-year-old female presents to the outpatient clinic with a history of progressive difficulty in walking for 6 months along with numbness in hands and feet. On examination, she has a bilateral high stepping gait with a positive Romberg sign. There was wasting and weakness of distal muscles of both upper and lower limbs with reduced reflexes. What will be the first investigation of choice to diagnose the disease?","answers":[{"option":"Creatine phosphokinase levels","bool":false},{"option":"MRI cervical spine","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebrospinal fluid analysis","bool":false},{"option":"Nerve conduction studies","bool":true},{"option":"Muscle biopsy","bool":false}],"id":5},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2021","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A child requires multiple minor surgical procedures in the nasopharynx. Which drug has high surface local anesthetic activity and intrinsic vasoconstrictor actions that reduce bleeding in the mucous membrane?","answers":[{"option":"Procaine","bool":false},{"option":"Lidocaine","bool":false},{"option":"Cocaine","bool":true},{"option":"Bupivacaine","bool":false},{"option":"Tetracaine","bool":false}],"id":6},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2021","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 19-year-old male is brought by his father to the psychiatry clinic with complaints of singing out loud throughout the night, sleeplessness, and claiming he is a famous singer. He had one similar episode in the past and one previous episode with symptoms of low energy and mood, for which he received treatment and reached a pre-morbid level of functionality. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Mania","bool":false},{"option":"Depression with psychotic features","bool":false},{"option":"Bipolar affective disorder","bool":true},{"option":"Schizophrenia","bool":false},{"option":"Cyclothymia","bool":false}],"id":7},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021","4th-year/neuroscience/2022","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Which of the following anti-depressants has a stronger risk of self-harm and suicide?","answers":[{"option":"Tricyclic antidepressants","bool":true},{"option":"Selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors","bool":false},{"option":"Atypical antidepressants","bool":false},{"option":"Serotonin norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors","bool":false},{"option":"Monoamine oxidase inhibitors","bool":false}],"id":8},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of the following neurological diseases has the highest mortality rate?","answers":[{"option":"Meningitis","bool":false},{"option":"Neurodegenerative diseases","bool":false},{"option":"Gliomas","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebrovascular disease","bool":true},{"option":"Neuropathies","bool":false}],"id":9},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"Which of the following can be found in the brain in neurosarcoidosis?","answers":[{"option":"Reactive gliosis","bool":false},{"option":"Liquefactive necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Plaques in MRI","bool":false},{"option":"Gliotic scars","bool":false},{"option":"Non-caseating granulomas","bool":true}],"id":10},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"What basal exudate will be seen in tuberculous meningitis?","answers":[{"option":"Serous","bool":false},{"option":"Mucinous","bool":false},{"option":"Necrotic","bool":false},{"option":"Mucopurulent","bool":false},{"option":"Gelatinous","bool":true}],"id":11},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A 31-year-old female presents to the emergency room with a headache, fever, and swelling around the eyes. She has had a history of sinusitis for the past 4 months. Examination revealed decreased visual acuity, diminished pupillary reflexes, ptosis, periorbital edema, and painful eye movement. Fundoscopic examination shows papilledema. Vitals include a temperature of 102Â°F, a heart rate of 110 beats per minute, and blood pressure of 130/87 mmHg.  What is the most likely cause of her symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Subarachnoid hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Cluster headache","bool":false},{"option":"Meningitis","bool":false},{"option":"Cavernous sinus thrombosis","bool":true},{"option":"Stroke","bool":false}],"id":12},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A 10-year-old boy presents to the hospital with a severe headache and high-grade fever. Examination reveals he is irritable, febrile, and nuchal rigidity is present. A lumbar puncture with cerebrospinal fluid detailed report (CSF D/R) is ordered. What finding would indicate viral meningitis?","answers":[{"option":"Cloudy fluid","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased glucose","bool":false},{"option":"Lymphocytosis","bool":true},{"option":"Very high opening pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased proteins","bool":false}],"id":13},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is not a risk factor for subdural hematoma?","answers":[{"option":"Previous shunt surgery","bool":false},{"option":"Head trauma","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic alcoholism","bool":false},{"option":"Old age","bool":false},{"option":"Smoking","bool":true}],"id":14},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of these is the first-line investigation in a patient presenting with subarachnoid hemorrhage?","answers":[{"option":"Plain computed tomography","bool":true},{"option":"Magnetic resonance imaging","bool":false},{"option":"Ultrasound","bool":false},{"option":"Contrast enhanced computed tomography","bool":false},{"option":"Lumbar puncture","bool":false}],"id":15},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of the following disorder is not a risk factor for suicide?","answers":[{"option":"Depressive disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Schizophrenic disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Personality disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Obsessive-compulsive disorder (OCD)","bool":true},{"option":"Alcohol abuse","bool":false}],"id":16},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 65-year-old male presents to the clinic with progressive bilateral asymmetric tremors, which disappear upon performing routine activities. He has no history of forgetfulness. His attendants notice his movements are slow and sluggish. There is no history of falls, difficulty in swallowing, or respiratory problems. Upon questioning, his daughter reports a long history of constipation and sleep issues such as dream reenactments and insomnia. An MRI of the brain shows insignificant age-related changes. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Huntington disease","bool":false},{"option":"Parkinson disease","bool":true},{"option":"Lewy body dementia","bool":false},{"option":"Severe depression","bool":false},{"option":"Multiple cortical infarcts","bool":false}],"id":17},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"What is the first-line drug used in the treatment of status epilepticus?","answers":[{"option":"Diazepam","bool":true},{"option":"Phenytoin","bool":false},{"option":"Parenteral valporic acid","bool":false},{"option":"Fosphenytoin","bool":false},{"option":"Flumazenil","bool":false}],"id":18},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"What is the first-line treatment for trigeminal neuralgia?","answers":[{"option":"Ethosuximide","bool":false},{"option":"Carbamazepine","bool":true},{"option":"Phenytoin","bool":false},{"option":"Lamotrigine","bool":false},{"option":"Gabapentin","bool":false}],"id":19},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"What is another name for neurofilaments?","answers":[{"option":"Neurotransmitters","bool":false},{"option":"Nerve fibers","bool":false},{"option":"Nodes of Ranvier","bool":false},{"option":"Neurotubules","bool":false},{"option":"Neurofibrils","bool":true}],"id":20},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of the following anxiety disorders comprises of specific conditions?","answers":[{"option":"Obsessive-compulsive disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Panic disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Generalized anxiety disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Post-traumatic stress disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Phobic anxiety disorder","bool":true}],"id":21},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common mechanism of action of antipsychotic drugs?","answers":[{"option":"Alpha-adrenergic activity","bool":false},{"option":"Increase serotonin levels","bool":false},{"option":"Decrease dopamine levels","bool":true},{"option":"Decrease norepinephrine","bool":false},{"option":"Beta-adrenergic activity","bool":false}],"id":22},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Why is epinephrine recommended in local anesthesia?","answers":[{"option":"It is easily reversible","bool":false},{"option":"It vasoconstricts and prolongs anesthesia","bool":true},{"option":"It is a vasodilator","bool":false},{"option":"It increases body secretions","bool":false},{"option":"It is rapid acting","bool":false}],"id":23},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A 37-year-old male presents to the neurology outpatient department with drooping eyelids and double vision. He is diagnosed with oculomotor nerve palsy. Damage to which vessel is most likely to cause his condition?","answers":[{"option":"Middle cerebral artery","bool":false},{"option":"Posterior communicating artery","bool":true},{"option":"Posterior cerebral artery","bool":false},{"option":"Anterior cerebral artery","bool":false},{"option":"Posterior inferior cerebral artery","bool":false}],"id":24},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 38-year-old woman presents to the outpatient clinic with complaints of double vision and unable to open the right eye completely. She has a history of a road traffic accident 4 months back. On examination of the right eye, there is eyelid drooping. The eye deviates outward and downward. Which cranial nerve is most likely damaged in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Cranial nerve II","bool":false},{"option":"Cranial nerve V","bool":false},{"option":"Cranial nerve III","bool":true},{"option":"Cranial nerve VI","bool":false},{"option":"Cranial nerve IV","bool":false}],"id":25},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"An 8-year-old child is brought to the clinic by his parents with the complaint of inattention and inability to sit in the class. What is the probable diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Personality disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Reactive attachment disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Conduct disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Oppositional defiant disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD)","bool":true}],"id":26},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 30-year-old male presents to the emergency room after head trauma with complaints of headache and bleeding from the right ear. CT scan shows a right temporal bone fracture. He is discharged after a period of observation. One week later he came with difficulty in closing the right eye, which of the following nerve is likely to be involved in this case?","answers":[{"option":"V","bool":false},{"option":"II","bool":false},{"option":"III","bool":false},{"option":"VI","bool":false},{"option":"VII","bool":true}],"id":27},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the most appropriate first step in the immediate management of a patient presenting to the emergency room with status epilepticus?","answers":[{"option":"Draw blood to send for complete blood count","bool":false},{"option":"Ensure patent airway access","bool":true},{"option":"Administer intravenous diazepam 10 mg","bool":false},{"option":"Administer etomidate for intubation","bool":false},{"option":"Give the patient general anesthesia","bool":false}],"id":28},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which of the following bacteria is a known cause of meningitis and can be diagnosed by Quellung reaction?","answers":[{"option":"Neisseria gonorrhea","bool":false},{"option":"Streptococcus pneumoniae","bool":true},{"option":"Salmonella enterica","bool":false},{"option":"Haemophilus influenzae","bool":false},{"option":"Escherichia coli","bool":false}],"id":29},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which organism can cause meningitis in a child consuming unpasteurized milk?","answers":[{"option":"Staphylococcus aureus","bool":false},{"option":"Listeria monocytogenes","bool":true},{"option":"Neisseria meningitidis","bool":false},{"option":"Streptococcus pneumoniae","bool":false},{"option":"Clostridium botulinum","bool":false}],"id":30},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is a major risk factor for most forms of dementia?","answers":[{"option":"Advanced age","bool":true},{"option":"Smoking","bool":false},{"option":"Lifestyle","bool":false},{"option":"Genetic cause","bool":false},{"option":"Environmental factor","bool":false}],"id":31},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 30-year-old male presents to the outpatient department with complaints of loss of pain and temperature sensations in the right arm. He has a history of gunshot wounds to the left side of the spinal cord. Where is the lesion located?","answers":[{"option":"Posterior spinocerebellar tract","bool":false},{"option":"Anterior spinocerebellar tract","bool":false},{"option":"Lateral corticospinal tract","bool":false},{"option":"Medial lemniscus","bool":false},{"option":"Left lateral spinothalamic tract","bool":true}],"id":32},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 50-year-old man presents to the outpatient department (OPD) with the complaint of a severe headache on the side of his head for the past 6 months. He also complains of vision loss in his left eye, blackouts, low-grade fever, and weight loss. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Brain abscess","bool":false},{"option":"Subarachnoid hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Trigeminal neuralgia","bool":false},{"option":"Temporal arteritis","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic migraine","bool":false}],"id":33},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 6-year-old male child weighing 20 kgs is brought to emergency with a history of weakness in both lower extremities, which has now progressively involved the trunk and upper limbs over a period of ten days. On examination, the sensations are intact, the tone is reduced, and reflexes are not elicited in lower limbs and +1 in upper limbs. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Guillain-Barre syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Myasthenia gravis","bool":false},{"option":"Poliomyelitis","bool":false},{"option":"Transverse myelitis","bool":false},{"option":"Traumatic neuritis","bool":false}],"id":34},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"Which spinal ligament connects two laminae and fuses with the facet joint?","answers":[{"option":"Supraspinous ligament","bool":false},{"option":"Ligamentum flavum","bool":true},{"option":"Interspinous ligament","bool":false},{"option":"Anterior longitudinal ligament","bool":false},{"option":"Posterior longitudinal ligament","bool":false}],"id":35},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 55-year-old male patient, previously diagnosed patient of diabetes mellitus type-2 and hypertension, is diagnosed with idiopathic Parkinson disease. Which of the following symptoms is not typically seen in this condition?","answers":[{"option":"Postural instability","bool":false},{"option":"Bradykinesia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypersomnia","bool":true},{"option":"Rigidity","bool":false},{"option":"Resting tremor","bool":false}],"id":36},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 29-year-old woman, 28 weeks pregnant, presents to the emergency room with persistent vomiting associated with mild to moderate diffuse headache and visual blurring for the last 2-3 weeks. Her last two pregnancies were uneventful. Her blood pressure is 150/90 mmHg with a pulse of 102 beats/min and she is afebrile. The only significant finding on a neurologic exam is significant bilateral papilledema. Routine investigations show mild leukocytosis and sodium levels of 128 mEq/l. CSF analysis is unremarkable. An MRI of the brain is unremarkable, but MR venography showed filling defects in superior sagittal and bilateral transverse venous sinuses. APLA and the rest of the investigations for the autoimmune disease were negative. What could be the most likely predisposing etiological factor in her problem in this clinical vignette?","answers":[{"option":"Tuberculous meningitis","bool":false},{"option":"Space-occupying lesion in brain","bool":false},{"option":"Eclampsia","bool":false},{"option":"Electrolyte imbalance","bool":false},{"option":"Pregnancy","bool":true}],"id":37},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 30-year-old male with a history of road traffic accident complains of severe backache and severe pain in both legs with paraparesis, urinary and fecal incontinence. A lesion of conus medullaris is suspected. Where does it terminate in adults?","answers":[{"option":"L3","bool":false},{"option":"L4","bool":false},{"option":"T12","bool":false},{"option":"L1","bool":true},{"option":"T11","bool":false}],"id":38},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of these reduces intracranial pressure?","answers":[{"option":"Keep patient lying in prone position","bool":false},{"option":"Tight cervical collar","bool":false},{"option":"Hypotonic collar","bool":false},{"option":"Keep patient sedated","bool":true},{"option":"Keep patient flat","bool":false}],"id":39},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is true regarding acute viral encephalitis?","answers":[{"option":"Glucose is raised","bool":false},{"option":"There is polymorphic leukocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Herpes RNA is detected by polymerase chain reaction (PCR)","bool":false},{"option":"Acyclovir 10 mg/kg 3 times daily for 2-3 weeks is given","bool":true},{"option":"Protein > 700 mg/dL","bool":false}],"id":40},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"An unvaccinated, 18-month-old child is brought to the clinic with left lower limb weakness. His parents say that he had fever and diarrhea two days ago, which was managed with oral rehydration salts (ORS). Which of the following investigations is the most appropriate?","answers":[{"option":"X-ray","bool":false},{"option":"Lumbar puncture","bool":false},{"option":"Stool viral antigen","bool":true},{"option":"CT spine","bool":false},{"option":"MRI","bool":false}],"id":41},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following agents is a weak anesthetic but a potent analgesic and thus is given with other inhalants?","answers":[{"option":"Etomidate","bool":false},{"option":"Midazolam","bool":false},{"option":"Halothane","bool":false},{"option":"Thiopental","bool":false},{"option":"Nitrous oxide","bool":true}],"id":42},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 39-year-old man presents to the emergency room with a traumatic spinal cord injury after a road traffic accident. Examination reveals spastic paralysis of the lower limbs. Which of the following benzodiazepines has the longest duration of action and is most suitable in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Triazolam","bool":false},{"option":"Midazolam","bool":false},{"option":"Oxazepam","bool":false},{"option":"Alprazolam","bool":false},{"option":"Diazepam","bool":true}],"id":43},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 45-year-old man presents to the emergency department after cutting his finger with a handsaw. There is a deep 2-cm long laceration on his right index finger. Bupivacaine is used as local anesthesia for suturing. What is the most common toxic adverse effect of bupivacaine?","answers":[{"option":"Ototoxicity","bool":false},{"option":"Addison's disease","bool":false},{"option":"Cardiotoxicity","bool":true},{"option":"Neurotoxicity","bool":false},{"option":"Nephrotoxicity","bool":false}],"id":44},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 33-year-old man undergoes surgery under general anesthesia. Which of the following anesthetic agents can sensitize the heart to the effects of catecholamines?","answers":[{"option":"Nitrous oxide","bool":false},{"option":"Sevoflurane","bool":false},{"option":"Enflurane","bool":false},{"option":"Isoflurane","bool":false},{"option":"Halothane","bool":true}],"id":45},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 14-year-old adolescent suddenly begins choking while having dinner and is in severe distress. What life-saving intervention must be done immediately?","answers":[{"option":"Seldingerâs technique","bool":false},{"option":"Awake fiberoptic bronchoscopy","bool":false},{"option":"Heimlich maneuver","bool":true},{"option":"Rigid bronchoscopy","bool":false},{"option":"Magill's forceps retrieval","bool":false}],"id":46},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 40-year-old male patient presents to the emergency department with complaints of high-grade fever and a headache for the last 20 days. He describes the headache as gradual in onset and moderate in intensity.  In the last 10 days, he suffered three episodes of generalized seizures followed by weakness on the right side of the body. He was recently treated for a middle ear infection last month. He has a history of diabetes mellitus, controlled with metformin twice daily. On examination, his GCS is 15/15, right-sided power 2/5 in the upper and lower right limb, and speech is slurred. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Cerebral abscess","bool":true},{"option":"Intracranial hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Middle cerebral artery occlusion","bool":false},{"option":"Meningioma","bool":false},{"option":"Meningitis","bool":false}],"id":47},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Lorazepam can be safely used as a pre-anesthetic medication in a patient undergoing liver transplantation without the fear of excessive CNS depression. What is the reason for this?","answers":[{"option":"A selective anxiolytic devoid of CNS depressant actions","bool":false},{"option":"Excreted in unchanged form","bool":false},{"option":"Actively secreted into the GI tract","bool":false},{"option":"Conjugated extra-hepatically","bool":true},{"option":"Reversible by flumazenil","bool":false}],"id":48},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 40-year-old male presents to the emergency department with complaints of vomiting and headache for the past hour. He had a road traffic accident this morning. Glasgow's consciousness score is E4M6V4. Pupils are anisocoric and reactive. CT scan reveals a biconvex hyperdensity over the right temporoparietal region along with a fracture of the temporal bone. What is the most likely source of the blood?","answers":[{"option":"Middle meningeal artery","bool":true},{"option":"Middle cerebral artery","bool":false},{"option":"Superior saggital sinus","bool":false},{"option":"Inferior petrosal sinus","bool":false},{"option":"Cortical veins","bool":false}],"id":49},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 47-year-old man with seizure disorder presents to his primary care physician for follow-up. Because of a recent exacerbation in his seizures, he has been prescribed lamotrigine. What is the most likely mechanism of action of this medication?","answers":[{"option":"Blockade of calcium channels","bool":false},{"option":"Binds to collapsing response mediator protein-2","bool":false},{"option":"Binds to GABA receptors","bool":false},{"option":"Blockade of sodium channels","bool":false},{"option":"Blockade of both sodium and calcium channels","bool":true}],"id":50},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 40-year-old married man presents to the emergency room with coarse tremors and visual hallucinations. He is unable to identify his family members. When asked about the time of the day he gives an incorrect answer. He also gives vague answers on the hospital whereabouts. Detailed history reveals regular and heavy alcohol intake for the last 10 years. On examination his pulse is 100/min, blood pressure is 150/95 mm Hg and respiratory rate of 32 per min. There are no focal neurological deficits. What is the most probable diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Delirium tremens","bool":true},{"option":"Amnestic disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Acute psychosis","bool":false},{"option":"Wernicke-Korsakoff syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Alcohol intoxication","bool":false}],"id":51},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 50-year-old male presents to the emergency room with a history of a road traffic accident with an altered level of consciousness and vomiting. The patient has abnormal flexion on pain, opens eyes on pain with no verbal response. Pupils are equal and reactive to pain stimuli. CT scan reveals a crescent hyper-density over the right frontoparietal region along with the midline shift. What is the GCS of this patient?","answers":[{"option":"9","bool":false},{"option":"7","bool":false},{"option":"8","bool":false},{"option":"5","bool":false},{"option":"6","bool":true}],"id":52},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Mitochondrial dysfunction has been implicated as a contributing factor for Parkinson disease, that is caused by mutations in genes that encode the proteins DJ-1, PINK1, and parkin. What is the mode of inheritance?","answers":[{"option":"X-linked dominant","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal recessive","bool":true},{"option":"Polygenic inheritence","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal dominant and X- linked recessive","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal dominant","bool":false}],"id":53},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 35-year-old man has sustained multiple injuries in a road traffic accident and has to undergo emergency surgery for penetrating abdominal injury. The patient is given rapid sequence general anesthesia. Which neuromuscular blocking agent is given for rapid sequence induction?","answers":[{"option":"Cis-atracurium","bool":false},{"option":"Succinylcholine","bool":true},{"option":"Vacuronium","bool":false},{"option":"Atracurium","bool":false},{"option":"Pancronium","bool":false}],"id":54},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 78-year-old man with generalized anxiety disorder and mild dementia visits his primary care physician. Physical examination of the heart, lungs, and abdomen are unremarkable. Which of the following would be the best treatment option for his generalized anxiety disorder?","answers":[{"option":"Alprazolam","bool":false},{"option":"Flumazenil","bool":false},{"option":"Temazepam","bool":false},{"option":"Triazolam","bool":false},{"option":"Buspirone","bool":true}],"id":55},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of the following anesthetics allows patients to ambulate faster and has the lowest risk of postoperative vomiting?","answers":[{"option":"Propofol","bool":true},{"option":"Etomidate","bool":false},{"option":"Remifentanil","bool":false},{"option":"Thiopental","bool":false},{"option":"Enflurane","bool":false}],"id":56},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"An elderly woman is about to undergo cardiothoracic surgery. If total intravenous anesthesia with fentanyl has been selected, then which of the following properties regarding fentanyl is the most appropriate one?","answers":[{"option":"Amnesic","bool":false},{"option":"Muscle rigidity","bool":false},{"option":"Respiratory stimulation","bool":false},{"option":"Hypertension","bool":false},{"option":"Analgesic","bool":true}],"id":57},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 45-year-old woman on antiepileptic therapy complains of acne and increased facial hair growth. She is on no other medication. Which of the following most probable antiepileptic medication is responsible for the adverse effects this woman is experiencing?","answers":[{"option":"Gabapentin","bool":false},{"option":"Phenytoin","bool":true},{"option":"Sodium valproate","bool":false},{"option":"Diazepam","bool":false},{"option":"Phenobarbitone","bool":false}],"id":58},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"An 81-year-old female comes to the neurology outpatient department with complaints of diminished facial expression (often termed masked facies), stooped posture, slowing of voluntary movement, taking progressively shortened, accelerated steps, rigidity, and a âpill-rollingâ tremor. The first gene to be identified as a cause of Parkinson's Disease encodes a-synuclein, an abundant lipid-binding protein normally associated with synapses. Mutations in alpha-synuclein take the form of point mutations and amplification of the region of chromosome 4q21 that contains the gene. What is the mode of inheritance of these genes?","answers":[{"option":"Mitochondrial inheritance","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal recessive","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal dominant","bool":true},{"option":"X-linked dominant","bool":false},{"option":"X-linked recessive","bool":false}],"id":59},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 2-year-old baby is brought to the outpatient department with complaints of progressive lower limb weakness for the last five days. He has a history of viral sore throat ten days back. On examination, reflexes are absent in both lower limbs. The child is otherwise conscious and vitally stable. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Meningitis","bool":false},{"option":"Duchenne muscular dystrophy","bool":false},{"option":"Multiple sclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Guillain-BarrÃ© syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Poliomyelitis","bool":false}],"id":60},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which drug has the capacity to reverse the effects of opioids?","answers":[{"option":"Naloxone","bool":true},{"option":"Buprenorphine","bool":false},{"option":"Disulfiram","bool":false},{"option":"Flumazenil","bool":false},{"option":"Acamprosate","bool":false}],"id":61},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Which of the following is a common variable used for a pie chart?","answers":[{"option":"Weight","bool":false},{"option":"Length","bool":false},{"option":"Gender","bool":true},{"option":"Height","bool":false},{"option":"Age","bool":false}],"id":62},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 40-year-old female presents with right-sided unilateral headaches for the past 5 months. Physical examination yields no remarkable findings. The representative gross appearance of the lesion seen on the CT scan of the head shows a dura-based mass. Surgical removal and microscopic examination show elongated cells with pale, oblong nuclei and pink cytoplasm with occasional psammoma bodies. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Metastasis","bool":false},{"option":"Astrocytoma","bool":false},{"option":"Tuberculoma","bool":false},{"option":"Ependymoma","bool":false},{"option":"Meningioma","bool":true}],"id":63},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Which of the following options include all four cardinal symptoms that are present in Parkinson disease?","answers":[{"option":"Tremor, bradycardia, rigidity, and postural instability","bool":false},{"option":"Ageusia, bradykinesia, dementia, and rigidity","bool":false},{"option":"Tremor, bradykinesia, rigidity, and postural instability","bool":true},{"option":"Tremor, bradykinesia, rigidity, and depression","bool":false},{"option":"Tremor, bradykinesia, seborrhea, and constipation","bool":false}],"id":64},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 66-year-old male complains of progressive problems with gait, speech, and hand tremors for two years. He also has occasional lightheadedness with standing and a 6-year history of impotence. He has no past medical history and takes no medications. His blood pressure is 140/84 mm Hg lying down, and 98/72 mm Hg standing, without change in pulse. Mental status is normal. He has reduced facial expression, high-pitched dysarthria, and mild anterocollis. There is no resting tremor. He has an irregular tremulousness of both hands when outstretched, worse on the right, without ataxia on finger-to-nose testing. He is bradykinetic and his gait is slow, shuffling, and unsteady. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Corticobasal degeneration","bool":false},{"option":"Multiple system atrophy-cerebellar subtype","bool":false},{"option":"Progressive supranuclear palsy","bool":false},{"option":"Parkinson's disease","bool":false},{"option":"Multiple system atrophy-parkinsonian subtype","bool":true}],"id":65},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Compared to sporadic Parkinson disease (PD), PD that is due to a dominantly inherited mutation in the a-synuclein gene is characterized by which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Less frequent cognitive decline","bool":false},{"option":"More cortical features (such as aphasia)","bool":true},{"option":"Older age at the onset of symptoms","bool":false},{"option":"The stronger association with neuromuscular junction dysfunction","bool":false},{"option":"More robust response to dopaminergic therapy","bool":false}],"id":66},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common brain tumor in children occurring in the posterior cranial fossa?","answers":[{"option":"Astrocytoma","bool":false},{"option":"Hemangioblastoma","bool":false},{"option":"Medulloblastoma","bool":true},{"option":"Central neurocytoma","bool":false},{"option":"Ependymoma","bool":false}],"id":67},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Which of the following is considered a subset of a population?","answers":[{"option":"Subjects","bool":false},{"option":"Target population","bool":false},{"option":"Subunit","bool":false},{"option":"Participants","bool":false},{"option":"Sample","bool":true}],"id":68},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"How soon after a stroke should rehabilitation be initiated?","answers":[{"option":"Immediately","bool":true},{"option":"6 hours","bool":false},{"option":"30 minutes","bool":false},{"option":"2 hours","bool":false},{"option":"1 day","bool":false}],"id":69},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Which of the disease-modifying medications used for multiple sclerosis (MS) is administered via the intramuscular route?","answers":[{"option":"Teriflunomide","bool":false},{"option":"Dimethyl fumarate","bool":false},{"option":"Fingolimod","bool":false},{"option":"Glatiramer acetate","bool":false},{"option":"Interferon-beta","bool":true}],"id":70},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"A glioma is the most common tumor in which of the following cases?","answers":[{"option":"Primary brain tumor in children","bool":false},{"option":"Primary brain tumor in the elderly","bool":false},{"option":"Primary brain tumor in adults","bool":true},{"option":"Secondary brain tumor in adults","bool":false},{"option":"Secondary brain tumor in children","bool":false}],"id":71},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"Which of the following features is a characteristic feature of upper motor neuron disease?","answers":[{"option":"Optic neuritis","bool":false},{"option":"Spastic paralysis","bool":true},{"option":"Urinary retention","bool":false},{"option":"Cyclic headaches","bool":false},{"option":"Respiratory collapse","bool":false}],"id":72},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"Lacrimation, rhinorrhea, vomiting, and nausea are symptoms indicating withdrawal of which of the following substances?","answers":[{"option":"Methamphetamine","bool":false},{"option":"Alcohol","bool":false},{"option":"Cocaine","bool":false},{"option":"Nicotine","bool":false},{"option":"Opioid","bool":true}],"id":73},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"Damage to what part of the brain leads to a condition called astereognosis?","answers":[{"option":"Parietal lobe","bool":true},{"option":"Cerebellum","bool":false},{"option":"Frontal lobe","bool":false},{"option":"Temporal lobe","bool":false},{"option":"Occipital lobe","bool":false}],"id":74},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"The primary motor cortex is located in what part of the brain?","answers":[{"option":"Cerebellum","bool":false},{"option":"Frontal lobe","bool":true},{"option":"Parietal lobe","bool":false},{"option":"Temporal lobe","bool":false},{"option":"Occipital lobe","bool":false}],"id":75},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"Grandiosity is a hallmark of which of the following conditions?","answers":[{"option":"Mania","bool":true},{"option":"Mood disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Somatoform disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Dementia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypomania","bool":false}],"id":76},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"An 18-year-old female presents to the clinic with complaints of trouble walking properly. She cannot maintain her balance and stumbles often. Upon asking her to pace the room, it is observed her gait is uneven. Which of the following is a likely etiology of her condition?","answers":[{"option":"Cerebellar dysfunction","bool":true},{"option":"Muscular dystrophy","bool":false},{"option":"Psychosomatic dysfunction","bool":false},{"option":"Neuromuscular dysfunction","bool":false},{"option":"Neurodegeneration","bool":false}],"id":77},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"Which anti-epileptic drug acts on calcium T-type channels?","answers":[{"option":"Gabapentin","bool":false},{"option":"Ethosuximide","bool":true},{"option":"Carbamezapine","bool":false},{"option":"Lamotrigine","bool":false},{"option":"Diazepam","bool":false}],"id":78},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"What artery in the vertebral artery circulation supplies the brain?","answers":[{"option":"Labyrinthine artery","bool":false},{"option":"Posterior cerebral artery","bool":true},{"option":"Posterior communicating artery","bool":false},{"option":"Anterior cerebral artery","bool":false},{"option":"Middle cerebral artery","bool":false}],"id":79},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"How long must symptoms persist to warrant a diagnosis of depression?","answers":[{"option":"3 days to 1 month","bool":false},{"option":"1- 6 months","bool":false},{"option":"> 4 weeks","bool":false},{"option":"> 6 months","bool":false},{"option":">2 weeks","bool":true}],"id":80},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"Which of the following are cardinal symptoms of depression?","answers":[{"option":"Low mood, lack of interest in activities, and lack of energy","bool":true},{"option":"Delusions, lack of insight, and hallucinations","bool":false},{"option":"Lack of insight, disorganized speech, and auditory hallucinations","bool":false},{"option":"Obsessive intrusive thoughts and repetitive behavior","bool":false},{"option":"Palpitations, paresthesias, and chest pain","bool":false}],"id":81},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"A 71-year-old male presents to the emergency room with complaints of slurring speech and trouble understanding those around him. He is unable to comprehend simple commands given by the doctor and cannot vocalize his problems. What parts of the brain are damaged in this man?","answers":[{"option":"Broadman's area 41 and 42","bool":false},{"option":"Prefrontal cortex and Broadman area 6","bool":false},{"option":"Broca's and Wernicke's area","bool":true},{"option":"Premotor cortex and Broadman area 4","bool":false},{"option":"Primary motor cortex and Broadman area 8","bool":false}],"id":82},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"A 13-year-old female presents to the clinic with complaints of trouble walking. She is asked to stand still but begins to sway. A Romberg's test is conducted and the patient is asked to close her eyes while standing and the swaying worsens. Which of the following is a likely cause of her walking problems?","answers":[{"option":"Muscular dystrophy","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebellar dysfunction","bool":true},{"option":"Cerebral lesions","bool":false},{"option":"Neurodegeneration","bool":false},{"option":"Lower motor neuron lesions","bool":false}],"id":83},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"What antibodies are involved in myasthenia gravis?","answers":[{"option":"Anti-cyclic citrullinated polypeptide","bool":false},{"option":"Anticardiolipin antibodies","bool":false},{"option":"Acetylcholine receptor antibodies","bool":true},{"option":"Anti-double stranded DNA","bool":false},{"option":"Anti-smooth muscle antibodies","bool":false}],"id":84},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"Negri bodies are a histopathological finding in which of the following conditions?","answers":[{"option":"Acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS)","bool":false},{"option":"Poliomyelitis","bool":false},{"option":"Rabies","bool":true},{"option":"Herpes","bool":false},{"option":"Duchenne muscular dystrophy","bool":false}],"id":85},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"Acute bacterial meningitis will have which of the following findings?","answers":[{"option":"B cell lymphocytosis","bool":false},{"option":"Neutrophilia","bool":true},{"option":"Raised plasma cells","bool":false},{"option":"Basophilia","bool":false},{"option":"Eosinophilia","bool":false}],"id":86},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"Which of the following cells are involved in the pathophysiology of neurosarcoidosis?","answers":[{"option":"T-helper 2 cell (Th2)","bool":false},{"option":"Cytotoxic killer T-cells","bool":false},{"option":"B cells","bool":false},{"option":"T-helper 1 cell (Th1)","bool":true},{"option":"Antigen presenting cells (APCs)","bool":false}],"id":87},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"What is the most common causative organism of meningitis in young adults?","answers":[{"option":"Neisseria meningitidis","bool":true},{"option":"Streptococcus pneumoniae","bool":false},{"option":"Streptococcus pyogenes","bool":false},{"option":"Escherichia coli","bool":false},{"option":"Listeria monocytogenes","bool":false}],"id":88},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"Which of the following rarely occurs in Friedreich's ataxia?","answers":[{"option":"Patient walks without support","bool":true},{"option":"Loss of temperature sensation","bool":false},{"option":"Areflexia","bool":false},{"option":"Absent extensor plantar reflex","bool":false},{"option":"Pes cavus","bool":false}],"id":89},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"Which of the following best describes the difference between Arnold Chiari I and II malformations?","answers":[{"option":"Type II presents in adolescence while type I presents in infancy","bool":false},{"option":"Type I has respiratory distress and type II does not","bool":false},{"option":"Type I is less severe than type II","bool":true},{"option":"Type I is associated with meningomyelocele and type II is not","bool":false},{"option":"Type II is often a silent abnormality but type I is not","bool":false}],"id":90},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"Locked-in syndrome occurs due to which of the following causes?","answers":[{"option":"Rupture of middle meningeal artery","bool":false},{"option":"Occlusion of posterior cerebral artery","bool":false},{"option":"Rupture of the bridging cerebral veins","bool":false},{"option":"Basilar pontine hemorrhage","bool":true},{"option":"Occlusion of the anterior cerebral artery","bool":false}],"id":91},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"Which of the following is a reason for the rapid action of benzodiazepine?","answers":[{"option":"Large size","bool":false},{"option":"Lipophilicity","bool":true},{"option":"Lipophobicity","bool":false},{"option":"Hydrophobicity","bool":false},{"option":"Hydrophilicity","bool":false}],"id":92},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"A 40-year-old male presents with a disconjugate gaze such that when looking to the left, his left eye moves while his right eye stays fixed. A lesion in which of the following sites is most likely responsible for this presentation?","answers":[{"option":"Left pons","bool":false},{"option":"Left cerebral hemisphere","bool":false},{"option":"Right cerebral hemisphere","bool":false},{"option":"Right pons","bool":true},{"option":"Midbrain","bool":false}],"id":93},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2016"],"question":"Damage to what structure in the brain can lead to coma or lack of awareness of one's surroundings?","answers":[{"option":"Medulla oblongata","bool":false},{"option":"Paraventricular nucleus","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebellum","bool":false},{"option":"Broca's area","bool":false},{"option":"Reticular activating system","bool":true}],"id":94},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"In which of the following ways does HIV encephalitis cause brain damage?","answers":[{"option":"Viral toxins and cytokines","bool":false},{"option":"CNS lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"All of these","bool":true},{"option":"Gradual decline in cognitive function","bool":false},{"option":"Opportunistic infections","bool":false}],"id":95},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"Which of these conditions is the greatest risk factor for suicide?","answers":[{"option":"Female gender","bool":false},{"option":"Puerperium","bool":false},{"option":"Depression","bool":true},{"option":"Obsessive-compulsive disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Parkinson's disease","bool":false}],"id":96},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"Which of these can prevent complications in Streptococcus pneumoniae meningitis if given at an early stage?","answers":[{"option":"Corticosteroids","bool":true},{"option":"Antibiotics","bool":false},{"option":"Anti-epileptic drugs","bool":false},{"option":"Hormonal therapy","bool":false},{"option":"IV fluids","bool":false}],"id":97},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"Which of these is a microglial marker?","answers":[{"option":"CD8","bool":false},{"option":"CD68","bool":true},{"option":"CD21","bool":false},{"option":"CD40","bool":false},{"option":"PTEN","bool":false}],"id":98},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"Coma involves which part of the brain?","answers":[{"option":"Pituitary gland","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebellum","bool":false},{"option":"Hippocampus","bool":false},{"option":"Hypothalamus","bool":false},{"option":"Diencephalon","bool":true}],"id":99},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"What is the appropriate management for meningocele?","answers":[{"option":"Laminectomy","bool":false},{"option":"No treatment","bool":false},{"option":"Repair within 48-72 hours","bool":true},{"option":"Laminotomy","bool":false},{"option":"Laminectomy with shunting","bool":false}],"id":100},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"What is the most common complication of bacterial meningitis?","answers":[{"option":"Epilepsy","bool":false},{"option":"Cognitive impairment","bool":false},{"option":"Hydrocephalus","bool":false},{"option":"Abscess","bool":false},{"option":"Hearing loss","bool":true}],"id":101},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"What is the most common peripheral neuropathy seen in diabetes mellitus?","answers":[{"option":"Optic neuritis","bool":false},{"option":"Sensory","bool":false},{"option":"Focal","bool":false},{"option":"Mononeuritis multiplex","bool":false},{"option":"Polyneuropathy","bool":true}],"id":102},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"Which of these is a cause of reversible dementia?","answers":[{"option":"Extracellular deposition of amyloid protein","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased dendritic branching","bool":false},{"option":"Intercellular neurofibrillary tangles","bool":false},{"option":"Cortical lewy bodies","bool":false},{"option":"Alcohol consumption","bool":true}],"id":103},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"What investigation is used to diagnose a child with cerebral palsy?","answers":[{"option":"X-ray Water's view","bool":false},{"option":"Magnetic resonance imaging","bool":true},{"option":"Cognitive function testing","bool":false},{"option":"Cranial ultrasonography","bool":false},{"option":"Head CT with contrast","bool":false}],"id":104},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"What type of speech is observed in patients with Parkinson disease?","answers":[{"option":"Sing-song","bool":false},{"option":"Disorganized (word salad)","bool":false},{"option":"Difficult to interpret","bool":false},{"option":"Soft and rapid","bool":true},{"option":"Flight of ideas","bool":false}],"id":105},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"Which of these is the cause of congenital cerebral palsy in a child?","answers":[{"option":"Premature birth","bool":true},{"option":"Maternal-fetal Rh incompatibility","bool":false},{"option":"Congenital infection","bool":false},{"option":"Genetic aberration","bool":false},{"option":"Trauma","bool":false}],"id":106},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"What is the most common site for metastasis of a tumor?","answers":[{"option":"Lung","bool":true},{"option":"Intestines","bool":false},{"option":"Kidney","bool":false},{"option":"Colon","bool":false},{"option":"Breast","bool":false}],"id":107},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"What is the most common and preventable cause of fetal and neonatal brain damage?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin D deficinecy","bool":false},{"option":"Genetic abberation","bool":false},{"option":"Trauma","bool":false},{"option":"Folic acid deficiency","bool":true},{"option":"Accumulation of bilirubin","bool":false}],"id":108},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"What is the most common histopathological finding in multiple sclerosis (MS)?","answers":[{"option":"Neurofibrillary tangles","bool":false},{"option":"Gliosis","bool":false},{"option":"Demyelinated plaques","bool":true},{"option":"Neurodegeneration","bool":false},{"option":"Lewy body accumulation","bool":false}],"id":109},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"Which of the following is an indication for migraine prophylaxis?","answers":[{"option":"Satisfactory response to acute therapy","bool":false},{"option":"Severe unilateral orbital pain","bool":false},{"option":"One attack per month","bool":false},{"option":"Non-pulsating type of headache","bool":false},{"option":"Two or more attacks per month","bool":true}],"id":110},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"Which of these is given to pregnant women in order to prevent brain damage and psychomotor developmental issues in the fetus?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin D","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12","bool":false},{"option":"Folic acid","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin C","bool":false},{"option":"Calcium","bool":false}],"id":111},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"Ketamine causes dissociative anesthesia. Which of these is not associated with dissociative anesthesia caused by ketamine?","answers":[{"option":"Sedation","bool":false},{"option":"Post-anesthesia confusion","bool":false},{"option":"Vivid dreams","bool":false},{"option":"Analog of phencyclidine (PCP)","bool":false},{"option":"Bronchoconstriction","bool":true}],"id":112},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"Anosmia is caused by damage to which nerve?","answers":[{"option":"Cranial nerve III","bool":false},{"option":"Cranial nerve V","bool":false},{"option":"Cranial nerve II","bool":false},{"option":"Cranial nerve I","bool":true},{"option":"Cranial nerve IV","bool":false}],"id":113},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"What does a lesion in the right optic tract cause?","answers":[{"option":"Monoccular blindness","bool":false},{"option":"Right homonymous hemianopia","bool":false},{"option":"Complete blindness","bool":false},{"option":"Left homonymous hemianopia","bool":true},{"option":"Heteronymous hemianopia","bool":false}],"id":114},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"Which modality affects T1 and T2?","answers":[{"option":"Repetition time (TR) and time to echo (TE)","bool":true},{"option":"Matrix size","bool":false},{"option":"Field of view","bool":false},{"option":"Number of excitations (NEX)","bool":false},{"option":"Slice thickness","bool":false}],"id":115},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"What is the pathophysiology of depressive disorder?","answers":[{"option":"Loss of neurons","bool":false},{"option":"Alcohol consumption","bool":false},{"option":"Intercellular neurofibrillary tangles","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased serotonin","bool":true},{"option":"Lewy body dementia","bool":false}],"id":116},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"Which of these is the most important risk factor for suicide worldwide?","answers":[{"option":"Drug addiction","bool":false},{"option":"Prior suicide attempt","bool":true},{"option":"Work-related stress","bool":false},{"option":"Relationship stress","bool":false},{"option":"Alcohol dependence","bool":false}],"id":117},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"What is the cause of pupil-sparing oculomotor nerve palsy?","answers":[{"option":"Lewy body dementia","bool":false},{"option":"Posterior communicating artery aneurysm","bool":false},{"option":"Diabetes mellitus","bool":true},{"option":"Depressive disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Genetic aberration","bool":false}],"id":118},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2017"],"question":"A 6-month-old child is brought by his parents to the outpatient department and he presents with recurrent seizures, infantile spasms, and mental retardation. Upon performing an interictal electroencephalogram (EEG), a pattern of hypsarrhythmia is obtained. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Infantile neuroaxonal dystrophy (INAD)","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebral palsy","bool":false},{"option":"Stroke","bool":false},{"option":"Encephalopathy","bool":false},{"option":"West syndrome","bool":true}],"id":119},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of the following disorders is characterized by weakness in lower limbs and tongue, and dysphagia?","answers":[{"option":"Myasthenia gravis","bool":false},{"option":"Multiple sclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Kennedy disease","bool":true},{"option":"Duchenne muscular dystrophy","bool":false}],"id":120},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of the following neoplasms is characterized by a whorled cluster of cells without an obvious cell membrane?","answers":[{"option":"Syncytial meningioma","bool":true},{"option":"Schwannoma","bool":false},{"option":"Ependymoma","bool":false},{"option":"Fibroblastic meningioma","bool":false},{"option":"Medulloblastoma","bool":false}],"id":121},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is not a sign of motor neuron disease?","answers":[{"option":"Fasciculations","bool":false},{"option":"Muscle wasting","bool":false},{"option":"Sensory loss","bool":true},{"option":"Brisk reflexes","bool":false},{"option":"Spasticity","bool":false}],"id":122},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of the following inhaled anesthetics is the least hepatotoxic?","answers":[{"option":"Methoxyflurane","bool":false},{"option":"Enflurane","bool":false},{"option":"Halothane","bool":false},{"option":"Sevoflurane","bool":false},{"option":"Isoflurane","bool":true}],"id":123},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A 60-year-old male with a past medical history of schizophrenia controlled by antipsychotics presents to the emergency department with complaints of high-grade fever, sweating, shortness of breath, and muscle stiffness. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Neuroleptic malignant syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Delirium tremens","bool":false},{"option":"Serotonin syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Acute dystonia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypertensive crisis","bool":false}],"id":124},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which cranial nerve is an extension of the brain tract?","answers":[{"option":"Fourth cranial nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Fifth cranial nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Third cranial nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Second cranial nerve","bool":true},{"option":"First cranial nerve","bool":false}],"id":125},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"According to the International Classification of Diseases 10th Revision (ICD-10) classification, which of the following is the most typical complaint seen in depression?","answers":[{"option":"Diminished appetite","bool":false},{"option":"Reduced self-esteem and self-confidence","bool":false},{"option":"Ideas of guilt and unworthiness","bool":false},{"option":"Loss of interest or pleasure in activities","bool":true},{"option":"Disturbed sleep","bool":false}],"id":126},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which cells are responsible for the myelination of central nervous system (CNS) axons?","answers":[{"option":"Schwann cells","bool":false},{"option":"Oligodendrocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Ependymal cells","bool":false},{"option":"Astrocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Glial cells","bool":false}],"id":127},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A 36-year-old man with no relevant medical history presents to the emergency department with complaints of abnormal tongue motility, which causes difficulty in chewing food. The neurological examination reveals right-sided deviation of the tongue; the patient has difficulty moving it further to the right. Which cranial nerve is most likely damaged in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Trigeminal","bool":false},{"option":"Facial","bool":false},{"option":"Hypoglossal","bool":true},{"option":"Vagus","bool":false},{"option":"Glossopharyngeal","bool":false}],"id":128},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A 17-year-old boy is brought to the outpatient department (OPD) by his mother. She reports that her son hears voices that are not real, and faces problems making and keeping friends over the past 6 months. She also mentions how he has been feeling low, stopped taking an interest in his hobbies, and generally lazes about stating he no longer has the energy to carry out simple tasks. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Personality disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Bipolar disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Delusional disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Depressive disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Schizoaffective disorder","bool":true}],"id":129},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A crescent-shaped lesion on computed tomography (CT) is a hallmark of which type of hemorrhage?","answers":[{"option":"Subarachnoid hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Epidural hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Subdural hemorrhage","bool":true},{"option":"Intracerebral hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Deep parenchymal hemorrhage","bool":false}],"id":130},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A lesion in the medial lemniscus would result in which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Ipsilateral loss of light touch and pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Ipsilateral loss of discriminative touch","bool":false},{"option":"Contralateral loss of fine touch, vibration, and proprioception","bool":true},{"option":"Contralateral loss of pain and temperature","bool":false},{"option":"Ipsilateral loss of fine touch, vibration, and proprioception","bool":false}],"id":131},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A 35-year-old male presents to the emergency department with vision loss. He is unable to see anything in his temporal field of vision from both eyes. A lesion of the visual pathway is suspected. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Homonymous hemianopia","bool":false},{"option":"Unihedral hemianopia","bool":false},{"option":"Bitemporal hemianopia","bool":true},{"option":"Trihedral hemianopia","bool":false},{"option":"Unilateral hemianopia","bool":false}],"id":132},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A 10-year-old boy presents to the clinic with complaints of headache and papilledema. The magnetic resonance imaging of the head reveals a mass in the fourth ventricle. Which of the following neoplasms does he most likely have?","answers":[{"option":"Pilocytic astrocytoma","bool":false},{"option":"Meningioma","bool":false},{"option":"Oligodendroglioma","bool":false},{"option":"Ependymoma","bool":true},{"option":"Glioblastoma","bool":false}],"id":133},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A 7-year-old girl is brought to the outpatient department by her mother because she is unable to lift her arms to comb her hair. Laboratory analysis shows the presence of antinuclear antibodies (ANA) and serum creatinine kinase (CK) levels are raised. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Duchenne muscular dystrophy","bool":false},{"option":"Dermatomyositis","bool":false},{"option":"Myasthenia gravis","bool":false},{"option":"Scleroderma","bool":false},{"option":"Polymyositis","bool":true}],"id":134},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A 40-year-old woman undergoes a parotidectomy and the facial nerve is damaged during the procedure. Examination findings in this patient would most likely be summarized as which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Complete facial weakness on the ipsilateral side","bool":true},{"option":"No facial weakness but ptosis is present","bool":false},{"option":"Inability to protrude the tongue","bool":false},{"option":"Weakness of the contralateral face with the presence of forehead movement","bool":false},{"option":"Weakness of the ipsilateral face movements with preservation of eye closing","bool":false}],"id":135},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A 43-year-old female presents to the emergency room with complaints of fever, worsening headache, and neck stiffness for 4 days. The cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) detailed report shows neutrophilia, raised protein, and low glucose levels. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Acute bacterial meningitis","bool":true},{"option":"Fungal meningitis","bool":false},{"option":"Brain abscess","bool":false},{"option":"Viral meningitis","bool":false},{"option":"Encephalitis","bool":false}],"id":136},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is caused by intoxication with lysergic acid diethylamide (LSD)?","answers":[{"option":"Malar rash","bool":false},{"option":"Hypotension","bool":false},{"option":"Bradycardia","bool":false},{"option":"Piloerection","bool":true},{"option":"Weight gain","bool":false}],"id":137},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which enzyme produces amyloid beta-peptide (AÎ²) through the proteolytic processing of the transmembrane glycoprotein?","answers":[{"option":"Iduronate 2-sulfatase","bool":false},{"option":"Î²- and Î³-secretases","bool":true},{"option":"Ubiquitin ligase","bool":false},{"option":"Choline acetyltransferase (CAT)","bool":false},{"option":"Glutamic acid decarboxylase (GAD)","bool":false}],"id":138},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"What is the mechanism of action of tolcapone?","answers":[{"option":"N-methyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) receptor antagonist","bool":false},{"option":"Gamma-aminobutyric acid (GABA) receptor agonist","bool":false},{"option":"Acetylcholinesterase enzyme (AChE) inhibitor","bool":false},{"option":"Catechol-O-methyl transferase (COMT) inhibitor","bool":true},{"option":"Monoamine oxidase (MAO) inhibitor","bool":false}],"id":139},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A 49-year-old man presents to the outpatient department (OPD) with a complaint of the drooping left eyelid. On examination, the eyeball deviates downward laterally, and the pupil is dilated and unresponsive to light. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Ischemic atrophy of ocular muscles","bool":false},{"option":"Diabetic retinopathy","bool":false},{"option":"Oculomotor nerve palsy","bool":true},{"option":"Myasthenia gravis","bool":false},{"option":"Acquired exotropia","bool":false}],"id":140},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is not a risk factor for carpal tunnel syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"Smoking","bool":false},{"option":"Hypothyroidism","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperthyroidism","bool":true},{"option":"Rheumatoid arthritis","bool":false},{"option":"Pregnancy","bool":false}],"id":141},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A 15-year-old male presents with the complaint of muscle twitching in arms and legs on waking up for the past 2-3 months. Which of the following would be your first differential diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Progressive myoclonic epilepsy","bool":false},{"option":"Childhood absence epilepsy","bool":false},{"option":"Hypocalcemic tetany","bool":false},{"option":"Juvenile absence epilepsy","bool":false},{"option":"Juvenile myoclonic epilepsy","bool":true}],"id":142},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A patient presents to the outpatient department (OPD) with weakness in both lower limbs. His upper limb function is normal and abdominal reflexes are absent. Which part of the spine should be assessed by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI)?","answers":[{"option":"T6-T12","bool":false},{"option":"L1-L4","bool":false},{"option":"C1-C4","bool":false},{"option":"T6-T11","bool":true},{"option":"C5-C8","bool":false}],"id":143},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A patient presents to the outpatient department (OPD) with symptoms of excessive cholinergic activity. He is a diagnosed case of myasthenia gravis for which he is taking pyridostigmine. Which of the following will confirm a cholinergic crisis?","answers":[{"option":"Cessation of pyridostigmine","bool":false},{"option":"Small dose of edrophonium","bool":true},{"option":"Urine toxicology screen","bool":false},{"option":"Intravenous immunoglobulin","bool":false},{"option":"Administration of atropine","bool":false}],"id":144},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which nerve root allows elbow extension?","answers":[{"option":"C7","bool":true},{"option":"C8","bool":false},{"option":"C6","bool":false},{"option":"T1","bool":false},{"option":"C5","bool":false}],"id":145},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which one of the following sensorimotor modalities is preserved in facial nerve lesions?","answers":[{"option":"Facial expressions","bool":false},{"option":"Taste in anterior tongue","bool":false},{"option":"Lacrimation","bool":false},{"option":"Taste from posterior tongue","bool":true},{"option":"Taste from hard and soft palates","bool":false}],"id":146},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Neural tube defects are due to a defect in which stage?","answers":[{"option":"Induction","bool":false},{"option":"Neurulation","bool":true},{"option":"Gastrulation","bool":false},{"option":"Fertilization","bool":false},{"option":"Morulation","bool":false}],"id":147},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is used for the treatment of inflammatory demyelinating polyneuropathy?","answers":[{"option":"Diclofenac","bool":false},{"option":"Azathioprine","bool":false},{"option":"Cephalosporins","bool":false},{"option":"Pyridostigmine","bool":false},{"option":"Methylprednisolone","bool":true}],"id":148},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"What is the mechanism of action of benzodiazepines?","answers":[{"option":"Blocks T-Type Ca 2+ channels in thalamic neurons","bool":false},{"option":"Facilitates GABA-A action by increasing frequency of Cl- channel opening","bool":true},{"option":"Blocks axonal Na+ channels","bool":false},{"option":"Blocks AMPA glutamate receptors","bool":false},{"option":"Enhances K+ channels activity","bool":false}],"id":149},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A 3-year-old boy with a reported intelligence quotient (IQ) of 45 is brought to the clinic. His parents complain that he is unable to communicate with them. What is his degree of intellectual disability?","answers":[{"option":"Mild","bool":false},{"option":"Profound","bool":false},{"option":"Moderate","bool":true},{"option":"Normal for age","bool":false},{"option":"Severe","bool":false}],"id":150},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"What is the global burden of neuropsychiatric disorders?","answers":[{"option":"10%","bool":false},{"option":"1%","bool":false},{"option":"2%","bool":true},{"option":"5%","bool":false},{"option":"7%","bool":false}],"id":151},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"What is the standard intravenous dose of recombinant plasminogen tissue activator in ischemic stroke patients?","answers":[{"option":"0.5 mg/kg","bool":false},{"option":"1 mg/kg","bool":false},{"option":"0.7 mg/kg","bool":false},{"option":"0.3 mg/kg","bool":false},{"option":"0.9 mg/kg","bool":true}],"id":152},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of these is not a common cause of non-compressive myelopathy?","answers":[{"option":"Vitamin B12","bool":false},{"option":"Spinal artery occlusion","bool":false},{"option":"Metastasis","bool":true},{"option":"Transverse myelitis","bool":false},{"option":"Radiation","bool":false}],"id":153},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A 45-year-old male patient presents to the emergency department with a fever and an altered level of consciousness. He also has a low score on the Glasgow coma scale and complains of neck rigidity. What investigations should be performed?","answers":[{"option":"Magnetic resonance imaging followed by a lumbar puncture","bool":false},{"option":"Only lumbar puncture","bool":false},{"option":"Computed tomography  followed by lumbar puncture","bool":true},{"option":"Lumbar puncture  followed by computed tomography","bool":false},{"option":"Lumbar puncture followed by magnetic resonance imaging","bool":false}],"id":154},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A 45-year-old male patient presents to the emergency department with an altered level of consciousness, and fever. His brother reports he has had a fever and neck stiffness for 2 days along with a rash on his arms and legs. What is the most probable diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Viral encephalitis","bool":false},{"option":"Subarachnoid hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Meningocele","bool":false},{"option":"Meningoccocal meningitis","bool":true},{"option":"Subdural hemorrhage","bool":false}],"id":155},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A patient starts using a drug that is prescribed to him and develops Parkinson-like features. Which drug is he most probably using?","answers":[{"option":"Carbamazepine","bool":false},{"option":"Haloperidol","bool":true},{"option":"Olanzapine","bool":false},{"option":"Clozapine","bool":false},{"option":"Zolpidem","bool":false}],"id":156},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which drug is used to treat neuroleptic malignant syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"Dantrolene","bool":true},{"option":"Haloperidol","bool":false},{"option":"Clozapine","bool":false},{"option":"Zolpidem","bool":false},{"option":"Olanzapine","bool":false}],"id":157},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of these best defines hyperactivity?","answers":[{"option":"Low mood","bool":false},{"option":"Prolonged activity","bool":false},{"option":"Increased movement","bool":true},{"option":"Loss of attention","bool":false},{"option":"Loss of sensation","bool":false}],"id":158},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"What type of schizophrenia shows spasticity?","answers":[{"option":"Paranoid","bool":false},{"option":"Hebephrenic","bool":false},{"option":"Catatonic","bool":true},{"option":"Residual","bool":false},{"option":"Undifferentiated","bool":false}],"id":159},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of the following causes schizophrenia?","answers":[{"option":"Increased dopamine","bool":true},{"option":"Decreased dopamine","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased norepinephrine","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased serotonin","bool":false},{"option":"Increased glutamine","bool":false}],"id":160},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is a true statement about neurotransmitters?","answers":[{"option":"All of these","bool":false},{"option":"Adenosine receptors are blocked by caffeine","bool":true},{"option":"Acetylcholine is involved in inhibition","bool":false},{"option":"GABA is involved in excitation","bool":false},{"option":"Acetylcholine is involved in motor and sensory system","bool":false}],"id":161},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of these is the lethal dose of caffeine?","answers":[{"option":"50 ug","bool":false},{"option":"70 ug","bool":false},{"option":"100 ug","bool":true},{"option":"80 ug","bool":false},{"option":"30 ug","bool":false}],"id":162},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Brain metastasis is a result of cancers originating in which of the following organs?","answers":[{"option":"Lymph nodes","bool":false},{"option":"Kidneys","bool":false},{"option":"Spleen","bool":false},{"option":"Lungs","bool":true},{"option":"Skin","bool":false}],"id":163},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which brain tumor is most likely to occur in a patient with acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS) after a transplant?","answers":[{"option":"Primary CNS lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"Haemangioblastoma","bool":false},{"option":"Astrocytoma","bool":false},{"option":"Oligodendroglioma","bool":false},{"option":"Pituitary adenoma","bool":false}],"id":164},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"What is the most alarming complication of local anesthetic administration?","answers":[{"option":"Lung infections","bool":false},{"option":"Altered mental status with convulsions","bool":false},{"option":"Muscle spasms and rigidity","bool":false},{"option":"Altered mental status and cardiovascular instability","bool":true},{"option":"Respiratory depression with altered mental status","bool":false}],"id":165},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A woman is suspected to have a lumbar disc herniation. Why is magnetic resonance imagining recommended over computed tomography scan?","answers":[{"option":"It gives better view of bone","bool":false},{"option":"It is less time consuming","bool":false},{"option":"It is a quicker procedure","bool":false},{"option":"It is less expensive","bool":false},{"option":"It gives better soft tissue visualization","bool":true}],"id":166},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common sign of anterior territory circulation stroke?","answers":[{"option":"Diplopia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemiparesis","bool":true},{"option":"Vomitting","bool":false},{"option":"Ataxia","bool":false},{"option":"Strabismus","bool":false}],"id":167},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A patient forgets his way to the mosque. What is the best clinical test to assess his mental condition?","answers":[{"option":"Zung self-rating depression scale","bool":false},{"option":"Beck depression inventory (BDI)","bool":false},{"option":"Mental state examination","bool":true},{"option":"Penn state worry questionnaire","bool":false},{"option":"Patient health questionnaire-9 (PHQ-9)","bool":false}],"id":168},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of these is not a part of the visual dysfunction pathway?","answers":[{"option":"Bitemporal hemianopia","bool":false},{"option":"Optic neuritis","bool":false},{"option":"Diplopia","bool":true},{"option":"Homonymous hemianopia","bool":false},{"option":"Color blindness","bool":false}],"id":169},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"How many nuclei of the trigeminal nerve are present in the brain?","answers":[{"option":"2","bool":false},{"option":"5","bool":false},{"option":"4","bool":true},{"option":"6","bool":false},{"option":"3","bool":false}],"id":170},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Meningococcal meningitis is most commonly seen in which of the following groups?","answers":[{"option":"Alcoholics","bool":false},{"option":"Children","bool":false},{"option":"Diabetics","bool":false},{"option":"Elderly","bool":false},{"option":"Adults","bool":true}],"id":171},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"What is the most prevalent neurological disorder?","answers":[{"option":"Epilepsy","bool":false},{"option":"Brain tumor","bool":false},{"option":"Migraine","bool":false},{"option":"Stroke","bool":true},{"option":"Meningitis","bool":false}],"id":172},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"What is the most common cause of stroke?","answers":[{"option":"Infection","bool":false},{"option":"Edema","bool":false},{"option":"Infarction","bool":true},{"option":"Trauma","bool":false},{"option":"Hemorrhage","bool":false}],"id":173},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A 40-year-old patient with Huntington's disease comes to a psychiatrist for the treatment of his psychosis. What drug will be prescribed to treat his mental condition?","answers":[{"option":"Sulpiride","bool":false},{"option":"Dantrolene","bool":false},{"option":"Fluoxetine","bool":false},{"option":"Risperidone","bool":true},{"option":"Tetrabenzine","bool":false}],"id":174},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Why is computed tomography opted for instead of magnetic resonance imaging for the imagining of brain lesions?","answers":[{"option":"More suitable for highly unstable patient","bool":false},{"option":"Better demonstration of intercranial hemorrhage","bool":true},{"option":"Cost-effective","bool":false},{"option":"Shows the extent of infarction","bool":false},{"option":"Time-saving","bool":false}],"id":175},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of these is clasically seen in anxiety disorders?","answers":[{"option":"Aggressive behavior","bool":false},{"option":"Worrying thoughts","bool":true},{"option":"Being suspicious of everyone","bool":false},{"option":"Low moods","bool":false},{"option":"Talking a lot","bool":false}],"id":176},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"If a person survives after a suicide attempt, what is it called?","answers":[{"option":"Self-harm","bool":false},{"option":"Attempted suicide","bool":true},{"option":"Suicidal tendencies","bool":false},{"option":"Para suicide","bool":false},{"option":"Attempted homicide","bool":false}],"id":177},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of these is the complete transection cutting of a nerve?","answers":[{"option":"Stroke","bool":false},{"option":"Infarction","bool":false},{"option":"Axonotmesis","bool":false},{"option":"Neurotmesis","bool":true},{"option":"Neurapraxia","bool":false}],"id":178},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"A transtentorial herniation causes hemorrhage at which site?","answers":[{"option":"Hindbrain","bool":false},{"option":"Pons","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebral cortex","bool":false},{"option":"Brainstem","bool":true},{"option":"Spinal cord","bool":false}],"id":179},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2018"],"question":"Which of these is true about caffeine?","answers":[{"option":"Mild diuretic","bool":true},{"option":"Potent stimulant","bool":false},{"option":"Causes osteoporosis","bool":false},{"option":"Hydration","bool":false},{"option":"Lethal at low doses","bool":false}],"id":180},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which of the following statements is true regarding post-dural puncture headache?","answers":[{"option":"It is relieved within 12 hours by an epidural blood patch","bool":false},{"option":"It is noted immediately","bool":false},{"option":"It is aggravated by the supine position","bool":false},{"option":"It is most frequent with large-bore needles","bool":true},{"option":"It is not lessened by the use of a Whitacre needle as compared to a Quincke needle","bool":false}],"id":181},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is not an indication for a X-ray?","answers":[{"option":"Patellar fracture","bool":false},{"option":"Skull fracture","bool":false},{"option":"Detection of calcification in brain","bool":true},{"option":"Palpable head vertex injury","bool":false},{"option":"Headache","bool":false}],"id":182},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"A 45-year-old man presents to the clinic with complaints of a chronic, dull headache, that feels like a tight band around his head. His headache is associated with neck stiffness but there is no association with nausea, vomiting, or photophobia. He has had this complaint for one year now. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Classic migraine","bool":false},{"option":"Cluster headache","bool":false},{"option":"Trigeminal neuralgia","bool":false},{"option":"Tension headache","bool":true},{"option":"Giant cell arteritis","bool":false}],"id":183},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"A couple has brought their 6-year-old child to the outpatient department with the complaint that he has been remaining inattentive in class and seems to go blank and stare in space. There is no other significant past medical history. What is the going to be the most likely finding on electroencephalography (EEG)?","answers":[{"option":"Slow wave pattern","bool":false},{"option":"3 Hz spike-and-wave","bool":true},{"option":"Hypsarrhythmia","bool":false},{"option":"Centrotemporal spikes","bool":false},{"option":"High voltage discharges","bool":false}],"id":184},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which of the following conditions is a neurodegenerative disease?","answers":[{"option":"Epilepsy","bool":false},{"option":"Subarachnoid hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Multiple sclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Poliomyelitis","bool":false},{"option":"Alzheimer disease","bool":true}],"id":185},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is a common infectious agent found in children after contracting an upper respiratory tract infection?","answers":[{"option":"Haemophilus influenzae","bool":true},{"option":"Escherichia coli","bool":false},{"option":"Streptococcus pneumoniae","bool":false},{"option":"Staphylococcus aureus","bool":false},{"option":"Neisseria meningitidis","bool":false}],"id":186},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"A 45-year-old male presented to the outpatient department with a painful vesicular rash on his face. He is diagnosed as a case of shingles. What is the most common causative organism for this condition?","answers":[{"option":"Varicella zoster virus (VZV)","bool":true},{"option":"Poxvirus","bool":false},{"option":"Cytomegalovirus","bool":false},{"option":"Herpes simplex virus (HSV)","bool":false},{"option":"Poliovirus","bool":false}],"id":187},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the most likely to be the earliest finding in Parkinson disease?","answers":[{"option":"Bradykinesia","bool":false},{"option":"Ataxic gait","bool":false},{"option":"Rigidity","bool":false},{"option":"Tremors","bool":true},{"option":"Clonus","bool":false}],"id":188},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which of the following best describes pleocytosis in the cerebrospinal fluid?","answers":[{"option":"Presence of erythrocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Increase in lymphocyte count","bool":true},{"option":"Decrease in glucose levels","bool":false},{"option":"Increase in protein levels","bool":false},{"option":"Increase in glucose levels","bool":false}],"id":189},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Damage to which area of the brain can cause alexia and agraphia?","answers":[{"option":"Cingulate gyrus","bool":false},{"option":"Broca","bool":false},{"option":"Prefrontal cortex","bool":false},{"option":"Frontal cortex","bool":false},{"option":"Left angular gyrus","bool":true}],"id":190},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common type of hallucination in schizophrenia?","answers":[{"option":"Auditory","bool":true},{"option":"Visual","bool":false},{"option":"Tactile","bool":false},{"option":"Gustatory","bool":false},{"option":"Hypnagogic","bool":false}],"id":191},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is true regarding Guillain-BarrÃ© syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"It is an infective polyneuropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Relapsing and remitting course","bool":false},{"option":"Miller Fisher syndrome is a common variant","bool":false},{"option":"Tendon reflexes are preserved","bool":false},{"option":"Acute demyelinating inflammatory polyneuropathy","bool":true}],"id":192},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Sensorineural deafness is an integral part of which disease?","answers":[{"option":"Neurofibromatosis type 1","bool":false},{"option":"Acoustic schwannoma","bool":true},{"option":"Trigeminal neuralgia","bool":false},{"option":"Medulloblastoma","bool":false},{"option":"Glioblastoma","bool":false}],"id":193},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"What is the anatomical localization of the structure involved in a 'glove and stocking' pattern type of neurological deficit?","answers":[{"option":"Cerebral cortex","bool":false},{"option":"Nerve root","bool":false},{"option":"Spinal cord","bool":false},{"option":"Peripheral nerve","bool":true},{"option":"Brainstem","bool":false}],"id":194},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which pathway carries pain, temperature, touch, and pressure sensations?","answers":[{"option":"Spinocerebellar pathway","bool":false},{"option":"Spinothalamic pathway","bool":true},{"option":"Sensory pathway","bool":false},{"option":"Spinocerebellar pathway","bool":false},{"option":"Dorsal column","bool":false}],"id":195},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"A lesion at the level of the optic chiasma leads to which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Homonymous quadrantanopia","bool":false},{"option":"Complete loss of vision","bool":false},{"option":"Homonymous hemianopsia","bool":false},{"option":"Heteronymous bitemporal hemianopsia","bool":true},{"option":"Unilateral hemianopsia","bool":false}],"id":196},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"What is the duration of action of lignocaine?","answers":[{"option":"Long","bool":false},{"option":"Very long","bool":false},{"option":"Intermediate","bool":true},{"option":"Very short","bool":false},{"option":"Short","bool":false}],"id":197},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which of the following statements is most accurate regarding myasthenia gravis?","answers":[{"option":"IgG antibodies against acetylcholine receptors are the main cause","bool":true},{"option":"Weakness improves with exercise","bool":false},{"option":"Respiratory involvement is common","bool":false},{"option":"Sensory involvement may occur","bool":false},{"option":"D-penicillamine may relieve transient myasthenia gravis","bool":false}],"id":198},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Neuroleptic agents have maximum effect in which of the following symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Apathy","bool":false},{"option":"Interest","bool":false},{"option":"Sleep","bool":false},{"option":"Apetite","bool":false},{"option":"Hallucinations","bool":true}],"id":199},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"A pregnant lady was given a local anesthetic after which she developed severe anaphylaxis. Which drug was most likely given to her?","answers":[{"option":"Tetracaine","bool":false},{"option":"Ropivacaine","bool":false},{"option":"Lidocaine","bool":false},{"option":"Bupivacaine","bool":false},{"option":"Procaine","bool":true}],"id":200},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"What is the immediate complication of spinal puncture for anesthesia?","answers":[{"option":"Urinary retention","bool":false},{"option":"Hypertension","bool":false},{"option":"Hypothermia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypotension","bool":true},{"option":"Blurry vision","bool":false}],"id":201},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"A 40-year-old male is taking antipsychotics for ten years. He has developed tardive dyskinesia. This effect is due to the lack of which of the following neurotransmitters?","answers":[{"option":"Dopamine","bool":true},{"option":"Serotonin","bool":false},{"option":"Epinephrine","bool":false},{"option":"Acetylcholine","bool":false},{"option":"Histamine","bool":false}],"id":202},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is a therapeutic indication for a lumbar puncture?","answers":[{"option":"Meningitis","bool":false},{"option":"Guillain-Barre syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Idiopathic intracranial hypertension","bool":true},{"option":"Subarachnoid hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Multiple sclerosis","bool":false}],"id":203},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"A 54-year-old man is brought to the emergency department because of altered loss of consciousness after being severely injured in a road traffic accident. The patient opens his eyes to pain; his pupils are reactive and equal. There is no verbal response, and his limbs extend abnormally when stimulated by pain. Which of the following is the score of this patient on the Glasgow coma scale (GCS)?","answers":[{"option":"4","bool":false},{"option":"1","bool":false},{"option":"5","bool":true},{"option":"8","bool":false},{"option":"3","bool":false}],"id":204},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which of the following antipsychotic agents has effects at the serotonin receptor?","answers":[{"option":"Promethazine","bool":false},{"option":"Risperidone","bool":true},{"option":"Haloperidol","bool":false},{"option":"Thioridazine","bool":false},{"option":"Chlorpromazine","bool":false}],"id":205},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"What is the mechanism of action of vigabatrin?","answers":[{"option":"Blocks acetylcholine","bool":false},{"option":"Increases GABA levels","bool":true},{"option":"Activates potassium channels","bool":false},{"option":"Inactivates sodium channels","bool":false},{"option":"Blocks calcium channels","bool":false}],"id":206},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"What is the mechanism of action of lacosamide?","answers":[{"option":"Inactivates potassium channels","bool":false},{"option":"Activates potassium channels","bool":false},{"option":"Inactivates sodium channels","bool":true},{"option":"Blocks calcium channels","bool":false},{"option":"Increases GABA","bool":false}],"id":207},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which class of drugs does amitriptyline belong to?","answers":[{"option":"Selective serotonin re-uptake inhibitors","bool":false},{"option":"Serotonin-norepinephrine re-uptake inhibitors","bool":false},{"option":"Monoamine oxidase inhibitors","bool":false},{"option":"Tricyclic antidepressants","bool":true},{"option":"Heterocyclic antidepressants","bool":false}],"id":208},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Children should be prescribed valproate with caution due to the risk of which of the following side effects?","answers":[{"option":"Gingival hyperplasia","bool":false},{"option":"Paralytic ileus","bool":false},{"option":"Vomiting","bool":false},{"option":"Hepatotoxicity","bool":true},{"option":"Anorexia","bool":false}],"id":209},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"A man presents to the emergency and head CT findings show a crescent-shaped lesion. Which of the following is not a risk factor for this patient's disease?","answers":[{"option":"Anticoagulant","bool":false},{"option":"Shaken babies","bool":false},{"option":"Trauma","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic kidney disease","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic alcoholism","bool":false}],"id":210},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which of the following foods is given to a stroke patient?","answers":[{"option":"Sugary food","bool":false},{"option":"Pureed food","bool":true},{"option":"Salty food","bool":false},{"option":"Food rich in saturated fat","bool":false},{"option":"Sauteed food","bool":false}],"id":211},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Which of the following is used for treatment of resistant schizophrenia?","answers":[{"option":"Clozapine","bool":true},{"option":"Chlorpromazine","bool":false},{"option":"Benzodiazepines","bool":false},{"option":"Risperidone","bool":false},{"option":"Olanzapine","bool":false}],"id":212},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"What is the initial choice of investigation for a patient who presents with signs and symptoms of suspected acute stroke?","answers":[{"option":"Lumbar puncture","bool":false},{"option":"Magnectic resonance imaging (MRI)","bool":false},{"option":"Electroencephalography (EEG)","bool":false},{"option":"Contrast MRI","bool":false},{"option":"Non-contrast CT","bool":true}],"id":213},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"Excessive autonomic activation is a feature of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Depression","bool":false},{"option":"Autism","bool":false},{"option":"Phobia","bool":false},{"option":"Panic","bool":true},{"option":"Psychosis","bool":false}],"id":214},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2019"],"question":"An 80-year-old patient with asthma and low blood pressure required anesthesia for an emergency surgical procedure. Which of the following is the anesthetic of choice?","answers":[{"option":"Etomidate","bool":false},{"option":"Ketamine","bool":true},{"option":"Desflurane","bool":false},{"option":"Thiopental","bool":false},{"option":"Propofol","bool":false}],"id":215},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 20-year-young man is brought to the casualty in an unconscious state with a history of head injury. His pupils are asymmetrically pinpoint, body temp 105 degrees Fahrenheit. Which of these hemorrhages occurred in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Pontine hemorrhage","bool":true},{"option":"Intraventricular hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Subdural hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Intracerebral hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Extradural hemorrhage","bool":false}],"id":216},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"During a professional car race, a car moving at speed suddenly loses control and crashes into the guard grill. The driver sustained severe injuries to the face and neck. As a complication of these injuries, the driver develops paralysis of all four limbs. What is the most likely cause of paralysis?","answers":[{"option":"Dislocation of axis","bool":false},{"option":"Dislocation at C2-C3","bool":false},{"option":"Concussion of spinal cord","bool":true},{"option":"Concussion of brain","bool":false},{"option":"Dislocation at C4-C6","bool":false}],"id":217},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 45-year-old male patient presents to the outpatient clinic with complaints of progressive walking difficulty for the past year. Nine months ago he noticed weakness in his grip with thinning of his hand muscles first on the right and then on the left side. There are no sensory complaints or sphincter disturbance. On examination, there is muscle wasting with a power of 3/5 proximally and distally in both lower limbs with brisk reflexes. Asymmetric wasting is present in both his hands with intact reflexes. An oral cavity examination shows fine rippling movement in the tongue. What is the most likely diagnosis of this man's condition?","answers":[{"option":"Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis","bool":true},{"option":"Ischemic stroke","bool":false},{"option":"Cervical myelopathy","bool":false},{"option":"Myasthenia gravis","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic demyelinating polyneuropathy","bool":false}],"id":218},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 28-year-old man falls and rolls along the pavement for 100 m. He has multiple contusions and abrasions involving the skin of his torso and extremities, but none on his head. He is unconscious. There is no decerebrate posturing. A CT scan of the head shows no intracranial hemorrhage or edema and no skull fractures. He remains in a persistent vegetative state. Which of the following pathological findings is most likely to be present?","answers":[{"option":"Central pontine myelinolysis","bool":false},{"option":"Meningoencephalitis","bool":false},{"option":"Demyelination","bool":false},{"option":"Diffuse axonal injury","bool":true},{"option":"Cerebral venous thrombosis","bool":false}],"id":219},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A researcher wants to see the effects of pain killer medication among three groups of post-surgical patients. What best statistical test is suited in this scenario?","answers":[{"option":"Unpaired t-test","bool":false},{"option":"Regression","bool":false},{"option":"Chi-squared test","bool":false},{"option":"Paired t-test","bool":false},{"option":"Analysis of variance (ANOVA)","bool":true}],"id":220},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 2-month-old male presents to the clinic with a history of progressively enlarging head size since birth. His fontanelles are bulging and tense. Regarding the anatomy of the ventricles which of the following is true?","answers":[{"option":"CSF enters subarachnoid space by foramen of Luschka","bool":true},{"option":"Sylvian aqueduct connects the lateral and 3rd ventricles","bool":false},{"option":"Foramen of Monroe connects the lateral and 4th ventricles","bool":false},{"option":"There are two foramen of Magendie","bool":false},{"option":"There are two 3rd ventricles","bool":false}],"id":221},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 60-year-old male presents to the outpatient clinic with complaints of neck pain and difficulty in carrying out daily activities. He has a previous history of falls. Neurological examination findings reveal weakness and sensory disturbance more on upper limbs than on lower limbs. What kind of spinal cord injury is most likely?","answers":[{"option":"Brown-Sequard syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Complete spinal cord syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Anterior spinal cord syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Central cord syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Posterior spinal cord syndrome","bool":false}],"id":222},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 48-year-old male comes to the emergency room, with complaints of headache, malaise, mental confusion, and vomiting. The cerebrospinal fluid analysis shows a pleocytosis made up of mononuclear and neutrophils, an elevated protein concentration, and moderately reduced or normal glucose. What microorganism commonly causes chronic bacterial meningitis?","answers":[{"option":"Mycobacterium tuberculosis","bool":true},{"option":"Group B streptococci","bool":false},{"option":"Haemophilus infuenzae","bool":false},{"option":"Listeria monocytogenes","bool":false},{"option":"Neisseria meningitides","bool":false}],"id":223},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 39-year-old male presents to a neurologist's clinic with complaints of double vision and drooping of the upper eyelid. After examination and investigation, a diagnosis of damage to the oculomotor nucleus at the level of superior colliculus was made. What structure is not seen at this level?","answers":[{"option":"Trochlear nucleus","bool":true},{"option":"Medial lemniscus","bool":false},{"option":"Spinal lemniscus","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebral aqueduct","bool":false},{"option":"Pretectal nucleus","bool":false}],"id":224},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 26-year-old female comes to the outpatient department with complaints of bilateral lower limb weakness and urinary incontinence for 3 days. She has a history of painful vision loss in the left eye a year ago which resolved on its own within few days. On examination, she has spastic paraparesis with sensory loss from the toes up to the level of the umbilicus. On funduscopic examination, there is optic atrophy on the left side. An MRI is ordered and T2 imaging shows areas of hyperintensities around the lateral ventricles and a post-contrast T1 sequence reveals a large hyperintense lesion in the spinal cord at the T8 level. The rest of the systemic examination was unremarkable. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Anterior spinal artery infarction","bool":false},{"option":"Neuromyelitis optica","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebrovascular trauma","bool":false},{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus","bool":false},{"option":"Multiple sclerosis","bool":true}],"id":225},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A woman brings her 13-year-old son to the psychiatry department after many complaints from the school that the child does not speak properly and has trouble articulating his words. His grades have also been falling. The child's Intelligence quotient (IQ) is checked and is found to be 57. Which of the following terms best describes the intellectual disability of this child?","answers":[{"option":"Mild intellectual disability","bool":true},{"option":"Borderline intellectual functioning","bool":false},{"option":"Severe intellectual disability","bool":false},{"option":"Moderate intellectual disability","bool":false},{"option":"Profound intellectual disability","bool":false}],"id":226},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 55-year-old man presents to the clinic with the complaint of inability to taste anything on the anterior portion of his tongue. What nerve innervates this part of the tongue?","answers":[{"option":"Accessory nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Hypoglossal nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Glossopharyngeal nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Trigeminal nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Facial nerve","bool":true}],"id":227},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 37-year-old male presents with double vision. Initial evaluation concludes he has lateral rectus palsy. Which cranial nerve is most likely lesioned in this young man?","answers":[{"option":"Abducens nerve","bool":true},{"option":"Trigeminal nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Glossopharyngeal nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Trochlear nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Oculomotor nerve","bool":false}],"id":228},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 62-year-old man is brought to the neurology clinic by his son with complaints of walking slower every day and tremors of hands at rest for 1 year. In the last 6 months, he has also become forgetful of recent events and asks simple questions repeatedly. Recently, he started claiming that he could see an elephant and a tiger in his room. These problems have become progressively worse gradually. He has had a couple of falls in this period but luckily did not acquire any major injury. What is the most likely diagnosis in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Frontotemporal dementia","bool":false},{"option":"Lewy body dementia","bool":true},{"option":"Alzheimer disease","bool":false},{"option":"Progressive supranuclear palsy","bool":false},{"option":"Parkinson disease","bool":false}],"id":229},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A researcher wants to see the differences in means among two groups of blood sugar control with new and old hypoglycemic drugs. What statistical test is best suited?","answers":[{"option":"T-test","bool":true},{"option":"Regression","bool":false},{"option":"Chi-squared test","bool":false},{"option":"One way ANOVA","bool":false},{"option":"Two way ANOVA","bool":false}],"id":230},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 50-year-old male presents to the emergency room after a road traffic accident with an altered level of consciousness and vomiting. GCS is motor 4, eye-opening 2, and verbal 1. Pupils are equal and reactive. CT scan reveals multiple frontoparietal contusions along with effacement of sulci and cisterns. Intracranial pressure can be reduced by which of the following management techniques?","answers":[{"option":"Decreasing respiratory minute volume","bool":false},{"option":"Administration of hypotonic saline","bool":false},{"option":"Keeping patient flat","bool":false},{"option":"Applying tight cervical collar","bool":false},{"option":"Keeping patient sedated","bool":true}],"id":231},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A researcher has different types of variables in their data set. They have categorical data as well as discrete data in the study. Which test will be used to analyze nominal data?","answers":[{"option":"Chi-squared test","bool":true},{"option":"Pooled t- test","bool":false},{"option":"Z-test","bool":false},{"option":"ANOVA","bool":false},{"option":"Paired t-test","bool":false}],"id":232},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 78-year-old male comes to the neurology outpatient clinic with complaints of diminished facial expression, stooping posture, slowing of voluntary movement, muscle rigidity, and a âpill-rollingâ tremor. He complains of taking short quick-paced steps when walking. An acute parkinsonian syndrome and destruction of neurons in the substantia nigra follows exposure to which of the following toxins?","answers":[{"option":"Nicotine","bool":false},{"option":"Tobacco","bool":false},{"option":"Caffeine","bool":false},{"option":"Methyl-phenyl-tetrahydropyridine","bool":true},{"option":"Dopamine","bool":false}],"id":233},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 50-year-old male patient is brought to the emergency department with an altered mental state and two episodes of generalized tonic-clonic seizures. He also complains of low-grade fever with headaches for the past month. On examination, GCS is 13/15, with bilateral 6th nerve palsy. Cerebrospinal fluid analysis shows a leukocyte count of 12/mm3 (N- 0-10/mm3) with predominant lymphocytes, protein 110 mg/dl (N <40 mg/dl), and glucose 40 mg/dl (N- 40-70 mg/dl). Gram and India ink staining were negative. MRI of the brain shows leptomeningeal enhancement in the base of the brain sections. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Cerebral abscess","bool":false},{"option":"Toxoplasmosis","bool":false},{"option":"Cryptococcal meningitis","bool":false},{"option":"Viral meningitis","bool":false},{"option":"Tuberculous meningitis","bool":true}],"id":234},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 28-year-old male came to the emergency room, with complaints of malaise, headache, and fever for 3 days and now the slightest touch is painful and produces violent motor responses or even convulsions. Negri bodies are the cytoplasmic, round to oval, eosinophilic inclusions that can be found in pyramidal neurons of the hippocampus and Purkinje cells of the cerebellum, sites usually devoid of inflammation. Which of the following virus can be detected within Negri bodies by ultrastructural and immunohistochemical methods?","answers":[{"option":"Rabies virus","bool":true},{"option":"Varicella-zoster virus","bool":false},{"option":"Herpes simplex virus-2","bool":false},{"option":"Cytomegalovirus","bool":false},{"option":"Poliovirus","bool":false}],"id":235},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 39-year-old female is scheduled to undergo a laparoscopic cholecystectomy. The anesthesiology team decides to perform induction with propofol. Which of the following is a unique property of this anesthetic agent?","answers":[{"option":"Relaxes uterine smooth muscle","bool":false},{"option":"Depresses myocardium","bool":false},{"option":"Powerful analgesia","bool":false},{"option":"High dose required to induce sedation","bool":false},{"option":"Low incidence of postoperative nausea and vomiting","bool":true}],"id":236},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A study was conducted in a village and the researcher wanted to see differences in fasting blood sugar among three groups of people. To do this he used a t-test instead of ANOVA. What statistical error may come as a result?","answers":[{"option":"Error in means","bool":false},{"option":"Standard error","bool":false},{"option":"Type 1 error","bool":true},{"option":"Type 2 error","bool":false},{"option":"Error in variance","bool":false}],"id":237},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"Which of the following statements is correct regarding the arterial supply of the spinal cord?","answers":[{"option":"Posterior spinal artery supplies posterior 2/3rd","bool":false},{"option":"Anterior spinal artery primarily supplies anterior 1/3rd","bool":false},{"option":"Spinal arteries are branches of basilar artery","bool":false},{"option":"Anterior spinal artery primarily supplies anterior 2/3rd","bool":true},{"option":"Entire cord supplied by artery of Adamkiewic","bool":false}],"id":238},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 59-year-old man diagnosed with Parkinson disease is initiated on bromocriptine therapy. Follow-up investigations that are performed six months later reveal bilateral hydronephrosis on renal ultrasound and elevation of serum creatinine. What is the most likely explanation for these findings?","answers":[{"option":"Nephrotoxicity","bool":false},{"option":"Renal artery thrombosis","bool":false},{"option":"Renal artery stenosis","bool":false},{"option":"Renal vein thrombosis","bool":false},{"option":"Retroperitoneal fibrosis","bool":true}],"id":239},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 15-year-old boy presents with complaints of recurrent loss of consciousness followed by confusion. He had three similar episodes within the last 6 months. All these episodes are associated with the inability to recall the events that occurred during the episode. Trauma to the tongue and incontinence is observed by his family after each episode. Which of the following is the best procedure to reach an accurate diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"MRI of the brain","bool":false},{"option":"Electroencephalography","bool":true},{"option":"Tilt table testing","bool":false},{"option":"Positive family history","bool":false},{"option":"An eye witness account","bool":false}],"id":240},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A second-year neurology resident is examining a patient diagnosed as a case of medial medullary syndrome. She detects hemiparesis, an impaired sensation of position and movements, and tactile discrimination (proprioception) all on the contralateral half of the body. Impaired sensations are due to lesions affecting which of the following structures?","answers":[{"option":"Spinothalamic tract","bool":false},{"option":"Pyramids","bool":false},{"option":"Corticospinal tract","bool":false},{"option":"Medial leminiscus","bool":true},{"option":"Lateral leminiscus","bool":false}],"id":241},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 55-year-old male with diabetes mellitus type 2, hyperlipidemia, and hypertension presents to his primary care provider with a diagnosis of brain stroke syndrome. Which of the following clinical findings is not associated with this condition?","answers":[{"option":"Hemineglect","bool":false},{"option":"Ataxia","bool":false},{"option":"Vertigo","bool":false},{"option":"Hoarseness","bool":true},{"option":"Diplopia","bool":false}],"id":242},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 65-year-old female is brought by her husband with a history of weakness and wasting of hand muscles associated with fasciculation and stiffness in both legs for the past nine months. Motor neuron disease is suspected and a resident is instructed to perform a detailed neurological examination. Which of the following clinical findings is not consistent with the provisional diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Absent ankle jerk","bool":false},{"option":"Diminished pin-prick sensation on sole of feet","bool":true},{"option":"Positive Hoffman sign","bool":false},{"option":"Muscle fasciculations","bool":false},{"option":"Muscle wasting","bool":false}],"id":243},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 60-year-old male with uncontrolled hypertension, active smoker, alcohol abuse presents to the emergency room. On examination, he is drowsy, able to follow commands, has right mild facial paresis, right upper and lower extremity pronator drift, and has moderate spatial hemineglect. If there is a suspicion of a middle cerebral artery lesion in a stroke patient which of the following is present?","answers":[{"option":"Ipsilateral ataxia","bool":false},{"option":"Bitemporal hemianopsia","bool":false},{"option":"Leg > arm weakness","bool":false},{"option":"Arm > leg weakness","bool":true},{"option":"Spastic paralysis","bool":false}],"id":244},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"Which of the following is a screening questionnaire for alcohol use disorder?","answers":[{"option":"Addiction severity index","bool":false},{"option":"Clinical opiate withdrawal scale","bool":false},{"option":"Clinical alcohol withdrawal scale","bool":false},{"option":"Clinical institute withdrawal assessment of alcohol","bool":false},{"option":"AUDIT-C questionnaire","bool":true}],"id":245},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 45-year-old male comes to an emergency room, with complaints of progressive weakness associated with decreased muscle mass and pain. On examination, there is muscle wasting and hyporeflexia. Cerebrospinal fluid analysis is consistent with aseptic meningitis. At what point can postpolio syndrome develop in a patient?","answers":[{"option":"At 41 to 50 years of age","bool":false},{"option":"At 61 to 70 years of age","bool":false},{"option":"15-45 years post infection","bool":true},{"option":"36 to 40 years after being cured","bool":false},{"option":"5-10 years after infection","bool":false}],"id":246},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 32-year-old firefighter is brought to the emergency department because of burns on over 60% of their body. Immediate excision and grafting are planned. During the procedure, the patient develops malignant hyperthermia. Which of the following drugs is most likely responsible for the findings in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Baclofen","bool":false},{"option":"Succinylcholine","bool":true},{"option":"Atracurium","bool":false},{"option":"Tubocurarine","bool":false},{"option":"Cyclobenzaprine","bool":false}],"id":247},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 10-year-old boy presents to the neurology clinic with complaints of fever, headache, confusion, left eye drooping, and right-sided weakness for 4 days. He had a mild upper respiratory tract infection 2 weeks ago. On examination, he has left eye ptosis with restricted medial gaze, 3/5 power on the right upper and lower extremity with brisk reflexes, and an upgoing plantar. Signs of meningeal irritation were absent. An MRI of the brain shows multiple large confluent areas of hyperintensities in the bilateral subcortical region, midbrain, and cerebellum with patchy enhancement. His cerebrospinal fluid analysis revealed lymphocytic pleocytosis. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Multiple sclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Viral meningitis","bool":false},{"option":"Acute disseminated encephalomyelitis","bool":true},{"option":"Systemic lupus erythematosus with vasculitis","bool":false},{"option":"Neuromyelitis optica spectrum disorders","bool":false}],"id":248},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"For a 65-year-old patient with controlled diabetes mellitus and hypertension, about to undergo biopsy for a small lesion on the left cheek. Which is the definitive method of securing airway under general anesthesia?","answers":[{"option":"I-gel","bool":false},{"option":"Laryngeal mask airway","bool":false},{"option":"Endotracheal tube","bool":true},{"option":"Guedel's airway","bool":false},{"option":"Nasopharyngeal airway","bool":false}],"id":249},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A researcher wants to forecast the events of drug-related effects in cardiovascular patients. Which of the following is best suited in this scenario?","answers":[{"option":"T-test","bool":false},{"option":"Chi-squared test","bool":false},{"option":"Regression model","bool":true},{"option":"Paired t-test","bool":false},{"option":"One-way ANOVA","bool":false}],"id":250},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A newborn baby boy was taken to a pediatrician because the mother noticed his head was larger than normal. After a thorough examination and investigation, a diagnosis of gross dilation of the third and lateral ventricle was made. This was due to compression of the narrow ventricular channel in the midbrain. What is the compressed narrow channel called?","answers":[{"option":"Cerebral aqueduct","bool":true},{"option":"Inferior branchium","bool":false},{"option":"Interpeduncular fossa","bool":false},{"option":"Superior branchium","bool":false},{"option":"Basis pedunculi","bool":false}],"id":251},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"Intervertebral discs are composed of which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Peripheral nucleus pulposis","bool":false},{"option":"Ligamentum flavum","bool":false},{"option":"Central Sharpey's fibers","bool":false},{"option":"Central nucleus pulposis","bool":true},{"option":"Central anulus fibrosus","bool":false}],"id":252},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 50-year-old smoker presents to the outpatient clinic with complaints of difficulty in rising above from the ground and holding heavy objects in her hands for 3-4 weeks. She has lost significant weight in the past few months. Upon examination, she had a low-grade fever, but the rest of the physical examination was normal. She had decreased power in hip and shoulder girdle muscles with normal reflexes and sensations. Erythrocyte sedimentation rate and C-reactive protein levels are raised. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Lambert-Eaton syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Inclusion body myositis","bool":false},{"option":"Dermatomyositis","bool":false},{"option":"Polymyositis","bool":true},{"option":"Myasthenia gravis","bool":false}],"id":253},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"You receive a letter from the provincial health minister to design a course related to substance-related disorders for general practitioners. The letter mentions the rising trend of substance abuse in the general population and the intent of the government to tackle the issue by integrating the care of patients with substance use disorder in primary health care. Given the dearth of specialists, the idea sounds promising. When designing the training program which areas would be kept in mind?","answers":[{"option":"Intoxication, abuse, dependence, and withdrawal","bool":true},{"option":"Assessment of substance-use disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Types of drugs and their different effects","bool":false},{"option":"Polysubstance use","bool":false},{"option":"Drug prevalence","bool":false}],"id":254},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"An ultrasound examination of a pregnant woman at 28 weeks of gestation confirms a diagnosis of a dilated fourth ventricle in the fetal brain. The appropriate part of the medulla oblongata that forms the floor of the dilated ventricle is which structure?","answers":[{"option":"Posterior surface","bool":true},{"option":"Pyramid","bool":false},{"option":"Inferior cerebellar peduncle","bool":false},{"option":"Anterior surface","bool":false},{"option":"Olive","bool":false}],"id":255},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A medico-legal officer while exploring the posterior cranial fossa during autopsy noticed the cranial nerves IX, X, and cranial part of XI nerve emerging from a groove on the brainstem. This groove is present between which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Cerebellum and medulla","bool":false},{"option":"Midbrain and medulla","bool":false},{"option":"Olive and inferior cerebellar peduncle","bool":true},{"option":"Pons and medulla","bool":false},{"option":"Pyramid and olive","bool":false}],"id":256},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"At a family gathering, a 19-year-old male is observed talking and laughing excessively and speaking about working on an invention that will change the world. His brother tells you his behavior has changed over the past 3 weeks; he hardly sleeps, listens to songs all night long, and gets violent at times. He was previously a shy person who seldom met anyone and has never behaved this way before. What is the most likely condition he is suffering from?","answers":[{"option":"Mania","bool":true},{"option":"Delusional disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Hypomania","bool":false},{"option":"Bipolar affective disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Schizophrenia","bool":false}],"id":257},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A second-year resident in neurology while discussing diagrams of the brainstem notices a pair of rounded structures (eminences) on the posterior surface of the midbrain that forms a part of the auditory pathway. What are these structures?","answers":[{"option":"Red nucleus","bool":false},{"option":"Crus cerebri","bool":false},{"option":"Inferior colliculi","bool":true},{"option":"Superior colliculi","bool":false},{"option":"Lateral geniculate body","bool":false}],"id":258},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A physician want to see the differences of blood sugar levels among three groups at different diabetic hospitals. What is the most suitable statistical test for accurate results in this case?","answers":[{"option":"ANOVA","bool":true},{"option":"Multivariate regression analysis","bool":false},{"option":"Chi-square","bool":false},{"option":"T-test","bool":false},{"option":"Univariate regression analysis","bool":false}],"id":259},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 23-year-old female presents complaining of hearing changes and balance issues. Which cranial nerve is most likely involved in this case?","answers":[{"option":"CN III","bool":false},{"option":"CN X","bool":false},{"option":"CN V","bool":false},{"option":"CN II","bool":false},{"option":"CN VIII","bool":true}],"id":260},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 15-year-old male is brought to the emergency department with a complaint of fever, drowsiness, and fits for six hours. He had a cough, sore throat, and generalized muscle, and joint pain for the past three days. On examination, he is drowsy, with neck rigidity, and a positive Kernig's sign. He is also noticed to have a widespread petechial rash on his body. Which of the following is an indicator for a bad prognosis in this condition?","answers":[{"option":"Raised ESR","bool":false},{"option":"Presence of meningitis","bool":false},{"option":"Arthralgia","bool":false},{"option":"Fever","bool":false},{"option":"Rapid progression of petechial rash","bool":true}],"id":261},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"In patients with Parkinson disease, histologic studies suggest an imbalance in brain neurotransmitters. In contrast to normal individuals, patients with Parkinson disease have an abundance of which of the following neurons and associated neurotransmitters?","answers":[{"option":"Acetylcholine","bool":true},{"option":"Norepinephrine","bool":false},{"option":"Dopamine","bool":false},{"option":"Epinephrine","bool":false},{"option":"Serotonin","bool":false}],"id":262},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 45-year-old lady who has had a history of regular alcohol intake for the last five years starts hearing voices. The voices discuss the intention to kill her. She also sees the faces of deceased relatives. On inquiry, she also reports disturbed sleep and low mood. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Wernicke-Korsakoff syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Amnestic disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Alcoholic hallcuinosis","bool":true},{"option":"Depression with psychotic features","bool":false},{"option":"Delirium tremens","bool":false}],"id":263},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"The use of cocaine produces its euphoric effect through following pharmacological action on the brain?","answers":[{"option":"Act as a direct agonist at dopaminergic D-2 receptors","bool":false},{"option":"Block the re-uptake of dopamine","bool":true},{"option":"Inhibit monoamine oxidase (MAO)","bool":false},{"option":"Act as a direct agonist at alpha-2 noradrenergic receptors","bool":false},{"option":"Inhibit the GABA receptors","bool":false}],"id":264},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 60-year-old male, with a history of hypertension and diabetes, is brought to the emergency department with complaints of sudden onset left-sided weakness for the last 1 hour. On examination, his blood pressure is 220/110 mm Hg, his pulse is regular at 90 beats/min, and his GCS is 12/15. He has left-sided hemiparesis with upgoing plantars. CT scan of the brain reveals no findings. All baseline investigations are also within normal limits. What should be the first step in the management of this case?","answers":[{"option":"Intravenous tPA administration","bool":false},{"option":"Intra-arterial thrombolysis","bool":false},{"option":"Oral aspirin 375 mg","bool":false},{"option":"Oral rivaroxaban 20 mg","bool":false},{"option":"Intravenous labetalol","bool":true}],"id":265},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A researcher wants to know the relationship between the dose of salt consumption and its effect on blood pressure. Which test is most applicable in this scenario?","answers":[{"option":"Chi square","bool":false},{"option":"ANOVA","bool":false},{"option":"Paired T-test","bool":false},{"option":"Regression","bool":true},{"option":"T-test","bool":false}],"id":266},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 6-year-old boy presents to the clinic with his mother who complains that he is inattentive in class and seems to go blank and stare into space at times. The neurological examination is unremarkable. What would be the most likely finding on EEG?","answers":[{"option":"High voltage discharges","bool":false},{"option":"Centro-temporal spikes","bool":false},{"option":"3/sec spike and wave","bool":true},{"option":"Slow wave pattern","bool":false},{"option":"Hypsarrhythmia","bool":false}],"id":267},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A researcher wants to see the mean difference of height amongst two groups of school children. What statistical test is best suited?","answers":[{"option":"ANOVA","bool":false},{"option":"Regression","bool":false},{"option":"T-test","bool":true},{"option":"Chi square","bool":false},{"option":"Logistic regression","bool":false}],"id":268},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A medicolegal officer, while performing an autopsy, notices a cranial nerve concerned with accommodation and light reflex emerges from a groove on the medial side of the crus cerebri and passes forward in the cavernous sinus. What is the cranial nerve in question?","answers":[{"option":"CN II","bool":false},{"option":"CN V","bool":false},{"option":"CN VIII","bool":false},{"option":"CN III","bool":true},{"option":"CN VII","bool":false}],"id":269},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A medical researcher wants to predict the dose-related effects of a drug on cancer patients. What best predictive model will be helpful in the given scenario?","answers":[{"option":"T-test","bool":false},{"option":"Regression","bool":true},{"option":"ANOVA","bool":false},{"option":"Chi square","bool":false},{"option":"Paired T-test","bool":false}],"id":270},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A neurophysician while discussing the MRI of a transverse section of the medulla oblongata at the level of decussation of lemnisci notices a cranial nerve emerge between olive and pyramid. What is the emerging nerve noticed by the neurophysician?","answers":[{"option":"Glossopharyngeal nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Vagus nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Hypoglossal nerve","bool":true},{"option":"Accessory nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Vestibulocochlear nerve","bool":false}],"id":271},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 30-year-old man whose right lower limb was weakened at age of 9 years after a febrile illness, could walk with a small limp but otherwise well till 6 months back, started feeling stiffness and cramps in his affected limb. The stiffness and cramps are associated with twitching. This gradually became worse and he now requires support in order to walk. On examination, the bulk is markedly reduced in the right lower limb as compared to the left side, with visible fasciculation, areflexia but intact sensations. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Post-polio syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Poliomyelitis","bool":false},{"option":"Primary lateral sclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Lumbar radiculopathy","bool":false}],"id":272},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"The United Nations Office of Drug Control (UNODC) is an international body that has the charter to support the government in its effort to curb the problems related to drugs. According to the UNODC report, which drug is most commonly abused in Pakistan?","answers":[{"option":"Opium","bool":false},{"option":"Heroin","bool":false},{"option":"Cannabis","bool":true},{"option":"Crystal meth","bool":false},{"option":"Alcohol","bool":false}],"id":273},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 17-year-old boy is brought to the emergency room after several episodes of epigastric discomfort followed by loss of sensorium. According to the attendants, he appears to be conscious but is non-responsive to his surroundings. During these 2-3 minute episodes he continues to make chewing movements and look around aimlessly. He reports a mild headache after the episode. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Complex partial seizure","bool":true},{"option":"Absence seizures","bool":false},{"option":"Myoclonic seizure","bool":false},{"option":"Migraine with aura","bool":false},{"option":"Acute psychosis","bool":false}],"id":274},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A patient suffers damage to the orbit in a road traffic incident resulting in damage to the third cranial nerve. Which of the following signs will be present?","answers":[{"option":"Pupillary constriction and a medial strabismus","bool":false},{"option":"Pupillary dilatation and a torsional strabismus","bool":false},{"option":"Pupillary dilatation and a lateral strabismus","bool":true},{"option":"Pupillary constriction and a lateral strabismus","bool":false},{"option":"Pupillary dilatation and a medial strabismus","bool":false}],"id":275},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"What is the embryological mechanism of myelomeningocele?","answers":[{"option":"Early closure of anterior neuropore","bool":false},{"option":"Early closure of posterior neuropore","bool":false},{"option":"Failure of closure of anterior neuropore","bool":false},{"option":"Reopening of anterior neuropore due to distension of central canal with CSF","bool":false},{"option":"Failure of closure of posterior neuropore","bool":true}],"id":276},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"The vertebral artery arises from which of the following structures?","answers":[{"option":"Subclavian artery","bool":true},{"option":"Internal carotid artery","bool":false},{"option":"External carotid artery","bool":false},{"option":"Descending aorta","bool":false},{"option":"Common carotid artery","bool":false}],"id":277},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"Vascular disorders of medulla oblongata present with signs and symptoms due to damage IXth, Xth, and XIth cranial nerve nuclei. Damaged nuclei are seen in the section of the medulla oblongata at the same level at which structure?","answers":[{"option":"Decussation of lemnisci","bool":false},{"option":"Olive","bool":true},{"option":"Inferior colliculus","bool":false},{"option":"Decussation of pyramid","bool":false},{"option":"Superior colliculus","bool":false}],"id":278},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 21-year-old male patient presents to the emergency room after a road traffic accident. On examination, there is complete motor paralysis and loss of temperature, and pain perception distal to the lesion. He is diagnosed with spinal cord injury. The anterior cord syndrome occurs due to which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Hemisection of the spinal cord","bool":false},{"option":"Flexion","bool":true},{"option":"Extension","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperextension","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperextension with fracture","bool":false}],"id":279},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 16-year-old girl presents to the emergency room with complaints of severe right-sided headache for the last 6 hours associated with vomiting and increased sensitivity to light and sounds. Vital signs were stable. What would be the best to differentiate between the sinister and benign causes of headaches?","answers":[{"option":"Fundoscopy","bool":true},{"option":"A detailed history of headache","bool":false},{"option":"Presence or absence of fever","bool":false},{"option":"Vomiting","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebrospinal fluid analysis","bool":false}],"id":280},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 28-year-old male presents to the outpatient clinic with a 9-year history of recurrent episodic headaches, lasting 30 minutes, at a frequency of 2-4 times a day. He claims that daily headache attacks lasted 3-4 weeks each year at the onset of winters but this year the attacks appeared at beginning of summer. The pain is excruciating and focused around his right eye. The right eye reddens, eyelid droops with ipsilateral clear nasal discharge. Physical examination, lumbar puncture, brain MRI (including pituitary views), and pituitary function blood tests are normal. What is the cause of this headache?","answers":[{"option":"Cluster headache","bool":true},{"option":"Common migraine","bool":false},{"option":"Raised intracranial pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Tension type headache","bool":false},{"option":"Intracranial infection","bool":false}],"id":281},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 45-year-old male presents to the clinic with abnormal movements of high frequency 10-12 Hertz involving his head and both the arms, bothering him mostly while taking meals and drinking water. His grandfather also had the same problem. What are these abnormal movements classified as?","answers":[{"option":"Dystonic tremors","bool":false},{"option":"Essential tremors","bool":true},{"option":"Resting tremors","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebellar tremors","bool":false},{"option":"Orthostatic tremors","bool":false}],"id":282},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"Examination of a patient indicates that he has a medially directed strabismus (squint). This could be due to damage of what structure?","answers":[{"option":"Oculomotor nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Abducens nerve","bool":true},{"option":"Ophthalmic division of trigeminal nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Trochlear nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Facial nerve","bool":false}],"id":283},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"Which of the following drugs blocks opiate receptors?","answers":[{"option":"Haloperidol","bool":false},{"option":"Chlordiazpoxide","bool":false},{"option":"Naloxone","bool":true},{"option":"Phenobarbitone","bool":false},{"option":"Benzodiazepine","bool":false}],"id":284},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 45-year-old lady is having severe toothache and is advised extraction. The lady wants it to be done under general anesthesia. She has a history of diabetes mellitus and taking oral hypoglycemic agents and her latest HbA1C is 4.7%. She also has a history of hypertension and takes antihypertensive medication. Her last blood pressure recorded was 135/85 mm Hg. All her routine lab investigations are within normal limits. According to ASA (American Society of Anesthesiologists), she will be in what ASA classification?","answers":[{"option":"VI","bool":false},{"option":"III","bool":false},{"option":"V","bool":false},{"option":"II","bool":true},{"option":"I","bool":false}],"id":285},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2020"],"question":"A 22-year-old male presents to the emergency room with recurring seizures for 3 hours. He has been running a fever for 2 days while exhibiting irritable behavior. Currently, he is very agitated and needs to be physically restrained. His body temperature is 104Â°F. Signs of meningeal irritation are absent. Plain CT scan brain shows abnormal hypo-dense signals in both temporal lobes. What is an important consideration in the management of this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Regular use of antipyretics may lead to early recovery","bool":false},{"option":"Early control of seizures is mandatory for good outcome","bool":false},{"option":"Intravenous ceftriaxone is the drug of choice","bool":false},{"option":"MRI brain is required as next step to confirm the diagnosis","bool":true},{"option":"Lumbar puncture is contraindicated because of abnormal findings in CT brain","bool":false}],"id":286},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 22-year-old female presents to the clinic in the 16th week of pregnancy for a routine check-up. Her doctor tells her that her baby has a neural tube defect. A deficiency of which of the following is cited as the most common cause of such defects?","answers":[{"option":"Iron","bool":false},{"option":"Folate","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin B12","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B6","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin C","bool":false}],"id":287},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"What type of prevention is the administration of the polio vaccine as part of the expanded program on immunization (EPI)?","answers":[{"option":"Primordial","bool":false},{"option":"Secondary","bool":false},{"option":"Quarternary","bool":false},{"option":"Tertiary","bool":false},{"option":"Primary","bool":true}],"id":288},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common presentation in multiple sclerosis (MS)?","answers":[{"option":"Diplopia","bool":false},{"option":"Stuttering","bool":false},{"option":"Blurred vision","bool":true},{"option":"Ataxia","bool":false},{"option":"Insomnia","bool":false}],"id":289},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which scale is used to measure the extent of dementia?","answers":[{"option":"Mini-mental state examination (MMSE)","bool":true},{"option":"Positive and negative syndrome scale (PANSS)","bool":false},{"option":"Beck depression inventory (BDI)","bool":false},{"option":"Brief psychiatric rating scale (BPRS)","bool":false},{"option":"General health questionnaire (GHQ)","bool":false}],"id":290},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"What is the appearance of blood on computed tomography (CT) scan?","answers":[{"option":"Fat density","bool":false},{"option":"Hypodense","bool":false},{"option":"Water density","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperdense","bool":true},{"option":"Isodense","bool":false}],"id":291},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 10-year-old boy is brought to the doctor by his parents with the complaint that he gets angry and frequently beats other children up at school. He also leaves school at times. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"No disease","bool":false},{"option":"Obssessive compulsive disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Behaviour disorder","bool":true},{"option":"Anxiety disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Dementia","bool":false}],"id":292},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is a primary tumor of the brain that often presents with calcification?","answers":[{"option":"Glioblastoma","bool":false},{"option":"Hemangioblastoma","bool":false},{"option":"Oligodendroglioma","bool":true},{"option":"Schwannoma","bool":false},{"option":"Meningioma","bool":false}],"id":293},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which lemniscus ends at the level of inferior colliculus?","answers":[{"option":"Anteriolateral","bool":false},{"option":"Medial","bool":false},{"option":"Anterior","bool":false},{"option":"Posterior","bool":false},{"option":"Lateral","bool":true}],"id":294},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 16-year-old boy presents to the hospital with complaints of lower limb weakness, respiratory distress, and unilateral facial paralysis. On examination, deep tendon reflex is absent. The level of proteins in the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) is raised. Which of the following is the most probable diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Sturge-Weber syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Tuberous sclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Guillain-BarrÃ© syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Multiple sclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease","bool":false}],"id":295},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"What is Cushing's triad?","answers":[{"option":"Hypertension, bradycardia, dyspnea","bool":false},{"option":"Hypotension, tachycardia, dyspnea","bool":false},{"option":"Hypertension, bradycardia, apnea","bool":true},{"option":"Hypotension, tachycardia, apnea","bool":false},{"option":"Hypertension, tachycardia, apnea","bool":false}],"id":296},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following occurs in Brown-SÃ©quard syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"Contralateral loss of all sensation at level of lesion","bool":false},{"option":"Contralateral loss of pain, temperature, and crude touch above level of lesion","bool":false},{"option":"Ipsilateral loss of all sensation below of lesion","bool":false},{"option":"Ipsilateral loss of pain, temperature, and crude touch below level of lesion","bool":false},{"option":"Ipsilateral loss of all sensation at level of lesion","bool":true}],"id":297},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 46-year-old male patient presents to the emergency department with right-sided weakness in the whole body. He has complained of experiencing confused behavior and being unable to control his urine. What would be the investigation of choice in this case?","answers":[{"option":"CT scan without contrast","bool":true},{"option":"CT scan with contrast","bool":false},{"option":"ECG","bool":false},{"option":"MRI with diffusion-weighted image","bool":false},{"option":"Ultrasound of the effected region","bool":false}],"id":298},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Albuminocytologic dissociation is seen in which of the following conditions?","answers":[{"option":"Guillain-BarrÃ© syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Neurofibromatosis type I","bool":false},{"option":"Charcot-Marie-Tooth disease","bool":false},{"option":"Multiple sclerosis (MS)","bool":false},{"option":"Tuberous sclerosis","bool":false}],"id":299},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is seen in case of a skull fracture?","answers":[{"option":"Subdural hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Intracranial hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Epidural hematoma","bool":true},{"option":"Subdural hematoma","bool":false},{"option":"Subarachnoid hemorrhage","bool":false}],"id":300},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A professor of epidemiology advises his students to take extreme care to avoid bias while taking a sample from the population. Which of the following is the more biased sampling technique?","answers":[{"option":"Convenience sampling","bool":true},{"option":"Cluster sampling","bool":false},{"option":"Systematic sampling","bool":false},{"option":"Simple random sampling","bool":false},{"option":"Stratified sampling","bool":false}],"id":301},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"An 80-year-old man is brought to the clinic by his son and he complains that his father is unable to recognize family members and is experiencing hallucinations for the past six months. However, he can clearly recall older memories. What is the most probable diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Dementia","bool":true},{"option":"Hemiballismus","bool":false},{"option":"Psychosis","bool":false},{"option":"Delirium","bool":false},{"option":"Restless leg syndrome","bool":false}],"id":302},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 50-year-old man suddenly developed a generalized tonic-clonic seizure during a social gathering. What is most important regarding first aid?","answers":[{"option":"Patient should be turned to his right side","bool":false},{"option":"Stay calm and observe the duration of the attack","bool":false},{"option":"No oral treatment should be given until complete consciousness is regained","bool":true},{"option":"To avoid tongue fall or bite insert a spoon in the patient's mouth","bool":false},{"option":"His clothes should be loosened and glasses removed","bool":false}],"id":303},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A seizing patient should be immediately taken to the hospital in what situation?","answers":[{"option":"Seizure is generalized tonic-clonic type","bool":false},{"option":"Patient is diabetic","bool":false},{"option":"Seizure lasts more than 30 minutes","bool":true},{"option":"Seizure starts when they are asleep","bool":false},{"option":"Family history is positive for seizure disorder","bool":false}],"id":304},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 15-year-old boy is brought to the emergency room after a sudden loss of consciousness with generalized stiffness in the body and jerking limbs. He is otherwise well but according to his parents, he is clumsy and drops objects in the morning 2-3 times per week, such as a toothbrush, teaspoon, breakfast plates, and cutlery. This has been going on for the last year. His paternal uncle is reported to have had epilepsy. What is the next best management plan?","answers":[{"option":"Observe; usually treatment is not indicated in a single seizure","bool":false},{"option":"Cardiac arrhythmias should be ruled out first","bool":false},{"option":"Suspect metabolic derangement and send blood for biochemical profile immediately","bool":true},{"option":"Start sodium valproic acid","bool":false},{"option":"EEG and MRI brain should be ordered","bool":false}],"id":305},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 70-year-old man is brought to the outpatient department with complaints of repeating phrases and questions, performing prayers at inappropriate times, and often incorrect use of vocabulary. His condition has been deteriorating for the last 2 years. What best describes his condition?","answers":[{"option":"Currently available treatment only delays progression","bool":false},{"option":"Cause may be hepatic or renal failure","bool":false},{"option":"Genetics are more commonly involved in this etiology","bool":true},{"option":"Inter-current illness, although common are not usually fatal","bool":false},{"option":"This is part of normal aging","bool":false}],"id":306},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 43-year-old man, with history of chronic alcoholism, often in his drunk state would physically and verbally abuse family members. He becomes amnestic of his aggressive behavior but felt ashamed the next morning when informed of his misconduct. These events occurred repeatedly every few weeks. Why cannot these events be called dementia?","answers":[{"option":"Patient is normal between the events","bool":false},{"option":"Condition is not progressive","bool":true},{"option":"Patient is under the influence of alcohol at the time of events","bool":false},{"option":"Age is not appropriate","bool":false},{"option":"Gender does not favor the diagnosis of dementia","bool":false}],"id":307},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 72-year-old man is brought to the neurology clinic by his son with the complaints of forgetting his way back home from the mosque multiple times in the past few months. What is a useful clinical scale to confirm a suspected cause of the mental decline?","answers":[{"option":"Hospital anxiety and depression scale","bool":false},{"option":"E1 Escorial criteria","bool":false},{"option":"Mini-mental state examination","bool":true},{"option":"ABCD2 score","bool":false},{"option":"Hamilton scale","bool":false}],"id":308},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 16-year-old girl was brought to the emergency room with complaints of fever and vomiting for the last two days. At the time of presentation, she was observed to have sudden onset deviation of eyes to the right side, and twisting of the right hand followed by loss of consciousness for about one minute, along with generalized stiffness of the body. Another similar episode was observed while the patient was being examined, lasting one minute. How will you classify this seizure type?","answers":[{"option":"Generalized tonic-clonic seizure of non-motor type","bool":false},{"option":"Focal to bilateral tonic clonic","bool":false},{"option":"Focal onset seizure with impaired awareness","bool":true},{"option":"Generalized tonic-clonic seizure of motor type","bool":false},{"option":"Aware focal onset seizure","bool":false}],"id":309},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 32-year-old lady presents to the emergency room with complaints of seizures for 3 hours, in the last two days she has had a high-grade fever with abnormal behavior and incoherent talk. On examination, there are no signs of meningeal irritation. Her blood glucose is 90 mg/dl. CT brain shows abnormal signals in both temporal lobes. Which of the following options most likely represents a cerebrospinal fluid detailed report for this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Protein 600 mg/dl, glucose 36 mg/dl, white blood cells 356/mm3, neutrophils 80%","bool":false},{"option":"Protein 39 mg/dl, glucose 79 mg/dl, white blood cells 2/mm3, lymphocytes 100%","bool":false},{"option":"Protein 246 mg/dl, glucose 70 mg/dl, white blood cells 3/mm3, lymphocytes 100%","bool":false},{"option":"Protein 800 mg/dl, glucose 24 mg/dl, white blood cells 498/mm3, lymphocytes 90%","bool":false},{"option":"Protein 90 mg/dl, glucose 73 mg/dl, white blood cells 38/mm3, lymphocytes 80%","bool":true}],"id":310},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following primary headaches is least commonly seen in neurology clinics?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic tension type of headache","bool":false},{"option":"Episodic tension type of headache","bool":false},{"option":"Cluster headache","bool":true},{"option":"Classic migraine","bool":false},{"option":"Common migraine","bool":false}],"id":311},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"What is the single most diagnostic bedside examination to rule out secondary malignant headache?","answers":[{"option":"Fundoscopic examination","bool":true},{"option":"Eliciting nystagmus","bool":false},{"option":"Kernig sign","bool":false},{"option":"Babinski sign","bool":false},{"option":"CSF manometry","bool":false}],"id":312},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 33-year-old female experienced recurrent attacks of loss of consciousness, almost every night before bedtime, variable in duration from 2 to 15 minutes, sometimes associated with jerking of the whole body and at other times total flaccidity. To differentiate between true seizures and non-epileptic psychogenic seizures, which is the best investigative modality?","answers":[{"option":"EEG with sleep deprivation","bool":false},{"option":"Detailed neurological examination","bool":false},{"option":"Polysomnography","bool":false},{"option":"Video EEG monitoring","bool":true},{"option":"Psychologic evaluation","bool":false}],"id":313},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 30-year-old female, primigravida, a known case of migraine since her teenage, presents with a recurrence of her usual headaches at the 28th week of gestation after remaining dormant for the first two trimesters. NSAIDs should be avoided in her case to avoid the risk of causing which of the following problems?","answers":[{"option":"Acute renal compromise in mother","bool":false},{"option":"Patent ductus arteriosus (PDA)","bool":false},{"option":"Pulmonary artery hypertension in fetus","bool":true},{"option":"Antepartum hemorrhage in mother","bool":false},{"option":"Fetal malformation","bool":false}],"id":314},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"What should be the initial investigation for stroke?","answers":[{"option":"Chest X-ray","bool":false},{"option":"Plain CT scan brain","bool":true},{"option":"Contrast CT scan brain","bool":false},{"option":"MRI brain screening","bool":false},{"option":"Echocardiography","bool":false}],"id":315},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 5-year-old baby is brought to the emergency room with complaints of fever on and off for the past 2 months, child has a history of cough along with fever. For 2 days, the child is drowsy and has multiple episodes of fits. According to the mother, the baby has lost weight in the last two months and the grandmother of the baby has a history of chronic cough. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Tuberculous meningitis","bool":true},{"option":"Brain abscess","bool":false},{"option":"Encephalitis","bool":false},{"option":"Stroke","bool":false},{"option":"Poliomyelitis","bool":false}],"id":316},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"An 8-year-old boy is brought to the emergency room with complaints of high-grade fever, vomiting, and headache for the past one week. On examination, he is conscious but agitated, his temperature is 103 degrees Fahrenheit, his heart rate is 140 bpm, neck rigidity is present, and plantars are bilaterally upgoing. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Miliary tuberculosis","bool":false},{"option":"Febrile fits","bool":false},{"option":"Enteric fever","bool":false},{"option":"Migraine","bool":false},{"option":"Meningitis","bool":true}],"id":317},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"What is the appearance of a cerebral hemorrhage in comparison to normal cerebral parenchyma in acute phase?","answers":[{"option":"Hyperdense","bool":true},{"option":"Water density","bool":false},{"option":"Hypodense","bool":false},{"option":"Fat density","bool":false},{"option":"Isodense","bool":false}],"id":318},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A physical therapist wants to assess the balance of a 40-year-old Parkinson's patient. Which of the following scales would be appropriate for this purpose?","answers":[{"option":"Fuctional independence measure (FIM)","bool":false},{"option":"Functional reach test (FRT)","bool":true},{"option":"10 metre walk test","bool":false},{"option":"6 minutes walk test","bool":false},{"option":"Manual muscle testing (MMT)","bool":false}],"id":319},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 3-year-old girl is brought to the outpatient department with complaints of limping in her right leg. She has a history of fever, nausea, vomiting, and headaches that occurred two weeks ago. On examination, power, tone, and reflexes are all decreased on the right side. She is vaccinated. What is the most probable diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Tenosynovitis","bool":false},{"option":"Rheumatoid arthritis","bool":false},{"option":"Myositis","bool":false},{"option":"Enthesitis","bool":false},{"option":"Poliomyelitis","bool":true}],"id":320},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"The supporting cells of the nervous system are known as neuroglia. Different neuroglia has different functions. Which of the following neuroglia pairs is mismatched?","answers":[{"option":"Schwann cells - myelin sheath in the peripheral nervous system","bool":false},{"option":"Ependymal cells - cerebrospinal fluid formation","bool":false},{"option":"Protoplasmic astrocytes - scarring cells of the central nervous system","bool":true},{"option":"Oligodendrocytes - myelin sheath in the central nervous system","bool":false},{"option":"Microglia - phagocytic cells","bool":false}],"id":321},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following neuroglial cells are responsible for filling the gap after tissue injury?","answers":[{"option":"Oligodendrocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Protoplasmic astrocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrous astrocytes","bool":true},{"option":"Neuroglias","bool":false},{"option":"Ependymal cells","bool":false}],"id":322},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"At which level are the cell bodies of preganglionic parasympathetic fibers located in the lateral grey horn of the spinal cord?","answers":[{"option":"C1, C2, and C3","bool":false},{"option":"T12 to L2","bool":false},{"option":"S2, S3, and S4","bool":true},{"option":"T1 to L2","bool":false},{"option":"L2, L3, and L4","bool":false}],"id":323},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"What is the investigation for chronic ataxia?","answers":[{"option":"Cerebrospinal fluid analysis","bool":false},{"option":"Thyroid profile","bool":false},{"option":"Urine for toxins","bool":false},{"option":"Serum electrolytes","bool":false},{"option":"MRI brain and spinal cord","bool":true}],"id":324},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"The parents of a 7-year-old boy bring him to the clinic because of concerns about his recent behavior in school and at home. In the first grade, he is unable to sit still in class and moves and talks excessively. At home, he cannot sit still at the dining table and often interrupts his parents' conversations. What is the tentative diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Oppositional defiant disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder","bool":true},{"option":"Conduct disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Autism spectrum disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Mental disability","bool":false}],"id":325},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 10-year-old boy is referred to a psychologist with complaints of extreme aggression towards his classmates, stealing others' belongings, manipulating his teachers and parents, and has also run away from school 2-3 times. What is the diagnosis in this boy?","answers":[{"option":"Disruptive mood dysregulation disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Conduct disorder","bool":true},{"option":"Anxiety disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Mood disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Kleptomania","bool":false}],"id":326},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"For many months a 36-year-old man struggled silently. He dealt with a combination of work, family, and personal issues including the way he perceived himself. He developed anxiety and began cutting and scratching himself, punching, and hitting walls to cope with his emotional pain, intense anger, and frustration. What is the most likely behavior of this man?","answers":[{"option":"Rational act","bool":false},{"option":"Solve his stresses by keeping his emotional wellbeing intact","bool":false},{"option":"Healthy coping","bool":false},{"option":"Self-harm","bool":true},{"option":"Positive thinking","bool":false}],"id":327},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 54-year-old male who has a history of asthma complains of abdominal pain for 6 months and feels something is really wrong with him. He feels a mass in his abdomen. All investigations are normal, endoscopy is done twice and comes back normal. A CT scan of the abdomen is also normal. What is the diagnosis in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Anxiety disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Schizophrenia","bool":false},{"option":"Medically unexplained symptoms","bool":true},{"option":"Depressive disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Obsessive compulsive disorder","bool":false}],"id":328},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 45-year-old man presents to the emergency department after cutting his finger with a handsaw. There is a 2 cm long laceration on his right index finger. Bupivacaine is used as local anesthesia for suturing. What is the most likely toxicity bupivacaine can produce?","answers":[{"option":"Neurotoxicity","bool":false},{"option":"Addison's disease","bool":false},{"option":"Thrombophlebitis","bool":false},{"option":"Renal toxicity","bool":false},{"option":"Cardiotoxicity","bool":true}],"id":329},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 45-year-old woman on anti-epileptic medication complains of acne and increased hair growth. She is on no other medications. Which of the following is the most likely antiepileptic medication is causing the adverse effects described?","answers":[{"option":"Phenytoin","bool":true},{"option":"Diazepam","bool":false},{"option":"Phenobarbital","bool":false},{"option":"Gabapentin","bool":false},{"option":"Sodium valproate","bool":false}],"id":330},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 70-year-old man has a 2-day history of a worsening generalized headache and increasing obtundation. He now complains of stiffness in the neck. On physical examination, vital signs include a temperature of 38.7Â°C (101.6Â°F), a pulse of 85 beats/minute, a respiratory rate is 23 breaths/minute, and blood pressure of 130/85 mmHg. A complete blood count (CBC) reveals a white blood cell (WBC) count of 16, 850/microliter. Serum electrolytes include glucose of 88 mg/dl. A lumbar puncture yields cloudy cerebrospinal fluid with a glucose of 32 mg/dl, protein of 146 mg/dl, and cell count of 3800 WBCs (95% polymorphonuclear cells and 5% mononuclear cells) and 122 red blood cells (RBCs). He is started on antibiotic therapy. Which of the following long-term complications is most likely to develop from this man's current disease?","answers":[{"option":"Hydrocephalus","bool":true},{"option":"Cerebellar infarction","bool":false},{"option":"Encephalitis","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebellar tonsillar herniation","bool":false},{"option":"Subdual hematoma","bool":false}],"id":331},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A patient presents to the outpatient department with complaints of headache and blurred vision. He has a surgical history of sigmoid carcinoma. The doctor suspects that cancer has metastasized to the brain and requests an MRI brain scan for him. Which of the following is an absolute contraindication of MRI?","answers":[{"option":"Abdominal surgery","bool":false},{"option":"Brain intervention with aneurysmal clips","bool":true},{"option":"Allergic reaction to MRI contrast","bool":false},{"option":"Coronary angiography","bool":false},{"option":"Chemotherapy","bool":false}],"id":332},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 73-year-old man is undergoing a radical prostatectomy for prostatic adenocarcinoma. During this procedure, the anesthesiologist reports a drop in blood pressure with hypotension that persists for 30 minutes despite intervention with pressor agents. Which of the following pathologic lesions is most likely to occur in his brain as a consequence of this prolonged hypotensive episode?","answers":[{"option":"Linear parasagittal infarction of watershed area","bool":true},{"option":"Anterior pituitary necrosis","bool":false},{"option":"Lacunar infarcts of basal ganglia","bool":false},{"option":"Parietal lobe hemorrhagic infarction","bool":false},{"option":"Transient ischemic attack","bool":false}],"id":333},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 40-year-old woman presents to the outpatient department with the complaint of blurred vision and gait disturbance. Her brain MRI demonstrates high-signal intensity lesions involving a short segment of the spinal cord. Simultaneous brain MRI scans show multiple new and old lesions in periventricular, cortical, and subcortical regions. She has a history of a similar attack a few months back. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Transverse myelitis","bool":false},{"option":"Multiple sclerosis","bool":true},{"option":"Susac syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Acute disseminated encephalomyelitis","bool":false},{"option":"Neuromyelitis optical","bool":false}],"id":334},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Each cellular component of the central nervous system responds differently to injury. Which of the following statements is correct about the pattern of injury in its respective cells?","answers":[{"option":"Microglia undergo cell death by necrosis or apoptosis","bool":false},{"option":"Neuronal injury commonly results in their hypertrophy","bool":false},{"option":"Neuronal injury commonly results in hyperplasia of neurons","bool":false},{"option":"Astrocytes show hypertrophy and hyperplasia","bool":true},{"option":"Neurons accumulate intermediate filaments","bool":false}],"id":335},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A young man is brought to the emergency department in an unconscious state after running into a traffic accident. Which of the following will be the first-line radiological investigation in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"MRI with contrast","bool":false},{"option":"MR angiography","bool":false},{"option":"Plain x-rays of skull and spine","bool":false},{"option":"MRI with diffusion weighted imaging","bool":false},{"option":"Plain CT scan of brain and spine","bool":true}],"id":336},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 32-year-old woman presents to the outpatient department with complaints of visual impairment and headache for three months. The examining medical student noted that the patient could not see in the temporal visual fields of both eyes. However, her visual acuity was normal. Which part of the optic pathway is involved in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Occipital cortex","bool":false},{"option":"Optic radiation","bool":false},{"option":"Lateral geniculate body","bool":false},{"option":"Optic chiasma","bool":true},{"option":"Optic nerves","bool":false}],"id":337},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 65-year-old man is admitted to the medical intensive care unit for the treatment of pneumonia. On the 3rd day of admission, the patient suddenly develops bilateral hearing loss. There is no previous history of hearing impairment. Which drug is the likely offender in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Levofloxacin","bool":false},{"option":"Ceftriaxone","bool":false},{"option":"Meropenem","bool":false},{"option":"Amikacin","bool":true},{"option":"Clarithromycin","bool":false}],"id":338},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 30-year-old female presents to the outpatient department with complaints of double vision and drooping of eyelids for one month. Upon questioning, she fatigues easily upon minimal exertion, and her symptoms worsen towards the end of the day. On examination, she has bilateral ptosis with external ophthalmoplegia and fatigable proximal limb muscles weakness. Reflexes and sensory examination are normal. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Botulism","bool":false},{"option":"Miller Fisher syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Grave's ophthalmology","bool":false},{"option":"Myasthenia gravis","bool":true},{"option":"Occulopharyngeal muscular dystrophy","bool":false}],"id":339},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"An 18-year-old boy presents to the outpatient department with a three-day history of progressive weakness of both the lower limbs. He has a history of diarrheal illness three weeks ago. On examination, he has decreased power in the lower limbs' proximal and distal muscles. Reflexes are absent all over. Sphincters are intact. Cerebrospinal fluid examination shows elevated proteins only. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Acute intermittent porphyria","bool":false},{"option":"Chronic inflammatory demyelinating polyneuropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Botulism","bool":false},{"option":"Transverse myelitis","bool":false},{"option":"Guillain-BarrÃ© syndrome","bool":true}],"id":340},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 35-year-old female, a typist by occupation, presents with pain and numbness in her right hand, mostly confined to the thumb, index, and middle fingers. Her sleep is also disturbed due to the pain. On examination, she had weakness in abduction and opposition of her right thumb and decreased sensation in lateral three and a half fingers. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Ulnar neuropathy at elbow","bool":false},{"option":"Radial neuropathy at the spinal groove","bool":false},{"option":"Median neuropathy at wrist","bool":true},{"option":"Cervical radiculopathy","bool":false},{"option":"Posterior introsseous neuropathy","bool":false}],"id":341},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 60-year-old woman presents to the outpatient department with complaints of progressively increasing headaches for three months, difficulty walking, and urinary incontinence. Her CT scan of the brain shows dilated ventricles. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Hydromyalgia","bool":false},{"option":"Hydrocele","bool":false},{"option":"Hydrocephalus","bool":true},{"option":"Hygroma","bool":false},{"option":"Hydromyelia","bool":false}],"id":342},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"When studying neurons under a microscope from an H&E stained slide, some basophilic granules called the Nissl's substances were seen in the cytoplasm. Where are these granules located?","answers":[{"option":"Axon","bool":false},{"option":"Soma","bool":true},{"option":"Dendrites","bool":false},{"option":"Neurites","bool":false},{"option":"Axon hillock","bool":false}],"id":343},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following cells with immune function arises from the embryonic mesoderm?","answers":[{"option":"Microglia","bool":true},{"option":"Ependymal cells","bool":false},{"option":"Schwann cells","bool":false},{"option":"Astrocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Oligodendrocytes","bool":false}],"id":344},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following lemniscus ends in the inferior colliculus of the mid-brain?","answers":[{"option":"Trigeminal","bool":false},{"option":"Internal arcuate fibers","bool":false},{"option":"Medial","bool":false},{"option":"Lateral","bool":true},{"option":"Spinal","bool":false}],"id":345},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is a major parasympathetic nucleus involved in the accommodation of the eye present in the midbrain?","answers":[{"option":"Edinger-Westphal nucleus","bool":true},{"option":"Pretectal nucleus","bool":false},{"option":"Oculomotor nucleus","bool":false},{"option":"Ciliary ganglion","bool":false},{"option":"Red nucleus","bool":false}],"id":346},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"What is the thin sheet of white matter that separates the lentiform nucleus from the claustrum in the basal nuclei?","answers":[{"option":"Internal capsule","bool":false},{"option":"Amygdala","bool":false},{"option":"Striatum","bool":false},{"option":"External capsule","bool":true},{"option":"Claustrum","bool":false}],"id":347},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"According to the morphological classification, neurons are divided into different types. Which of the following is not a type of neuron based on this classification?","answers":[{"option":"Interneuron","bool":true},{"option":"Unipolar","bool":false},{"option":"Bipolar","bool":false},{"option":"Pseudounipolar","bool":false},{"option":"Multipolar","bool":false}],"id":348},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"In which of the following sites is unipolar ganglia found?","answers":[{"option":"Vestibulocochlear nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Receptors","bool":false},{"option":"Optic nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Mesencephalic nucleus of trigeminal nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Dorsal root ganglia","bool":true}],"id":349},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common cause of dementia?","answers":[{"option":"Frontotemporal lobar degeneration","bool":false},{"option":"Alzheimer disease","bool":true},{"option":"Parkinson disease","bool":false},{"option":"Lewy body dementia","bool":false},{"option":"Vascular dementia","bool":false}],"id":350},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A brain tumor histopathology specimen shows cells with round nuclei with clear cytoplasm (fried egg appearance) associated with dystrophic calcification. What is the most likely brain tumor that exhibits these features?","answers":[{"option":"Pilocytic astrocytoma","bool":false},{"option":"Ependymoma","bool":false},{"option":"Medulloblastoma","bool":false},{"option":"Oligodendroglioma","bool":true},{"option":"Glioblastoma multiforme","bool":false}],"id":351},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A brain histopathology specimen shows pale substantia nigra and locus ceruleus with neuronal achromasia, tangles, and ballooned neurons. Which of the following diseases exhibits these features?","answers":[{"option":"Parkinson disease","bool":false},{"option":"Progressive supranuclear palsy","bool":false},{"option":"Corticobasal degeneration","bool":true},{"option":"Lewy body dementia","bool":false},{"option":"Multiple system atrophy","bool":false}],"id":352},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following risk factors is most commonly associated with patients requiring long-term treatment for depression?","answers":[{"option":"Diagnosis of bipolar affective disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Lack of social support","bool":false},{"option":"Incomplete symptomatic resolution","bool":true},{"option":"Associated behavioral disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Early age of onset","bool":false}],"id":353},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 10-year-old boy requires drug treatment for absence seizures. He has a past history of multiple generalized tonic-clonic seizures as well. Which of the following drugs is best suited in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Valproate","bool":true},{"option":"Carbamazepine","bool":false},{"option":"Lamotrigine","bool":false},{"option":"Levetiracetam","bool":false},{"option":"Ethosuximide","bool":false}],"id":354},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"What is the most likely condition associated with a pattern of hypsarrhythmia on an electroencephalogram (EEG)?","answers":[{"option":"Rolandic epilepsy","bool":false},{"option":"Landau-Kleffner syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Infantile spasms","bool":true},{"option":"Lennox-Gastaut syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Juvenile myoclonic epilepsy","bool":false}],"id":355},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 31-year-old male patient requires local anesthesia for lower limb surgery. Which of the following local anesthetics is most likely to cause cardiotoxicity and arrhythmias?","answers":[{"option":"Mepivacaine","bool":false},{"option":"Lignocaine","bool":false},{"option":"Bupivacaine","bool":true},{"option":"Ropivacaine","bool":false},{"option":"Prilocaine","bool":false}],"id":356},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 68-year-old male patient requires pharmacological treatment for Parkinson disease. He has a past medical history of benign prostatic hyperplasia and chronic constipation. Which of the following drugs should not be used in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Bromocriptine","bool":false},{"option":"Pergolide","bool":false},{"option":"Amantadine","bool":false},{"option":"Benztropine","bool":true},{"option":"Levodopa","bool":false}],"id":357},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common primary brain tumor?","answers":[{"option":"Glioma","bool":true},{"option":"Lymphoma","bool":false},{"option":"Hemangioblastoma","bool":false},{"option":"Meningioma","bool":false},{"option":"Medulloblastoma","bool":false}],"id":358},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 23-year-old male undergoes rapid sequence induction anesthesia for a life-saving surgery following a road traffic accident. During the procedure, he develops high-grade fever and generalized rigidity of the muscles. Which drug can be used to reverse this adverse outcome?","answers":[{"option":"Dantrolene","bool":true},{"option":"Neostigmine","bool":false},{"option":"Sugammadex","bool":false},{"option":"Baclofen","bool":false},{"option":"Succinylcholine","bool":false}],"id":359},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which drug is suitable for the treatment of malignant hyperthermia?","answers":[{"option":"Baclofen","bool":false},{"option":"Tizanidine","bool":false},{"option":"Succinylcholine","bool":false},{"option":"Dantrolene","bool":true},{"option":"Benztropine","bool":false}],"id":360},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is a characteristic histopathologic finding in Parkinson disease?","answers":[{"option":"Negri bodies","bool":false},{"option":"Cowdry bodies","bool":false},{"option":"Lewy bodies","bool":true},{"option":"Beta amyloid plaques","bool":false},{"option":"Neurofibrillary tangles","bool":false}],"id":361},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following drugs works by increasing dopamine release, blocking cholinergic receptors, and inhibiting the N-methyl-d-aspartate (NMDA) receptors?","answers":[{"option":"Levodopa","bool":false},{"option":"Tolcapone","bool":false},{"option":"Amantadine","bool":true},{"option":"Pramipexole","bool":false},{"option":"Entacapone","bool":false}],"id":362},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 16-year-old female presents with complaints of experiencing seizures after awakening from sleep for 2 months. The seizures do not appear at any other specific time. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Rolandic seizures","bool":false},{"option":"Petit mal epilepsy","bool":false},{"option":"Juvenile myoclonic epilepsy","bool":true},{"option":"Grand mal epilepsy","bool":false},{"option":"Lennox-Gustaut syndrome","bool":false}],"id":363},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is true regarding the production of cerebrospinal fluid?","answers":[{"option":"It is reabsorbed by the arachnoid granulations","bool":true},{"option":"Normal cerebrospinal fluid volume is 100 ml","bool":false},{"option":"It is mainly produced by the ventricular wall","bool":false},{"option":"It enters subarachnoid space via two foramen of magendie","bool":false},{"option":"It passes through lateral ventricle via aqueduct of sylvius","bool":false}],"id":364},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 44-year-old male presents to the outpatient clinic with complaints of mild fever for the past 3 months. The fever is associated with headaches, neck rigidity, malaise, and night sweats. His past medical history is significant for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection. On physical examination, vital signs include a temperature of 38 Â°C (100.4Â°F), a pulse of 85 beats/minute, a respiratory rate is 23 breaths/minute, and blood pressure of 130/85 mmHg. Serum electrolytes include glucose of 88 mg/dl. A lumbar puncture yields cloudy cerebrospinal fluid with a glucose of 32 mg/dl, protein of 146 mg/dl, and cell count of 3800 WBCs with predominant mononuclear cells, and a positive acid-fast bacillus (AFB) stain. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Tuberculous meningitis","bool":true},{"option":"Herpes simplex virus encephalitis","bool":false},{"option":"Tuberculous encephalitis","bool":false},{"option":"Progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy","bool":false},{"option":"Fungal meningitis","bool":false}],"id":365},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 22-year-old male swimmer presents in the emergency department with high-grade fever, headache, and neck stiffness. A provisional diagnosis of meningitis is made. What is the likely organism responsible for this presentation?","answers":[{"option":"Herpes simplex virus","bool":false},{"option":"Entamoeba histolytica","bool":false},{"option":"Staphylococcus aureus","bool":false},{"option":"Toxoplasma gondii","bool":false},{"option":"Naegleria fowleri","bool":true}],"id":366},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 16-year-old girl is brought by her mother to the psychiatry clinic with concerns regarding her behavior for 2 weeks. She has stopped going to school and stays in her room the entire day. She refuses to eat food and claims that it has been poisoned. She also believes that her family has installed cameras in her room to keep a close eye on her. She has stopped interacting with her friends and family. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Brief psychotic disorder","bool":true},{"option":"Schizoaffective disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Schizotypal personality disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Schizophreniform disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Schizophrenia","bool":false}],"id":367},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 41-year-old male presents to the outpatient clinic with worsening weakness in his right lower limb for the past three months. He also experiences extreme fatigue and pain in his limb. He has a medical history of a diagnosis of poliomyelitis at the age of 5 years which involved flaccid paralysis of the right lower limb that improved over a period of time. What is the likely diagnosis of this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Amyotropic lateral sclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Postpolio syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Spinal muscular atrophy","bool":false},{"option":"Acute poliomyelitis","bool":false},{"option":"Inclusion body myositis","bool":false}],"id":368},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 35-year-old male presents to the outpatient clinic with complaints of rigidity of his limbs for the past 2 weeks. He finds it difficult to initiate movements and when he tries to walk it feels as if he is shuffling along. His past medical history includes a diagnosis of schizophreniform disorder three months ago. He is currently taking depot injections of haloperidol for his treatment. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Dystonia","bool":false},{"option":"Tardive dyskinesia","bool":false},{"option":"Akathisia","bool":false},{"option":"Drug induced parkinsonism","bool":true},{"option":"Parkinson disease","bool":false}],"id":369},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A patient has been diagnosed with a motor neuron-related problem. Which of the following findings will lead to a revision of the diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Upgoing plantars","bool":false},{"option":"Loss of pin prick sensation","bool":true},{"option":"Exaggerated ankle reflexes","bool":false},{"option":"Pain in muscles","bool":false},{"option":"Loss of ankle reflexes","bool":false}],"id":370},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 45-year-old female presents to the outpatient clinic with a complaint of anosmia for 5 months. Radiological imaging shows a mass in the anterior cranial fossa along the olfactory groove. A primary brain tumor is suspected. What is the cell of origin of the most likely tumor?","answers":[{"option":"Meningothelial cells","bool":true},{"option":"Neurons","bool":false},{"option":"Oligodendrocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Astrocytes","bool":false},{"option":"Neuroblasts","bool":false}],"id":371},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is appropriate regarding histopathological features of multiple sclerosis?","answers":[{"option":"Perivascular demyelination","bool":false},{"option":"Perivascular lymphocytes with demyelination in white matter","bool":true},{"option":"Perivascular neutrophilic infiltrates","bool":false},{"option":"Perivascular reactive gliosis","bool":false},{"option":"Periventricular lymphoid aggregates with CD19 cells","bool":false}],"id":372},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following tumors crosses the cerebral hemispheres?","answers":[{"option":"Glioblastoma multiforme","bool":true},{"option":"Hemangioblastoma","bool":false},{"option":"Medulloblastoma","bool":false},{"option":"Craniopharyngioma","bool":false},{"option":"Meningioma","bool":false}],"id":373},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which type of cells are affected in poliomyelitis?","answers":[{"option":"Anterior horn cells of spinal cord","bool":true},{"option":"Glial cells","bool":false},{"option":"Pyramidal cells of cerebrum","bool":false},{"option":"Posterior horn cells","bool":false},{"option":"Purkinje cells of cerebellum","bool":false}],"id":374},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 23-year-old patient presents with loss of proprioception and two-point discrimination on the right side of the body. Which structure is most likely severed in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Right medial lemniscus","bool":false},{"option":"Left dorsal root ganglion","bool":false},{"option":"Left medial lemniscus","bool":true},{"option":"Left dorsal column","bool":false},{"option":"Right nucleus gracilis","bool":false}],"id":375},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following is appropriate regarding motor neuron disease?","answers":[{"option":"Physiotherapy has no role","bool":false},{"option":"Disease is curative in early stage","bool":false},{"option":"Immunosuppressive therapy is effective","bool":false},{"option":"Corticosteroids are very effective","bool":false},{"option":"Riluzole has small effect in increasing life expectancy up to 2 months","bool":true}],"id":376},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 50-year-old male presents to the clinic with proptosis and a black necrotic mass present in the nasal cavity. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Glioblastoma","bool":false},{"option":"Nasal carcinoma","bool":false},{"option":"Aspergillosis","bool":false},{"option":"Craniopharyngioma","bool":false},{"option":"Invasive fungal sinusitis","bool":true}],"id":377},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 35-year-old male presents to the outpatient clinic with difficulty in using his right hand with pain for 4 months. He also experiences paresthesias and numbness in the hand. On examination, the pain is reproduced on tapping the volar aspect of the wrist reflex hammer. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Amyotropic lateral sclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Carpal tunnel syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Cubital tunnel syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Neuropathic pain","bool":false},{"option":"Polyneuropathy","bool":false}],"id":378},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 33-year-old male presents to the neurology clinic with complaints of recurrent headaches for 1 year. The headaches are constant in character and produce a tight band-like pain. The headache episode last for a few hours and relieves with pain killers. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Migraine headache","bool":false},{"option":"Tension headache","bool":true},{"option":"Trigeminal neuralgia","bool":false},{"option":"Paroxysmal hemicrania","bool":false},{"option":"Cluster headache","bool":false}],"id":379},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following common causes of coma does not involve focal neurologic deficits?","answers":[{"option":"Multiple sclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Intracranial hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Stroke","bool":false},{"option":"Hypoglycemia","bool":true},{"option":"Brain abscess","bool":false}],"id":380},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"The first mutations identified as a cause of Parkinson disease involved SNCA, a gene that encodes Î±-synuclein, an abundant lipid-binding protein normally localized to synapses. This protein is a major component of the Lewy body, which is the diagnostic hallmark of Parkinson disease. What is the mode of inheritance of this mutation?","answers":[{"option":"Autosomal recessive","bool":false},{"option":"X-linked recessive","bool":false},{"option":"Polygenic inheritance","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal dominant","bool":true},{"option":"X-linked dominant","bool":false}],"id":381},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"What is the mode of inheritance of Duchenne muscular dystrophy?","answers":[{"option":"X-linked recessive","bool":true},{"option":"Multifactorial inheritance","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal recessive","bool":false},{"option":"Polygenic inheritance","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal dominant","bool":false}],"id":382},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 4-year-old boy is brought to the outpatient clinic by his mother with complaints of muscle weakness and clumsiness. He started walking at the age of 3 years. His gait remains unstable and he experiences frequent falls. On examination, when asked to stand up from a sitting position on the floor, the child assumes the hands-and-knees position and then climbs to a stand by walking his hands progressively up his shins, knees, and thighs. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Limb girdle muscular dystrophy","bool":false},{"option":"Inclusion body myositis","bool":false},{"option":"Becker muscular dystrophy","bool":false},{"option":"Periodic paralysis","bool":false},{"option":"Emery-Dreifuss muscular dystrophy","bool":false},{"option":"Duchenne muscular dystrophy","bool":true}],"id":383},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 16-year-old boy presents to the emergency department after sustaining a bullet injury on his back. After initial resuscitation, a complete head-to-toe examination is performed. On examination, the patient has loss of pain and temperature sensation on the right side of his body. Which structure is damaged in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Right anterior spinothalamic tract","bool":false},{"option":"Left lateral corticospinal tract","bool":false},{"option":"Left lateral spinothalamic tract","bool":true},{"option":"Left anterior spinothalamic tract","bool":false},{"option":"Right lateral spinothalamic tract","bool":false}],"id":384},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which among the following is/are biological symptoms of depression?","answers":[{"option":"Low mood","bool":false},{"option":"Suicidal ideation","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased interest","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased energy","bool":false},{"option":"Decreased appetite, libido, and sleep","bool":true}],"id":385},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 60-year-old male presents to the outpatient clinic with generalized weakness, pain in his limbs, and weight loss for 3 months. On examination, deep tendon reflexes are diminished. He has a 20-pack-year history of smoking. What is the likely diagnosis based on clinical suspicion?","answers":[{"option":"Primary brain tumor","bool":false},{"option":"Breast carcinoma","bool":false},{"option":"Thymoma","bool":false},{"option":"Liver carcinoma","bool":false},{"option":"Lung carcinoma","bool":true}],"id":386},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Chlorpromazine is a typical antipsychotic drug. Which of the following receptors is not targeted by this drug?","answers":[{"option":"Beta adrenergic receptors","bool":true},{"option":"Histamine receptors","bool":false},{"option":"Serotonin receptors","bool":false},{"option":"Alpha adrenergic receptors","bool":false},{"option":"Dopamine receptors","bool":false}],"id":387},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 30-year-old female presents to the outpatient clinic with complaints of recurrent headaches and visual disturbances for 1 month. She is currently taking retinoid derivatives for the treatment of acne. Her body mass index (BMI) is 32 kg/mÂ². On examination, fundoscopy reveals papilledema. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Benign intracranial hypertension","bool":true},{"option":"Primary brain tumor","bool":false},{"option":"Hydrocephalus","bool":false},{"option":"Normal pressure hydrocephalus","bool":false},{"option":"Temporal arteritis","bool":false}],"id":388},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"Which of the following are signs and symptoms of raised intracranial pressure?","answers":[{"option":"Hypotension, bradycardia, and headache","bool":false},{"option":"Headache, hypotension, and tachycardia","bool":false},{"option":"Headache, papilledema, and blurred vision","bool":true},{"option":"Hypotension, bradycardia, and papilledema","bool":false},{"option":"Hypertension, headache, and tachycardia","bool":false}],"id":389},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 35-year-old male presents to the clinic with weakness in his upper and lower limbs after falling from a height. The weakness is more in the upper limbs than the lower limbs. Which type of spinal cord injury is most likely responsible for this presentation?","answers":[{"option":"Spinal shock syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Anterior cord syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Brown Sequard syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Complete cord transection syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Central cord syndrome","bool":true}],"id":390},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A student is performing a neurological examination of a patient with positive lower motor neuron lesion findings. Which of the following finding will be seen in the patient?","answers":[{"option":"Muscle wasting","bool":true},{"option":"Increased tone","bool":false},{"option":"Clonus","bool":false},{"option":"Upgoing plantars","bool":false},{"option":"Exaggerated reflexes","bool":false}],"id":391},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 66-year-old male presents to the outpatient clinic with difficulty in getting up from his chair and buttoning his shirt for the past 3 months. On examination, no neurological deficits were noticed. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Myasthenia gravis","bool":false},{"option":"Necrotizing myositis","bool":false},{"option":"Dermatomyositis","bool":false},{"option":"Inclusion body myositis","bool":true},{"option":"Polymyositis","bool":false}],"id":392},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 45-year-old male is brought to the emergency department after experiencing a sudden \"thunderclap\" headache. The doctor ordered an urgent computed tomography scan and the results are inconclusive. What should be the next best investigation?","answers":[{"option":"Magnetic resonance angiography","bool":false},{"option":"Lumbar puncture","bool":true},{"option":"Digital subtraction cerebral angiography","bool":false},{"option":"Magnetic resonance imaging","bool":false},{"option":"Computed tomography angiography","bool":false}],"id":393},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 19-year-old male presents to the outpatient clinic with a complaint of muscle weakness for 8 months. After relevant examinations, the doctor ordered an evaluation of serum creatine kinase levels. The results show elevated levels of creatine kinase. What should be the next best step in the management of this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Genetic testing for X-linked mutations","bool":false},{"option":"Complete blood count","bool":false},{"option":"Computed tomography scan of brain","bool":false},{"option":"Muscle biopsy","bool":false},{"option":"Nerve conduction studies and electromyography","bool":true}],"id":394},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"What is the appropriate description for relapsing-remitting multiple sclerosis?","answers":[{"option":"Frequent acute attacks and no recovery","bool":false},{"option":"Fulminant attacks","bool":false},{"option":"Acute attacks with intervening recovery","bool":true},{"option":"Recovery with progressive disease","bool":false},{"option":"Slowly progressive disease","bool":false}],"id":395},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A 19-year-old male presents with multiple cutaneous macules, nodules of the iris, and a brain mass detected by a previous computed tomography scan. Recently, a computed tomography scan revealed an adrenal mass which prompted a visit to the consultant neurologist. What is the likely diagnosis based on these findings?","answers":[{"option":"Multiple endocrine neoplasia","bool":false},{"option":"Familial paraganglioma","bool":false},{"option":"Neurofibromatosis","bool":true},{"option":"Tuberous sclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Sturge Weber syndrome","bool":false}],"id":396},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2021"],"question":"A patient is asked to protrude the tongue during a cranial nerve examination. It is observed that the tongue is deviated towards the right side. What is the cause of this finding?","answers":[{"option":"Left cranial nerve XI injury","bool":false},{"option":"Left cranial nerve XII injury","bool":false},{"option":"Right cranial nerve XI injury","bool":false},{"option":"Right cranial nerve X injury","bool":false},{"option":"Right cranial nerve XII injury","bool":true}],"id":397},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Why is procaine relatively contraindicated in patients with cardiovascular or pulmonary diseases?","answers":[{"option":"It acts as a beta-agonist in the heart and lungs","bool":false},{"option":"It inhibits cyclooxygenase in cardiac and pulmonary cells","bool":false},{"option":"It acts as a chelating agent","bool":false},{"option":"It is a potent bronchoconstrictor","bool":false},{"option":"It causes decompensation through formation of methemoglobin","bool":true}],"id":398},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"The potency of inhaled anesthetics is defined as the minimum alveolar concentration. Which of the following denotes the minimum alveolar concentration of nitrous oxide?","answers":[{"option":"2%","bool":false},{"option":"6%","bool":false},{"option":"105%","bool":true},{"option":"1.2%","bool":false},{"option":"0.75%","bool":false}],"id":399},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 54-year-old male was admitted to the hospital for a laparoscopic hernia repair under general anesthesia. A suitable dose of diazepam was given intravenously, and the patient quickly lost consciousness. He regained consciousness 45 minutes later even though the half-life of diazepam is 40 hours. What is the most appropriate reason for the short duration of action of the drug in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Rapid metabolism of the drug within the central nervous system","bool":false},{"option":"Development of rapid tolerance to the drug effects","bool":false},{"option":"Biotransformation of the drug to active metabolites by the liver","bool":false},{"option":"Redistribution of the drug from the central nervous system to other  tissues","bool":true},{"option":"Rapid excretion of the drug by the kidneys","bool":false}],"id":400},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 35-year-old male complains to his physician about attacks of intense terror during sleep, such as feeling crushed, and often waking up with a scream, but is unable to remember any specific dream. He also feels anxious and restless from time to time during the day. Which of the following drugs is most appropriate for acutely improving the patient's symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Lithium","bool":false},{"option":"Imipramine","bool":false},{"option":"Phenobarbital","bool":false},{"option":"Haloperidol","bool":false},{"option":"Temazepam","bool":true}],"id":401},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 60-year-old male presented to the clinic with complaints of bradykinesia, rigidity, and resting tremors. The patient was diagnosed as a case of Parkinson's disease. Which of the following drugs is an appropriate combination for this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Levodopa and carbidopa","bool":true},{"option":"Bromocriptine and carbidopa","bool":false},{"option":"Entacapone and carbidopa","bool":false},{"option":"Pramipexole and carbidopa","bool":false},{"option":"Amantadine and carbidopa","bool":false}],"id":402},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of the following anti-parkinsonian drugs may cause vasospasm?","answers":[{"option":"Carbidopa","bool":false},{"option":"Bromocriptine","bool":true},{"option":"Amantadine","bool":false},{"option":"Levodopa","bool":false},{"option":"Entacapone","bool":false}],"id":403},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 35-year-old male is prescribed citalopram for depression. He stops taking the drug due to a negative impact on his sexual performance. Which of the following antidepressants should be started in this patient in place of citalopram?","answers":[{"option":"Bupropion","bool":true},{"option":"Fluoxetine","bool":false},{"option":"Amitriptyline","bool":false},{"option":"Imipramine","bool":false},{"option":"Venlafaxine","bool":false}],"id":404},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A recently widowed 76-year-old woman is prescribed benzodiazepines for several weeks after the death of her husband, but she does not like the daytime sedation it causes even at low doses. Since her depressive symptoms are not improving, the physician decides to prescribe an antidepressant medication. Which of the following drugs would be the most appropriate in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Mirtazapine","bool":false},{"option":"Phenalzine","bool":false},{"option":"Amitryptiline","bool":false},{"option":"Citalopram","bool":true},{"option":"Trazodone","bool":false}],"id":405},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 25-year-old female with generalized seizures is well-controlled on valproate. She indicates that she is interested in becoming pregnant next year. With respect to her antiseizure medication, which of the following would be the most appropriate next step in her therapy?","answers":[{"option":"Leave her on her current theraoy","bool":false},{"option":"Decrease her valproate dosage","bool":false},{"option":"Consider adding a second antiseizure medication","bool":false},{"option":"Stop the therapy during her pregnancy","bool":false},{"option":"Consider switching to lamotrigine","bool":true}],"id":406},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"An adult male is recently diagnosed as a case of schizophrenia. Which of the following antipsychotic drugs is most likely to improve his apathy and blunted affect?","answers":[{"option":"Haloperidol","bool":false},{"option":"Fluphenazine","bool":false},{"option":"Chlorpromazine","bool":false},{"option":"Risperidone","bool":true},{"option":"Thioridazine","bool":false}],"id":407},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of the following antipsychotics is considered to be the most potent and thus carries the greatest risk for causing extrapyramidal symptoms?","answers":[{"option":"Chlorpromazine","bool":false},{"option":"Thioridazine","bool":false},{"option":"Fluphenazine","bool":false},{"option":"Haloperidol","bool":true},{"option":"Olanzapine","bool":false}],"id":408},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"An 8-year-old male is brought to the clinic with complaints of multiple fits periodically for the past year. These episodes are generalized tonic-clonic convulsions followed by tongue biting and loss of consciousness. His uncle had similar complaints in his childhood which were cured by medication. What is the investigation of choice to make a definitive diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Complete blood picture","bool":false},{"option":"CT scan brain","bool":false},{"option":"ECG","bool":false},{"option":"CSF analysis","bool":false},{"option":"EEG","bool":true}],"id":409},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 3-year-old child is brought to the emergency department with a complaint of weakness in the right side of the body. The child has no history of fever. On examination, his vitals are normal and cyanosis is present. On auscultation, a murmur is found to be present. What is the most likely cause of this condition?","answers":[{"option":"Congenital cyanotic heart disease","bool":true},{"option":"Meningitis","bool":false},{"option":"Diabetes mellitus","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebral palsy","bool":false},{"option":"Anemia","bool":false}],"id":410},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 6-year-old female presents to the emergency department with complaints of severe headache, vomiting, altered sensorium, and weakness of the left side of the body. An urgent computed tomography (CT) brain was planned. What is the purpose of an urgent CT brain in such cases?","answers":[{"option":"To rule out infective etiology","bool":false},{"option":"To rule out congenital malformation","bool":false},{"option":"To rule out intracranial hemorrhage","bool":true},{"option":"To rule out brain herniation","bool":false},{"option":"To rule out ischemic infarct","bool":false}],"id":411},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 5-year-old male presents to the clinic with delayed milestones and fits. History reveals the fits to be generalized tonic-clonic jerks with atonic attacks associated with low IQ. What is the most likely diagnosis in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Febrile fits","bool":false},{"option":"Down syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebral palsy","bool":false},{"option":"Lennox-Gastaut syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"West syndrome","bool":false}],"id":412},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 3-year-old unvaccinated male presents to the emergency department with a 3-day history of high fever and sudden loss of ability to walk and stand. He also complains of severe body aches and backaches, but bladder and bowel control are intact. On examination, he is conscious and responsive with asymmetry of limb movements. There is hypotonia and hyporeflexia with power 2/5 in the left lower limb. The remaining motor examination is unremarkable. The sensation is normal in all limbs. What is the best diagnostic test in this case?","answers":[{"option":"MRI spine","bool":false},{"option":"CSF D/R","bool":false},{"option":"NCV and EMG","bool":false},{"option":"Serum potassium levels","bool":false},{"option":"Stool sample for viral isolation","bool":true}],"id":413},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 30-year-old male patient with a spinal cord injury is admitted for comprehensive rehabilitation. His neurological examination reveals intact sensory function, but no motor function is preserved below the neurological level at S4 and S5. What will be the grading of this patient according to the American Spinal Injury Association Impairment (ASIA) scale?","answers":[{"option":"ASIA C","bool":false},{"option":"ASIA E","bool":false},{"option":"ASIA A","bool":false},{"option":"ASIA B","bool":true},{"option":"ASIA D","bool":false}],"id":414},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A patient with a spinal cord injury develops a sudden rise in blood pressure. What is the most common cause of autonomic dysreflexia in a patient with a spinal cord injury?","answers":[{"option":"Ingrown toenails","bool":false},{"option":"Body postioning","bool":false},{"option":"Fecal impaction","bool":false},{"option":"Urinary bladder dysfunction","bool":true},{"option":"Pressure ulcers","bool":false}],"id":415},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 35-year-old male presents to the neurology clinic with complaints of pain, inability to close his right eye, and bilateral loss of vision for one week. He also reports fever, and flu-like symptoms as well as a distinctive rash resembling a bull's eye on his arm a few weeks prior to the onset of these symptoms. On examination, he had bilateral papillitis and right-sided lower motor neuron facial palsy. MRI brain is suggestive of white matter lesions. Cerebrospinal fluid has predominant lymphocytes, normal sugars, and raised proteins. What is the most appropriate diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Lyme disease","bool":true},{"option":"Cysticercosis","bool":false},{"option":"Brucellosis","bool":false},{"option":"Leptospirosis","bool":false},{"option":"Cryptococcosis","bool":false}],"id":416},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 65-year-old male presents to the neurology clinic after falling several times in the past few months. On examination, the most notable findings are a wide unstable gait and marked retropulsion. He also has bradykinesia, mask facies, and dysarthria. There is no evidence of cogwheeling or resting tremor. His symptoms do not respond to levodopa/carbidopa. His eye movements are notable for their vertical saccades, and fast phases. What is the most appropriate diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Normal pressure hydrocephalus","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebellar ataxia","bool":false},{"option":"Progressive supranuclear palsy","bool":true},{"option":"Amyotrophic lateral sclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"L-dopa resistant Parkinson disease","bool":false}],"id":417},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 60-year-old male shopkeeper is brought to the emergency room by his son due to his inability to recall names and phone numbers with some odd behavior since one day. He had recently been prescribed sleeping pills by a nearby doctor a few days prior to the illness. There is no history of fever, fits, trauma, or loss of consciousness. On examination, he is awake, inattentive, confused, and disoriented to place. There are no signs of meningeal irritation. The rest of the examination was unremarkable. What is the most appropriate diagnosis in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Dementia","bool":false},{"option":"Stupor","bool":false},{"option":"Depression","bool":false},{"option":"Coma","bool":false},{"option":"Delirium","bool":true}],"id":418},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 30-year-old male sustained a severe head injury in a road traffic accident 3 months back, following which he becomes unconscious, and required ventilatory support. He is currently still on ventilatory support, although he does make his own breaths as well. On examination, he has intact corneal, doll's eyes, and pupillary responses. There is no verbal response, although there is occasional eye-opening, and yawning. He is able to move all his limbs against gravity, but only on deep pain. His blood pressure, temperature, and pulse are within normal range. What is the most appropriate diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Permanent vegetative state","bool":false},{"option":"Locked-in syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Minimally conscious state","bool":false},{"option":"Brain death state","bool":false},{"option":"Persistent vegetative state","bool":true}],"id":419},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 25-year-old female presents with a 6-month-long history of drooping of both upper eyelids, transient double-vision, especially in the evening, and fatigue. On examination, she has striking fatigable bilateral ptosis, double vision on sustained lateral gaze with easily visible fatigable weakness of the medial recti, mild weakness in neck flexion, and fatigable weakness of shoulder abduction and hip flexion. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Neuropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Mitochondrial myopathy","bool":false},{"option":"Myasthenia gravis","bool":true},{"option":"Motor neuron disease","bool":false},{"option":"Frontal lobe tumor","bool":false}],"id":420},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 60-year-old shopkeeper, a known case of diabetes, and compliant with his medication, is found obtunded and confused by a customer in his shop. He is taken to a nearby hospital emergency room where he is found to have profuse sweating, and a Glasgow coma scale score of 8/15 (E2, M4, V2). There is no history of fever, fits, or trauma. His blood pressure is 140/90 mmHg, respiratory rate of 14 breaths/min, and he has a regular pulse of 99 beats/min. Blood samples are taken for electrolytes, and blood glucose levels. After maintaining airway, breathing, and circulation, what should be the next step in the management of this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Push I/V dextrose","bool":true},{"option":"Push I/V naloxone","bool":false},{"option":"Push I/V magnesium","bool":false},{"option":"Push I/V diazepam","bool":false},{"option":"Push I/V insulin","bool":false}],"id":421},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 50-year-old female diagnosed with chronic liver disease for more than eight years is on medical management of the illness. She is found to have an altered sleep pattern with insomnia for the last few days and is started on some sedatives and hypnotics. After taking the first few doses, she became progressively drowsy and is able to move her body and limbs in response to voice stimulation but is not making any eye contact  What is her score according to the Richmond agitation sedation score (RASS)?","answers":[{"option":"-1 drowsy","bool":false},{"option":"-4 deep sedation","bool":false},{"option":"-3 moderate sedation","bool":true},{"option":"-5 unarousable","bool":false},{"option":"-2 light sedation","bool":false}],"id":422},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 40-year-old boxer sustains a head injury during a tournament and is immediately rushed to the hospital. He is opening his eyes to painful stimuli and is attempting to remove the mask during resuscitation. He is also producing some inappropriate words. His blood pressure is 130/90 mmHg, heart rate 99 beats/min, and respiratory rate 20 breaths/min. How can his level of consciousness be graded by using the Glasgow coma scale?","answers":[{"option":"By using verbal response","bool":false},{"option":"By using motor response","bool":false},{"option":"By using grimace response","bool":false},{"option":"By using verbal, motor, and eye responses","bool":true},{"option":"By using eye response","bool":false}],"id":423},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 30-year-old male, who is a known case of diabetes, was found unconscious by a pedestrian who witnessed stiffness and jerking of the body as well as frothing at the mouth. He is brought to the emergency room where his blood pressure and glucose levels are found to be normal. There is no evidence of any head injury. What is the most appropriate next investigation in this case?","answers":[{"option":"X-ray skull","bool":false},{"option":"MRI brain","bool":false},{"option":"EEG","bool":true},{"option":"Ultrasound","bool":false},{"option":"CT brain","bool":false}],"id":424},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common ophthalmologic feature of multiple sclerosis?","answers":[{"option":"Occulomotor nerve palsy","bool":false},{"option":"Abducens nerve palsy","bool":false},{"option":"Optic neuritis","bool":true},{"option":"Intranuclear ophthalmoplegia","bool":false},{"option":"Nystagmus","bool":false}],"id":425},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of the following statements regarding transient ischemic attacks is true?","answers":[{"option":"It is insidious in onset","bool":false},{"option":"It lasts about 8 to 10 hours","bool":false},{"option":"It resolves within 24 hours","bool":true},{"option":"It is one of the causes of infarction","bool":false},{"option":"Aspirin can not be given","bool":false}],"id":426},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of the following conditions occurs as a result of brainstem infarction?","answers":[{"option":"Dizziness","bool":false},{"option":"Quadriparesis","bool":true},{"option":"Nausea and vomiting","bool":false},{"option":"Aphasia","bool":false},{"option":"Hemineglect","bool":false}],"id":427},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of the following statements is the most appropriate regarding subdural hematomas?","answers":[{"option":"It is caused by the rupture of the middle meningeal artery","bool":false},{"option":"It is crescent-shaped","bool":true},{"option":"It causes seizures in most cases","bool":false},{"option":"It should be drained immediately, regardless of the size of the hematoma","bool":false},{"option":"It can be diagnosed on X-ray skull","bool":false}],"id":428},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of the following central nervous system pathways, when disrupted, result in a coma?","answers":[{"option":"Bilateral temporoparietal cortices","bool":false},{"option":"Intracerebral pathways","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebellar connecting pathways","bool":false},{"option":"Region below the mid-pons","bool":false},{"option":"Both cerebral hemispheres diffusely, or brainstem ascending reticular activating system","bool":true}],"id":429},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is an inappropriate investigation to diagnose the cause of coma?","answers":[{"option":"Serum electrolytes","bool":false},{"option":"Erythrocyte sedimentation rate","bool":true},{"option":"Complete blood count","bool":false},{"option":"Serum glucose","bool":false},{"option":"Electroencephalography","bool":false}],"id":430},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is the most appropriate statement about the management of coma?","answers":[{"option":"Management of the underlying cause is necessary","bool":true},{"option":"The patient should be managed in the ICU","bool":false},{"option":"Hypertonic saline should be given","bool":false},{"option":"Metabolic causes of coma carry a worse prognosis","bool":false},{"option":"The patient is nursed in supine position","bool":false}],"id":431},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 78-year-old male presents to the neurology clinic with complaints of diminished facial expression (often termed masked facies), stooped posture, slowing of voluntary movement, festinating gait (progressively shortened, accelerated steps), rigidity, and a \"pill-rolling\" tremor. According to epidemiologic evidence, exposure to which of the following is protective for Parkinson disease (PD)?","answers":[{"option":"Tobacco","bool":false},{"option":"Dopamine","bool":false},{"option":"Caffeine","bool":true},{"option":"Pesticide","bool":false},{"option":"MPTP (1-methyl-4-phenyl-1,2,3,6-tetrahydropyridine)","bool":false}],"id":432},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 22-year-old male presents to the emergency department with complaints of headache, photophobia, irritability, clouding of consciousness, and neck stiffness. A spinal tap yields cloudy or frankly purulent cerebrospinal fluid, under increased pressure, with as many as 90,000 neutrophils per cubic millimeter, an increased protein concentration, and markedly reduced glucose content. Bacteria are visible on a smear. Which organism is responsible for causing acute pyogenic (bacterial) meningitis in adolescents and in young adults?","answers":[{"option":"Listeria monocytogenes","bool":false},{"option":"Escherichia coli","bool":false},{"option":"Mycobacterium tuberculosis","bool":false},{"option":"Group B streptococci","bool":false},{"option":"Neisseria meningitidis","bool":true}],"id":433},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is a commonly overlooked initial non-motor symptom of Parkinson disease?","answers":[{"option":"Cogwheel rigidity","bool":false},{"option":"Akinesia","bool":false},{"option":"Postural instability","bool":false},{"option":"Anosmia","bool":true},{"option":"Bradykinesia","bool":false}],"id":434},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 39-year-old HIV-positive male has received no antiretroviral therapy. CT scan of the head shows no intracranial hemorrhage, but there is a midline shift. MRI of the brain shows a 4-cm circumscribed and solid mass. Cytologic examination shows large cells with large nuclei and scant cytoplasm that mark with CD20, but not with GFAP or cytokeratin. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Large B-cell lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"Progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy","bool":false},{"option":"Medulloblastoma","bool":false},{"option":"Kaposi sarcoma","bool":false},{"option":"Glioblastoma","bool":false}],"id":435},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 69-year-old woman has exhibited fluctuating cognitive function, lapses in attention, excessive daytime sleepiness, and periods of disorganized speech over the past 3 years. In the past month, she has had visual hallucinations and memory loss. MR imaging of her brain shows minimal cortical and hippocampal atrophy. A SPECT dopamine transporter scan is abnormal. Which of the following movement problems is she most likely to manifest?","answers":[{"option":"Dysdiadochokinesia","bool":false},{"option":"Truncal ataxia","bool":false},{"option":"Tremor at rest","bool":true},{"option":"Hemiballismus","bool":false},{"option":"Choreoathetosis","bool":false}],"id":436},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 50-year-old male, a diagnosed case of acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS), dies due to meningoencephalitis. A brain autopsy shows soap-bubble lesions, and microorganisms are visible with India-ink preparation. Which of the following is the most likely organism responsible for the patient's condition?","answers":[{"option":"Listeria monocytogenes","bool":false},{"option":"Streptococcus pneumonia","bool":false},{"option":"Neisseria meningitides","bool":false},{"option":"Mycobacterium tuberculosis","bool":false},{"option":"Cryptococcus neoformans","bool":true}],"id":437},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 5-year-old boy presents with weakness of both lower limbs. He has no history of trauma. There is a history of upper respiratory tract infection 2 weeks back. On examination, power is reduced in both lower limbs, tendon reflexes are absent. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Stroke","bool":false},{"option":"Poliomyelitis","bool":false},{"option":"Transverse myelitis","bool":false},{"option":"Guillain-BarrÃ© syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Cerebral palsy","bool":false}],"id":438},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 65-year-old woman, with history of carcinoma of the right breast, was brought to the clinic with altered mentation for 2 weeks. Her CT scan brain revealed multiple enhancing lesions in brain parenchyma at the grey-white matter junction with perilesional edema. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Glioma","bool":false},{"option":"Schwannoma","bool":false},{"option":"Meningioma","bool":false},{"option":"Hemangioblastoma","bool":false},{"option":"Metastasis","bool":true}],"id":439},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 55-year-old male is brought to the emergency department with right-sided weakness within 2 hours after the onset of symptoms. He undergoes a plain CT scan which was unremarkable. Which will be the advantage of diffusion-weighted MRI in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Identification of salvageable brain tissue","bool":false},{"option":"Differentiation between ischemic and hemorrhagic infarct","bool":true},{"option":"Determine the size of infarct","bool":false},{"option":"Detect subarachnoid hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Confirmation of vascular thrombosis","bool":false}],"id":440},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 39-year-old male is referred for a contrast MRI cervical spine due to weakness and neck pain radiating to the right arm for 18 months. MRI shows an expansion of the cord with a well-defined enhancing intramedullary lesion at C2-C4 level, associated with surrounding edema. The given description best corresponds to which one of the following conditions?","answers":[{"option":"Transverse myelitis","bool":false},{"option":"Astrocytoma","bool":false},{"option":"Meningioma","bool":false},{"option":"Neurofibroma","bool":false},{"option":"Ependymoma","bool":true}],"id":441},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 27-year-old girl stated to her doctor that, \"I was walking with my dog in the park suddenly, I started sweating. Since it isn't hot outside, I couldn't quite understand why...then I started having trouble breathing and really got scared. My heart was pounding so hard I thought it might explode out of my chest. My knees felt weak - it seemed like my whole body was shaking, then my arms went numb. Apparently the whole thing only lasted a few minutes, but it felt like each second was an hour. Did I have a heart attack? Am I going crazy? I felt like I was going to die.\" What is the most likely diagnosis in that girl?","answers":[{"option":"High blood pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Mixed anxiety depression disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Cardiac arrest","bool":false},{"option":"Panic attack","bool":true},{"option":"Angina attack","bool":false}],"id":442},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 6-week-old baby boy is referred to the neurosurgery clinic by a pediatrician as she was concerned about the child's head circumference, which was raised on two successive measurements. The child was born by normal vaginal delivery. The pregnancy was uneventful; the mother has two older children with no medical problems. Both the 12- and 20-week ultrasound scans were normal. Since birth, the baby has been feeding well and not crying unduly. He has not had other symptoms such as fevers or unusual patterns of vomiting. What is the first step in the management of this condition?","answers":[{"option":"CT scan brain plain","bool":true},{"option":"Neurologic examination","bool":false},{"option":"MRI brain screening","bool":false},{"option":"Follow up in clinic","bool":false},{"option":"Ultrasound head","bool":false}],"id":443},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 30-year-old male, when leaving his house in the morning, always has to check the door multiple times to make sure that he has locked his front door. If he tries to leave his house without checking his door, or after only checking it once, he is filled with such anxiety and dread that he must abandon whatever else he is doing to return home and check his front door again. What is the most likely phenomenon this man is struggling with?","answers":[{"option":"Stigma","bool":false},{"option":"Ethical dilemma","bool":false},{"option":"Mania","bool":false},{"option":"Obsession","bool":false},{"option":"Compulsion","bool":true}],"id":444},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Parents of a 10-year-old boy are concerned that their child might be suffering from attention deficit hyperactivity disorder. Therefore, they brought him to a psychologist for a detailed assessment. Which behavior is most likely consistent with his diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"The child engages in self destructive behavior","bool":false},{"option":"The child lacks empathy for others","bool":false},{"option":"The child defies authority figures","bool":false},{"option":"The child interrupts others","bool":true},{"option":"The child has been hoarding objects","bool":false}],"id":445},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 17-year-old male is brought by his parents to a psychiatric clinic with 3 months history of isolation, poor self-care, self-talking, and refusing to go out. He has a past history of using cannabis. What is the most likely diagnosis of this boy?","answers":[{"option":"Schizophrenia","bool":false},{"option":"Mania with psychosis","bool":false},{"option":"Depression with psychosis","bool":false},{"option":"Drug induced psychosis","bool":true},{"option":"Acute and transient psychotic disorder","bool":false}],"id":446},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 14-year-old girl who took an overdose of paracetamol in the context of being called fat at school is brought to the emergency department. What is the most important assessment in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Medical history","bool":false},{"option":"Suicide risk assessment","bool":true},{"option":"Past psychiatry history","bool":false},{"option":"Personal history","bool":false},{"option":"Family history","bool":false}],"id":447},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 50-year-old female is brought by her daughter to a psychiatric clinic with complaints of headache, poor sleep, reduced energy, and lack of interest in her life along with suicidal thoughts for the last few months. What is the most likely important feature in her history to make a probable diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"History of suicide","bool":false},{"option":"History of medical illness","bool":false},{"option":"History of mania","bool":false},{"option":"History of similar illness in family","bool":false},{"option":"History of depression","bool":true}],"id":448},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 3-month-old child presents with an abnormal head shape since birth. He was born at term via normal vaginal delivery. The father has a similar but more accentuated head shape. The physical examination is otherwise normal. A computed tomography (CT) scan of the head shows thickening and ridging at the site of the sagittal suture. When does the growth of the cranial vault cease to occur at the site of sutures?","answers":[{"option":"2 years","bool":true},{"option":"3 years","bool":false},{"option":"3.5 years","bool":false},{"option":"4 years","bool":false},{"option":"1 year","bool":false}],"id":449},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 36-year-old male presents with neck and left arm pain. He reports paresthesias in the left index and long fingers. He is found to have weakness of the left triceps muscle and a diminished left triceps jerk. At which vertebral level is his disc herniation most likely to be?","answers":[{"option":"C7-T1","bool":false},{"option":"C5-C6","bool":false},{"option":"C4-C5","bool":false},{"option":"C3-C4","bool":false},{"option":"C6-C7","bool":true}],"id":450},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 20-year-old male after a road traffic accident developed alexia but his ability to write was intact. Damage to which of the following structures are likely to present with alexia without agraphia?","answers":[{"option":"Left geniculocalcarine tract, corpus callosum, and wernicke's area","bool":false},{"option":"Left geniculocalcarine tract and wernicke's area","bool":false},{"option":"Right geniculocalcarine tract and wernicke's area","bool":false},{"option":"Left geniculocalcarine tract and corpus callosum","bool":true},{"option":"Right geniculocalcarine tract and corpus callosum","bool":false}],"id":451},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 55-year-old male presents with lower back pain radiating to both lower limbs. On examination, weakness and decreased reflexes are noted in both limbs. He is suspected for spinal cord compression. Which of the following radiological investigations is the imaging modalities of choice to assess the exact site of abnormality?","answers":[{"option":"Myelography","bool":false},{"option":"Magnetic resonance imaging","bool":true},{"option":"X-ray spine","bool":false},{"option":"Nuclear medicine","bool":false},{"option":"Computed tomography","bool":false}],"id":452},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is not a cause of coma?","answers":[{"option":"Hypoxia","bool":false},{"option":"Malaria","bool":false},{"option":"Seizures","bool":false},{"option":"Blood transfusion","bool":true},{"option":"Hypertension","bool":false}],"id":453},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 60-year-old male smoker presents with a complaint of difficulty in walking. He is suspected of a case of vascular disease. Which clinical symptoms support this diagnosis against neurological disease?","answers":[{"option":"Poorly localized, electric shock like pain and often in both legs","bool":false},{"option":"Poorly localized, bursting pain which relief by bending forward","bool":false},{"option":"Electric shock like pain involving whole leg and relieved by bending forward","bool":false},{"option":"Bursting type of pain involving the whole leg, and relieved by sitting with elevation of leg","bool":true},{"option":"Poorly localized electric shock like pain in whole leg which relieved by leg elevation","bool":false}],"id":454},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common cause of coma and confusion?","answers":[{"option":"Metabolic or toxic","bool":true},{"option":"Hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Hydrocephalus","bool":false},{"option":"Seizures","bool":false},{"option":"Tumor","bool":false}],"id":455},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Following a diagnosis of multiple sclerosis on the basis of history and clinical examination, which of the following investigations is the best to confirm the diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Visual-evoked potentials","bool":false},{"option":"Poser's criteria","bool":false},{"option":"MRI brain and cervical spine with contrast","bool":true},{"option":"Lumbar puncture","bool":false},{"option":"MRI brain without contrast","bool":false}],"id":456},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 9-year-old male is having learning difficulties at school. He has brief lapses of awareness with eyelid fluttering that occurs every 5 to 10 minutes. Which drug would be effective in this child without the additional disadvantages of excessive sedation or tolerance development?","answers":[{"option":"Clonazepam","bool":false},{"option":"Phenobarbital","bool":false},{"option":"Ethosuxemide","bool":true},{"option":"Diazepam","bool":false},{"option":"Gabapentin","bool":false}],"id":457},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 5-year-old male presents to the emergency department with a complaint of fits. Past history reveals attacks of generalized tonic-clonic jerks along with atonic attacks. He has a low IQ and delayed milestones. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"West syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Febrile fits","bool":false},{"option":"Down syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebral palsy","bool":false},{"option":"Lennox-Gastaut syndrome","bool":true}],"id":458},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 35-year-old housewife presents to the neurology clinic for evaluation of persistent headache and vomiting for one week with intermittent clouding of consciousness and confusion. She had a prior history of fever and weight loss for more than 2 months. Two years back she was treated for pulmonary tuberculosis and became symptom-free. On examination signs of meningeal irritation were positive with bilateral papilledema. MRI brain contrast study is suggestive of CNS tuberculosis. The cerebrospinal fluid detailed report is awaited. What is the next step in the management of this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Wait for CSF report","bool":false},{"option":"Start anti-fungal therapy","bool":false},{"option":"Start steroids","bool":false},{"option":"Get EEG done","bool":false},{"option":"Start antituberculous therapy","bool":true}],"id":459},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is not a risk factor for stroke?","answers":[{"option":"Arteriovenous malformations","bool":true},{"option":"Hypercholesterolemia","bool":false},{"option":"Atrial fibrillation","bool":false},{"option":"Hypertension","bool":false},{"option":"Diabetes","bool":false}],"id":460},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"According to epidemiologic evidence, exposure to which of the following is protective for Parkinson disease (PD)?","answers":[{"option":"Gluten","bool":false},{"option":"Dopamine","bool":false},{"option":"MPTP (1-methyl-4-phenyl-1,2,3,6-tetrahydropyridine)","bool":false},{"option":"Nicotine","bool":true},{"option":"Pesticide","bool":false}],"id":461},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which type of prevention is exemplified by wearing a helmet?","answers":[{"option":"Quaternary","bool":false},{"option":"Primordial","bool":false},{"option":"Tertiary","bool":false},{"option":"Primary","bool":true},{"option":"Secondary","bool":false}],"id":462},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A government decides to educate the common population to spread awareness about a certain disease, so that people are aware of its preventive measures. What type of prevention is this?","answers":[{"option":"Primary","bool":true},{"option":"Primordial","bool":false},{"option":"Quaternary","bool":false},{"option":"Secondary","bool":false},{"option":"Tertiary","bool":false}],"id":463},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A young female presents to the emergency department following a head injury. What is the most appropriate initial investigation in this case?","answers":[{"option":"CT scan","bool":true},{"option":"X-ray","bool":false},{"option":"Fundoscopy","bool":false},{"option":"Ultrasound","bool":false},{"option":"MRI scan","bool":false}],"id":464},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Control of diabetes and hyperlipidemia is recommended to prevent potential strokes. What type of prevention is this?","answers":[{"option":"Tertiary","bool":false},{"option":"Secondary","bool":false},{"option":"Primary","bool":true},{"option":"Primordial","bool":false},{"option":"Quaternary","bool":false}],"id":465},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 25-year-old female presents to the clinic with a complaint of low energy levels throughout the day. Further questioning reveals that she also has a persistent low mood and a lack of interest in things she used to enjoy. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Cyclothymia","bool":false},{"option":"Schizophrenia","bool":false},{"option":"Depression","bool":true},{"option":"Mania","bool":false},{"option":"Bipolar affective disorder","bool":false}],"id":466},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of the following organisms most commonly causes Guillain-Barre syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"Campylobacter jejuni","bool":true},{"option":"Listeria monocytogenes","bool":false},{"option":"Neisseria meningitides","bool":false},{"option":"Streptococcus pneumonia","bool":false},{"option":"Cryptococcus neoformans","bool":false}],"id":467},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Anticonvulsive therapy is provided to patients in order to manage epilepsy patients and keep them seizure-free. What type of prevention is this?","answers":[{"option":"Primordial","bool":false},{"option":"Secondary","bool":true},{"option":"Tertiary","bool":false},{"option":"Primary","bool":false},{"option":"Quaternary","bool":false}],"id":468},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Why is levodopa used instead of dopamine in patients with Parkinson's disease?","answers":[{"option":"Levodopa is less expensive","bool":false},{"option":"Levodopa is more readily available","bool":false},{"option":"Levodopa is more stable","bool":false},{"option":"Levodopa is less toxic","bool":false},{"option":"Levodopa is more effective","bool":true}],"id":469},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A young male is currently taking prescribed amitryptiline for depression. He recently got diagnosed with schizophrenia and is prescribed chlorpromazine for this condition. What is the most major risk of using these two drugs simultaneously?","answers":[{"option":"Neuroleptic malignant syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Orthostatic hypotension","bool":true},{"option":"Abnormal movements","bool":false},{"option":"Extrapyramidal symptoms","bool":false},{"option":"Gynecomastia","bool":false}],"id":470},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of the following antipsychotic medications is least associated with sedation?","answers":[{"option":"Clozapine","bool":false},{"option":"Quetiapine","bool":false},{"option":"Olanzapine","bool":false},{"option":"Ziprasidone","bool":false},{"option":"Risperidone","bool":true}],"id":471},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 7-month-old male presents to the clinic with a history of progressively enlarging head size since birth. What is the initial investigation of choice?","answers":[{"option":"Biopsy","bool":false},{"option":"MRI","bool":false},{"option":"Ultrasound","bool":false},{"option":"CT scan","bool":true},{"option":"X-ray","bool":false}],"id":472},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is the most common suture involved in craniosynostosis?","answers":[{"option":"Sagittal","bool":true},{"option":"Metopic","bool":false},{"option":"All involved at the same time","bool":false},{"option":"Lambdoid","bool":false},{"option":"Coronal","bool":false}],"id":473},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"An 11-year-old girl presents to the clinic with slowly progressive difficulty maintaining balance. Her symptoms started when she started walking and now have progressed to the extent that she is wheelchair-bound. She has a significant history of recurrent infections. She also has reddish lesions on her ear lobes and conjunctiva. Neurological examination reveals truncal and appendicular ataxia. Other sensations, reflexes, and plantars are normal. What is the most probable diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Spinocerebellar ataxia","bool":false},{"option":"Ataxia telangiectasia","bool":true},{"option":"Sturge-Weber syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Friedreich's ataxia","bool":false},{"option":"Von-Hippel-Lindau disease","bool":false}],"id":474},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of the following are the most severe forms of neural tube defects?","answers":[{"option":"Spina bifida occulta and anencephaly","bool":false},{"option":"Encephalocele and craniosynostosis","bool":false},{"option":"Dandy-walker and myelomeningiocele","bool":false},{"option":"Spina bifida occulta and encephalocele","bool":false},{"option":"Anencephaly and rachischisis","bool":true}],"id":475},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is a term used to describe absence seizures?","answers":[{"option":"Petit mal","bool":true},{"option":"Myoclonic seizures","bool":false},{"option":"Tonic seizures","bool":false},{"option":"Grand mal","bool":false},{"option":"Atonic seizures","bool":false}],"id":476},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 17-year-old male presents to the clinic with a complaint of rigidity in the limbs for one week. He is a known case of schizophrenia and is currently using haloperidol injections for the treatment of psychosis. What is the most appropriate step to manage this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Keep the patient under observation","bool":false},{"option":"Increase the dose of haloperidol","bool":false},{"option":"Decrease the dose of haloperidol","bool":false},{"option":"Switch from haloperidol to fluphenazine","bool":false},{"option":"Administer benztropine","bool":true}],"id":477},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 70-year-old male patient with a confirmed diagnosis of Parkinson disease presents to the clinic and expresses concern that his medication now takes approximately one hour before it starts to alleviate his symptoms. The patient is currently taking levodopa. What is the term that describes the phenomenon being experienced by this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Early on phenomenon","bool":false},{"option":"Wearing off phenomenon","bool":false},{"option":"Delayed off phenomenon","bool":false},{"option":"Delayed on phenomenon","bool":true},{"option":"On-off phenomenon","bool":false}],"id":478},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 45-year-old male presents with bilateral lower limb weakness which seems to be progressing upwards. A provisional diagnosis of Guillain-BarrÃ© syndrome is made. Which of the following features least supports the provisional diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Normal nerve conduction velocities in the first week","bool":false},{"option":"Normal potassium level","bool":false},{"option":"Normal nerve conduction velocity in the sural nerve","bool":false},{"option":"Increased protein in cerebrospinal fluid","bool":false},{"option":"Polymorphonuclear cells > 50/mm3 of CSF","bool":true}],"id":479},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"A 30-year-old female presents to the clinic with quadriparesis, abdominal pain, and psychiatric symptoms for one day. All of her reflexes are absent apart from the ankle jerk, which is normal. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Acute intermittent porphyria","bool":true},{"option":"Chronic inflammatory demyelinating polyneuropathy","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebrovascular accident","bool":false},{"option":"Lead poisoning","bool":false},{"option":"Guillain-Barre syndrome","bool":false}],"id":480},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2022"],"question":"Which of the following is an absolute contraindication of central axial block?","answers":[{"option":"Hypovolemia","bool":false},{"option":"Drug allergy","bool":false},{"option":"Coagulopathy","bool":false},{"option":"Infection","bool":false},{"option":"Patient refusal","bool":true}],"id":481},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A politician intends to implement a primary prevention program against neurological diseases in the area. Which of the following measures would be appropriate as a primary prevention in the community?","answers":[{"option":"Screening of psychiatric diseases","bool":false},{"option":"Fostering strong social support","bool":true},{"option":"Preparing expert neurosurgeons","bool":false},{"option":"Building advance hospitals","bool":false},{"option":"Free supplies of psychiatric drugs","bool":false}],"id":482},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A group of students used an analysis of variance test (ANOVA) to test the hypothesis that the mean systolic blood pressure among various ethnicities is different. In the first step of ANOVA, they obtained an F-statistic less than the critical value.  What would be the second step considering their analysis is correct?","answers":[{"option":"Report the results as it is","bool":false},{"option":"Do the post hoc analysis","bool":false},{"option":"Reject the null hypothesis (HÂ°)","bool":false},{"option":"Apply more advanced statistical tests","bool":true},{"option":"Re-do the analysis","bool":false}],"id":483},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A student compares the body weights of a group of 100 children before and after four weeks of nutrition supplementation for his research project. His hypothesis is: \"the nutrition supplementation brings a change in the body weights of children\". He uses an independent sample t-test for his hypothesis testing and finds highly significant results at a p-value of 0.001. His professor checks his report and rejects it. Which of the following assumptions must have been violated?","answers":[{"option":"Independence of observations should be there","bool":true},{"option":"Independent variable should consist of three categories","bool":false},{"option":"The dependent variable should be categorical","bool":false},{"option":"There should be more significant outliers","bool":false},{"option":"The dependent variable should be skewed","bool":false}],"id":484},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A lecturer is teaching epidemiological study designs to his students. He emphasizes the follow-up data of the patients and how to reduce the loss of follow-up in an observational study design. The professor is teaching which of the following epidemiological study designs to his students?","answers":[{"option":"Case series","bool":false},{"option":"Experimental study","bool":false},{"option":"Case control study","bool":false},{"option":"Cross-sectional study","bool":false},{"option":"Cohort study","bool":true}],"id":485},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A group of students was conducting a research study to find out the risk factors of stomach cancer in Karachi city. They had a limited budget and time to complete this study on a rare disease such as stomach cancer. Which of the following epidemiological study designs would be appropriate to fulfill their study objectives?","answers":[{"option":"Cross-sectional study","bool":false},{"option":"Case control study","bool":true},{"option":"Experimental study","bool":false},{"option":"Case series","bool":false},{"option":"Cohort study","bool":false}],"id":486},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A group of researchers was conducting a study on the relationship of high dose vitamin D on stomach cancer 5-year survival outcome. They identified 100 stomach cancer patients and randomly allocated 50 patients to vitamin D and the other 50 to the placebo through a coin toss. The above statement refers to which of the following study designs?","answers":[{"option":"Case control study","bool":false},{"option":"Cross-sectional study","bool":false},{"option":"Experimental study","bool":true},{"option":"Case series","bool":false},{"option":"Cohort study","bool":false}],"id":487},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"While working in the health office of district Thatta a student came across several cases of oral cancers from 10 talukas. The student also had data on the number of gutka outlets in different talukas. He wanted to find an association between the number of persons affected and gutka sales in the area. What would be the most appropriate study design?","answers":[{"option":"Correlational","bool":true},{"option":"Cross-sectional","bool":false},{"option":"Case series","bool":false},{"option":"Cohort","bool":false},{"option":"Case control","bool":false}],"id":488},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A medical student wants to find the prevalence of coronary heart disease among adult males in the district central of Karachi. Which epidemiological study design is most appropriate for this study?","answers":[{"option":"Clinical trial","bool":false},{"option":"Cross sectional","bool":true},{"option":"Cohort","bool":false},{"option":"Case control","bool":false},{"option":"Case series","bool":false}],"id":489},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Qualitative data does not have quantitative x and y observations for each participant so the relationship between two variables cannot be computed by correlation coefficient. For example: the frequency of males smoking versus females smoking. Which one of the following tests can be performed to see the association between two variables in such situations?","answers":[{"option":"Chi square test","bool":true},{"option":"Analysis of variance (ANOVA)","bool":false},{"option":"Correlation","bool":false},{"option":"Paired T-test","bool":false},{"option":"Independent T-test","bool":false}],"id":490},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A survey of 100 men and 100 women revealed that 15 of the men and 36 of the women were overweight. The chi-square test of significance was applied to find an association at alpha equal to 0.05. Which one of the following options contains the correct decision if the calculated value for Chi is greater than the Chi critical?","answers":[{"option":"Inconclusive","bool":false},{"option":"Fail to accept the alternate hypothesis","bool":false},{"option":"Accept the null hypothesis","bool":false},{"option":"Reject the null hypothesis","bool":true},{"option":"Reject the alternate hypothesis","bool":false}],"id":491},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Which of the following steps should be avoided while giving first aid to the victim of a snake bite?","answers":[{"option":"Incision or suction of venom from bitten area","bool":true},{"option":"Application of local antibiotic","bool":false},{"option":"Immobilizing the person","bool":false},{"option":"Removing any items or clothing which may constrict the bitten area","bool":false},{"option":"Cleaning the wound area with water","bool":false}],"id":492},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"The snake venom can cause damage to multiple systems of the body depending upon the type of snake venom injected by the snake bite. A bite may also trigger a potentially fatal anaphylactic reaction. The manifestations of local pain, redness, swelling, and extravasation of blood are mostly in envenomation by which of the following snakes?","answers":[{"option":"Rattlesnake","bool":false},{"option":"Krait","bool":false},{"option":"Sea snake","bool":false},{"option":"Pit viper","bool":true},{"option":"Cobra","bool":false}],"id":493},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A consultant asked a medical student to assess a patient on a Glasgow coma scale in the emergency department. This scale generally assesses which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Gastrointestinal system","bool":false},{"option":"Neuromuscular system","bool":true},{"option":"Renal system","bool":false},{"option":"Cardiovascular system","bool":false},{"option":"Respiratory system","bool":false}],"id":494},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 60-year-old male patient was diagnosed as a case of Parkinson's disease in the neurology outpatient department. The neurophysician suggested levodopa for his disease-related symptoms. Which of the following statements is true about the mechanism of action of levodopa?","answers":[{"option":"Levodopa causes seizures","bool":false},{"option":"Levodopa is metabolized in liver","bool":false},{"option":"Levodopa is converted into dopamine by dopa decarboxylase in the brain","bool":true},{"option":"Levodopa is hydroxylated into the chemical compound in the brain","bool":false},{"option":"Levodopa is directly converted into dopamine in the periphery","bool":false}],"id":495},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Which of the following statements is the most accurate regarding the drugs used for the treatment of Parkinson disease?","answers":[{"option":"The benefit of antimuscarinic drugs in Parkinson's disease is to relieve bradykinesia","bool":false},{"option":"Levodopa causes mydriasis and may precipitate an acute attack of glaucoma","bool":true},{"option":"Therapeutic effects of amantadine continue for several years","bool":false},{"option":"Dopamine receptor agonists should never be used in Parkinson's disease before the trial of levodopa","bool":false},{"option":"Selegiline is a selective COMT inhibitor (catechol-o-methyl transferase inhibitor)","bool":false}],"id":496},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Which of the following is a troublesome adverse effect of levodopa when used for Parkinson disease?","answers":[{"option":"Ototoxicity","bool":false},{"option":"Choreoathetosis of face & distal extremities","bool":true},{"option":"Seizures","bool":false},{"option":"Day time sedation","bool":false},{"option":"Hypertension","bool":false}],"id":497},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A male patient reported to the psychiatric clinic for his psychiatric problem. He was prescribed lithium for his mental issues. Which of the following is the most accurate for the clinical indication of lithium?","answers":[{"option":"Acute mania","bool":true},{"option":"Tremors","bool":false},{"option":"Tardive dyskinesia","bool":false},{"option":"Rigidity","bool":false},{"option":"Choreoathetosis","bool":false}],"id":498},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Haloperidol is not a suitable option for the treatment of which of the following psychiatric conditions?","answers":[{"option":"Amenorrhea-galactorrhea syndrome","bool":true},{"option":"Acute mania","bool":false},{"option":"Resting tremors","bool":false},{"option":"Schizophrenia","bool":false},{"option":"Bipolar affective disorder","bool":false}],"id":499},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 30-year-old male office worker suffers from intense migraine headaches. Which of the following drugs is a serotonin 5-HT (1D/1B) agonist useful for decreasing an acute migraine headache?","answers":[{"option":"Ondansetron","bool":false},{"option":"Cimetidine","bool":false},{"option":"Sumatriptan","bool":true},{"option":"Nitroprusside","bool":false},{"option":"Ergotamine","bool":false}],"id":500},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 51-year-old woman presents with symptoms of major depression and closed-angle glaucoma. Which of the following antidepressants needs to be avoided in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Amitriptyline","bool":true},{"option":"Mirtazapine","bool":false},{"option":"Selegiline","bool":false},{"option":"Fluoxetine","bool":false},{"option":"Bupropion","bool":false}],"id":501},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 23-year-old patient with a history of severe postoperative nausea and vomiting comes for plastic surgery. Which of the following anesthetic drugs would be best to use for maintenance in this situation?","answers":[{"option":"Halothane","bool":false},{"option":"Nitrous oxide","bool":false},{"option":"Propofol","bool":true},{"option":"Isoflurane","bool":false},{"option":"Sevoflurane","bool":false}],"id":502},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 33-year-old female patient needs to be anesthetized before dilation and curettage for abnormal uterine bleeding. Her anesthesia is induced initially with an inhaled nonflammable anesthetic that contains no halogenated carbons. Which of the following agents best fits this description?","answers":[{"option":"Diethyl ether","bool":false},{"option":"Halothane","bool":false},{"option":"Nitrous oxide","bool":true},{"option":"Enflurane","bool":false},{"option":"Propofol","bool":false}],"id":503},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 19-year-old man has a 4-cm laceration of the palmar aspect of his hand. The wound needs to be sutured with absorbable sutures. Before beginning the procedure, the wound is injected with lidocaine containing 1:100,000 parts epinephrine. The rationale behind the use of epinephrine is which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Slow anesthetic metabolism from tissue","bool":true},{"option":"Releases nitric oxide from the vessels","bool":false},{"option":"Increase bleeding to improve toxin release from the wound","bool":false},{"option":"Augment pain sensation","bool":false},{"option":"Vasodilation at the side of administration","bool":false}],"id":504},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 7-year-old female is diagnosed with absence seizures by a neurophysician. Which of the following drugs will be most appropriate to prescribe as a drug of first choice for treating her seizures?","answers":[{"option":"Phenobarbital","bool":false},{"option":"Carbamazepine","bool":false},{"option":"Diazepam","bool":false},{"option":"Ethosuximide","bool":true},{"option":"Phenytoin","bool":false}],"id":505},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Which of the following is a very potent and short-acting benzodiazepine when used as a hypnotic causes psychiatric disturbances in some cases?","answers":[{"option":"Tremazepam","bool":false},{"option":"Diazepam","bool":false},{"option":"Flurazepam","bool":false},{"option":"Triazolam","bool":true},{"option":"Nitrazepam","bool":false}],"id":506},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Coadministration of monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOIs) with which one of the following drugs may induce a central serotonin syndrome?","answers":[{"option":"Citalopram","bool":true},{"option":"Amitriptyline","bool":false},{"option":"Venlafaxine","bool":false},{"option":"Duloxetine","bool":false},{"option":"Bupropion","bool":false}],"id":507},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Which of the following monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOIs) is most likely to produce a cheese reaction?","answers":[{"option":"Selegiline","bool":false},{"option":"Tranylcypromine","bool":true},{"option":"Mirtazapine","bool":false},{"option":"Clorgyline","bool":false},{"option":"Moclobemide","bool":false}],"id":508},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Which of the following antidepressant drugs affect dopamine reuptake?","answers":[{"option":"Fluoxetine","bool":false},{"option":"Selegiline","bool":false},{"option":"Mirtazapine","bool":false},{"option":"Imipramine","bool":false},{"option":"Bupropion","bool":true}],"id":509},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A first-year anesthesiology resident reaches for isoflurane as the induction agent for a patient who is about to receive general anesthesia. When the attending faculty sees this, he quickly takes the syringe away from the resident because this agent can cause which of the following effects when used for induction?","answers":[{"option":"Coughing","bool":true},{"option":"Laryngeal relaxation","bool":false},{"option":"Hypertension","bool":false},{"option":"Muscle relaxation","bool":false},{"option":"Dry mouth","bool":false}],"id":510},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 70-year-old patient in the intensive care unit needs sedation due to prolonged endotracheal intubation. Which of the following medications should be avoided for sedation in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Propofol","bool":false},{"option":"Etomidate","bool":true},{"option":"Fentanyl","bool":false},{"option":"Dexmedetomidine","bool":false},{"option":"Ketamine","bool":false}],"id":511},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 35-year-old male patient presents with appendicitis and requires a surgical intervention. He has a family history of malignant hyperthermia. Which anesthetic agent is the most appropriate to use in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Isoflurane","bool":false},{"option":"Desflurane","bool":false},{"option":"Sevoflurane","bool":false},{"option":"Succinylcholine","bool":false},{"option":"Propofol","bool":true}],"id":512},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 78-year-old male patient with a long history of seizure disorder controlled with phenytoin presents to his dentist for routine follow-up. Which of the following findings must the dentist be concerned about and evaluate for?","answers":[{"option":"Jaw bone exposure","bool":false},{"option":"Exposed nerve roots","bool":false},{"option":"Dental caries","bool":false},{"option":"Gingival overgrowth","bool":true},{"option":"Teeth erosion","bool":false}],"id":513},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A case of morphine poisoning is diagnosed in the medical emergency department. Which of the following drugs shall be given to reverse morphine intoxication in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Naloxone","bool":true},{"option":"Diazepam","bool":false},{"option":"Halothane","bool":false},{"option":"Dopamine","bool":false},{"option":"Phenytoin sodium","bool":false}],"id":514},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A young male patient suffers from a seizure disorder characterized by tonic rigidity of the extremities followed by 15 to 30 seconds of tremor progressing to massive jerking of the body. This clonic phase lasts for 1 to 2 minutes, leaving the patient in a stuporous state. Which of the following drugs would be most suitable for the long-term management of this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Felbamate","bool":false},{"option":"Clonazepam","bool":false},{"option":"Ethosuximide","bool":false},{"option":"Phenytoin","bool":true},{"option":"Pregabalin","bool":false}],"id":515},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 2-month-old male child presents with a history of progressively enlarging head size since birth. His fontanelles are bulging and tense. Which of the following is true regarding the production of CSF?","answers":[{"option":"Normally turnover of cerebrospinal fluid is 72 times a day","bool":false},{"option":"It is absorbed by the arachnoid granulation","bool":true},{"option":"The normal rate of production is 50 milliliters per hour","bool":false},{"option":"It is produced by the dura mater","bool":false},{"option":"A major source of production of cerebrospinal fluid is the ependymal lining","bool":false}],"id":516},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 38-year-old male presented with complaints of intermittent headaches and drop attacks. Investigation reveals a colloid cyst in the ventricles causing hydrocephalus. This type of hydrocephalus is known as which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Obstructive hydrocephalus","bool":true},{"option":"Communicating hydrocephalus","bool":false},{"option":"Colloid hydrocephalus","bool":false},{"option":"Arrested hydrocephalus","bool":false},{"option":"Normal pressure hydrocephalus","bool":false}],"id":517},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 45-year-old male presents in the emergency room after a road traffic accident with complaints of vomiting and headache. Glasgow coma scale (GCS) shows M6 E4 V4. Pupils are anisocoric and reactive. A computed tomography (CT) scan reveals a biconvex hyperdensity over the right temporoparietal region along with a fracture of the temporal bone. The sensory level is at the umbilicus. What is the most likely source of blood?","answers":[{"option":"Inferior petrosal sinus","bool":false},{"option":"Middle meningeal artery","bool":true},{"option":"Superior saggital sinus","bool":false},{"option":"Middle cerebral artery","bool":false},{"option":"Bridging veins","bool":false}],"id":518},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 50-year-old male presents in the emergency room after a road traffic accident with an altered level of consciousness and vomiting. The patient has abnormal flexion in pain and opens his eyes in pain with no verbal response. Pupils are equal and reactive. A computed tomography (CT) scan reveals a crescent hyperdensity over the right frontoparietal region along with a midline shift. What is the total Glasgow coma scale (GCS) score of the patient?","answers":[{"option":"3","bool":false},{"option":"6","bool":true},{"option":"4","bool":false},{"option":"7","bool":false},{"option":"5","bool":false}],"id":519},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 60-year-old male presents with a history of a fall, complaining of neck pain and difficulty in doing normal house activities. On examination, he has weakness and sensory disturbance more in the upper limbs than in the lower limbs. What kind of spinal cord injury does he have?","answers":[{"option":"Brown sequard injury","bool":false},{"option":"Complete cord injury","bool":false},{"option":"Anterior spinal cord syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Posterior spinal cord syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Central cord injury","bool":true}],"id":520},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A young soldier on the field had a gunshot injury on his back. On examination, he had paralysis of the right leg, loss of proprioception and fine discrimination of the right leg, and loss of pain and temperature in the left leg. What kind of spinal cord injury he had?","answers":[{"option":"Central cord injury","bool":false},{"option":"Posterior spinal cord syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Complete cord injury","bool":false},{"option":"Anterior spinal cord syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Brown-sequard injury","bool":true}],"id":521},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 30-year-old male presents to the emergency room with sustained head trauma after which he developed a headache and bleeding from his right ear. A computed tomography (CT) scan shows a right temporal bone fracture. He is managed and discharged home after a period of observation. One week later he comes with difficulty in closing his right eye. Which of the following nerves is most likely to be involved?","answers":[{"option":"VII","bool":true},{"option":"VIII","bool":false},{"option":"V","bool":false},{"option":"VI","bool":false},{"option":"III","bool":false}],"id":522},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 27-year-old nurse presented with occupational dysfunction and loss of interest in her hobbies for 2 months. She was convinced that she would not be able to work again nor would pursue her hobbies of trekking and painting. Recently, she broke up a relationship with her husband. She thought that her life was not worth living and had consumed 60 tablets of phenobarbitone to end her life. She is most likely suffering from which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Post-traumatic stress disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Acute stress disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Depressive disorder","bool":true},{"option":"Conversion disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Adjustment disorder","bool":false}],"id":523},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 26-year-old female is brought to the emergency department with symptoms of aggression, over-talkativeness, hyperactivity, and decreased sleep for one week. Her family reveals that she has had two similar episodes in the past 3 years, for which she received treatment. A diagnosis of bipolar affective disorder with a current episode of mania was made. Which of the following groups of medications would be suitable for treatment in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Mood stabilizers only","bool":false},{"option":"Mood stabilizers and antipsychotics","bool":true},{"option":"Antipsychotics only","bool":false},{"option":"Mood stabilizers and benzodiazepine","bool":false},{"option":"Antidepressants and antipsychotics","bool":false}],"id":524},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 35-year-old female patient presents with complaints of restlessness, sweating, tachycardia, and difficulty in breathing for 1 month. These symptoms are episodic. There is a family history of hypertension. Laboratory investigation shows a normal level of vanillylmandelic acid (VMA) in urine. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Phobic anxiety disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperthyroidism","bool":false},{"option":"Pheochromocytoma","bool":false},{"option":"Panic disorder","bool":true},{"option":"Generalized anxiety disorder","bool":false}],"id":525},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 25-year-old woman suffers from insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus. She has been thoroughly informed on how to use insulin and what her diet should be. Furthermore, she is an intelligent girl who understands all of this. Nonetheless, at times, she secretly stops her insulin for no clear external gain like missing a test, and takes in too many carbohydrate-containing foods and drinks that necessitate emergency treatment. Because this behavior is secretive, her doctors wonder what they are doing wrong regarding her treatment. The patient herself seems very forgiving, tells them that she knows they are doing their best, and seems to enjoy the attention of doctors and nurses. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis for this case?","answers":[{"option":"Factitious disorder","bool":true},{"option":"Psychological factors affecting diabetes mellitus","bool":false},{"option":"Malingering","bool":false},{"option":"Somatoform disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Illness anxiety disorder","bool":false}],"id":526},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 27-year-old electrical engineer is brought to the psychiatric unit involuntarily by his friend, who found a handwritten note in his apartment expressing feelings of hopelessness and despair, suggesting he might be contemplating ending his life. He recently lost his job and going through a crisis in his family. Which of the following is the most appropriate management step for this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Give alternate plans for coping","bool":false},{"option":"Detain under mental health law","bool":true},{"option":"Assess the capacity of the patient","bool":false},{"option":"Involve significant others","bool":false},{"option":"Give him emergency numbers","bool":false}],"id":527},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 25-month-old boy is brought to the outpatient department with complaints of being unable to walk. The father gave a history of delayed crying and was born with obstructed labor. On examination, he has increased tone and power of 2/5 in all four limbs. Which of the following is the most severe form of the above-mentioned disease?","answers":[{"option":"Spastic hemiplegia","bool":false},{"option":"Spastic quadriplegia","bool":true},{"option":"Spastic diplegia","bool":false},{"option":"Spastic paraplegia","bool":false},{"option":"Spastic monoplegia","bool":false}],"id":528},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 3-year-old, partially vaccinated boy presented with acute onset of fever with inability to walk because of weakness in both feet. Weakness progressed over 2 days to involve the whole of both lower limbs. On examination, he was conscious but anxious and irritable. Vitals were normal. He had hypotonia, hyporeflexia, and power of grade 2/5 in both lower limbs with mute planters and intact sensations. Upper limbs and cranial nerves were intact. What would be the most appropriate test to confirm the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Stool for viral isolation 48 hours after the onset of weakness","bool":false},{"option":"Two stool samples, 24 to 48 hours apart for viral isolation","bool":true},{"option":"Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) examination","bool":false},{"option":"Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) spine","bool":false},{"option":"Nerve conduction velocity (NCV)","bool":false}],"id":529},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 2-year-old boy presented to the emergency room with a complaint of fever for 2 days and seizure for 30 minutes, 4 hours back. His temperature was 38Â°C. On examination, the throat was congested, and the central nervous system (CNS) examination was normal. What would be the most probable diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Meningitis","bool":false},{"option":"Epilepsy","bool":false},{"option":"Simple febrile seizure","bool":false},{"option":"Complex febrile seizure","bool":true},{"option":"Hypocalcemia","bool":false}],"id":530},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 5-year-old boy was suffering from high-grade fever, cough, and runny nose for 3 days. Early in the morning, he developed right-sided focal fits involving the right arm, followed by unconsciousness for a few hours. Upon awakening, he was unable to move his right arm and right leg and had a left-sided facial palsy of the lower half. What would be the most likely cause of his condition?","answers":[{"option":"Left-sided infratentorial ischemic infarct","bool":true},{"option":"Right-sided cerebral ischemic infarct","bool":false},{"option":"Left-sided intra cerebral hemorrhage","bool":false},{"option":"Left-sided cerebral ischemic infarct","bool":false},{"option":"Right-sided infratentorial hemorrhage","bool":false}],"id":531},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 35-year-old clerk who lives in a slum area of Sindh, presented in the emergency department with low-grade fever, headache, and irritability for 2 months and one episode of uprolling of eyes, jerking of limbs, and incontinence of urine one day back. He had a history of chronic productive cough for six months. On examination, his Glasgow coma scale (GCS) score was 10/15 and he had bilateral papilledema. Which best possible treatment regimen would be appropriate to start?","answers":[{"option":"Anti-tuberculosis therapy, steroids, and analgesics","bool":false},{"option":"Antibiotics, steroids, and analgesics","bool":false},{"option":"Antifungal, analgesics, and anti-seizure drugs","bool":false},{"option":"Anti-tuberculosis therapy, steroids, and anti-seizure drugs","bool":true},{"option":"Antifungal, steroids and analgesics","bool":false}],"id":532},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 70-year-old male patient presented to the neurology outpatient department with complaints of slowness of walking and abnormal movements of hands for two years. On examination, the attending physician noted bradykinesia, postural instability, and resting tremors in both hands. The tremors were more pronounced in the left hand. What is the typical frequency of tremors in this case?","answers":[{"option":"12 to 14 hertz","bool":false},{"option":"4 to 6 hertz","bool":true},{"option":"20 to 24 hertz","bool":false},{"option":"8 to 12 hertz","bool":false},{"option":"1 to 5 hertz","bool":false}],"id":533},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 35-year-old female was referred to a tertiary care hospital with an hour history of sudden onset right-sided hemiplegia and aphasia. Her national institutes of health stroke scale (NIHSS) score was 20. The on-call neurologist was on board for consideration of an intravenous tissue plasminogen activator. He asked his junior to generate radiology requests immediately from the emergency department. Which specific imaging modality would be considered in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) brain and magnetic resonance venography (MRV)","bool":false},{"option":"Computed tomography (CT) scan brain plain","bool":true},{"option":"Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) brain and magnetic resonance angiogram (MRA)","bool":false},{"option":"Computed tomography (CT) scan brain with contrast","bool":false},{"option":"Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) brain plain","bool":false}],"id":534},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 30-year-old male presented to the outpatient department with complaints of difficulty in climbing the stairs and holding heavy objects in her hands for 4 months. It was associated with significant weight loss, dry cough, and muscle pain for 6 months. On examination, he was pale and febrile with generalized wasting. Proximal muscle powers were 3/5 with intact reflexes and downgoing plantar. Sensory examination was normal. What would be most likely seen on his muscle biopsy?","answers":[{"option":"Peri-fascicular atrophy","bool":false},{"option":"Red ragged fibers","bool":false},{"option":"Type 2 muscle fiber atrophy","bool":false},{"option":"Endomysial inflammation","bool":true},{"option":"Necrotic muscle fibers","bool":false}],"id":535},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 35-year-old male presented to the outpatient department with a complaint of sequential complete loss of vision in both eyes over one week. He had a history of both lower limb weakness 6 months back with minimal recovery despite taking treatment. On examination, he had no light perception in both eyes with bilateral pale disc. There was spastic quadriparesis with sensory level at the xiphisternum. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Paraneoplastic syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Vasculitic infarctions","bool":false},{"option":"Multiple sclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Neuromyelitis optica","bool":true},{"option":"Vitamin B12 deficiency","bool":false}],"id":536},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 78-year-old otherwise healthy male is brought to the outpatient department with complaints of increasing forgetfulness, subtle behavioral changes, and difficulty in managing home finances for 6 months. On examination, he is vitally stable and his mini-mental state examination (MMSE) score is 22/30. All other neurological examinations are normal. Which of the following are the initial and most common presenting symptoms of the suspected illness?","answers":[{"option":"Dyspraxia","bool":false},{"option":"Episodic short term memory loss","bool":true},{"option":"Language dysfunction","bool":false},{"option":"Sleep disturbances","bool":false},{"option":"Incontinence","bool":false}],"id":537},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 56-year-old female presented to the neurology outpatient department with complaints of multiple neurological symptoms that suddenly appeared two days ago. Her magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) brain showed an infarct in the left lateral medulla. Which of the following would most likely be present in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Right facial sensory loss","bool":false},{"option":"Left hemisensory loss","bool":false},{"option":"Dysphagia","bool":true},{"option":"Left hypoglossal nerve palsy","bool":false},{"option":"Hearing loss","bool":false}],"id":538},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 52-year-old diabetic man presents to the emergency room with complaints of right-sided weakness and inability to speak for one hour. Acute stroke treatment is planned for him. What is the immediate target to save this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Penumbra","bool":true},{"option":"Core","bool":false},{"option":"Blocked artery","bool":false},{"option":"Unaffected cortex","bool":false},{"option":"Unaffected artery","bool":false}],"id":539},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 27-year-old female presents to the emergency room with complaints of high-grade fever for one day and seizures for two hours. On examination, she has recurrent seizures, a fever of 103 degrees Fahrenheit, and a rigid neck. There is no focal weakness and both plantars are mute. Which of the following investigations has the highest diagnostic yield in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) brain","bool":false},{"option":"Computed tomography (CT) scan brain","bool":true},{"option":"Nasopharyngeal swab","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebrospinal fluid studies","bool":false},{"option":"Blood culture","bool":false}],"id":540},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 65-year-old gentleman presents to the outpatient department with complaints of twitching and wasting of his leg muscles for the last 2 years. He has also been experiencing progressive weakness in both lower limbs. He often chokes while drinking water and suddenly starts laughing without any reason. On examination, he has wasting and fasciculations in all four limbs with hyperreflexia and extensor plantar responses. What area of his nervous system is most likely affected?","answers":[{"option":"Dorsal spinal cord","bool":false},{"option":"Frontal lobe of brain","bool":false},{"option":"Cervical spinal cord","bool":false},{"option":"Motor neurons","bool":true},{"option":"Temporal lobe of brain","bool":false}],"id":541},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"An 11-year-old male student is sent home from school because he daydreams in class and does not pay attention. During the clinical consultation, he becomes unresponsive for about 10-15 seconds. He stares blankly off into space and then suddenly resumes talking. He has no recollection that anything abnormal has happened. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Attention deficit hyperactivity disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Atonic seizures","bool":false},{"option":"Autism","bool":false},{"option":"Absence seizures","bool":true},{"option":"Dissociative disorder","bool":false}],"id":542},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 30-year-old female presents to the emergency room. She is a known case of epilepsy and has been on no treatment for the last 2 weeks. She has generalized tonic-clonic seizures which are continuous for the last 30 minutes. On arrival in the emergency room, her oxygen saturation is 70% on room air. Seizures stop spontaneously but the patient does not regain consciousness. On examination, she is not opening her eyes even to painful stimuli. She is localizing a painful stimulus with both hands. She is making grunting noises at intervals. What is the Glasgow coma scale (GCS) score of this patient?","answers":[{"option":"6/15","bool":false},{"option":"12/15","bool":false},{"option":"15/15","bool":false},{"option":"3/15","bool":false},{"option":"7/15","bool":true}],"id":543},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 32-year-old male presents to the emergency department following a motor vehicle accident. On examination, there is a clear sensory level at the T6 dermatome on the left side of the body. Below this level, there is a loss of pain and temperature sensation on the left side and a loss of vibration and proprioception on the right side. Motor function is preserved on the right side but is impaired on the left side. What is the most likely\r\ndiagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Anterior cord syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Cauda equina syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Conus medullaris syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Dorsal column syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Brown-sequard syndrome","bool":true}],"id":544},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 20-year-old female presented with complaints of bilateral ptosis and fatigability for the last 2 years. After a clinical examination and confirmatory test, myasthenia gravis was diagnosed. Which of the following drugs would be safe to use?","answers":[{"option":"Ceftriaxone","bool":true},{"option":"Lithium","bool":false},{"option":"Chloroquine","bool":false},{"option":"Quinine","bool":false},{"option":"Procainamide","bool":false}],"id":545},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A patient with Parkinson's disease presented at the rehabilitation medicine outpatient department for management. Which of the following statements is correct regarding rehabilitation management of Parkinson's disease?","answers":[{"option":"The psychologist will give therapy to improve the activity of daily living (ADLs)","bool":false},{"option":"There are no rehabilitation management options available for Parkinson's disease","bool":false},{"option":"Increased weighted utensils and adaptive equipment will improve the activities of daily living (ADLs)","bool":true},{"option":"Auditory and visual queuing increase the risk of fall","bool":false},{"option":"Exercise is harmful and increase the progress of disease","bool":false}],"id":546},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 65-year-old male with a stroke presented to the rehabilitation outpatient department having left-sided hemiplegic and spastic gait. Which of the following orthosis is most commonly used to improve the gait of patients with stroke having spastic gait?","answers":[{"option":"Thoraco-lumbar orthosis (TLSO)","bool":false},{"option":"Supra-maleolar orthosis (SMO)","bool":false},{"option":"Ankle-foot orthosis (AFO)","bool":true},{"option":"Hip-knee-ankle-foot orthosis (HKAFO)","bool":false},{"option":"Knee-ankle-foot orthosis (KAFO)","bool":false}],"id":547},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 44-year-old male presented to the outpatient department with complaints of ascending weakness in all four limbs for 5 days. He was operated on for lumbar disc herniation 3 weeks back and became ambulatory within a week. On examination, he had grade 2/5 power in all four limbs with diminished reflexes and downgoing plantar. Which of the following investigation findings is most likely to be present in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Increased serum creatine phosphokinase (CPK) levels","bool":false},{"option":"Elevated proteins in cerebrospinal fluid (CSF)","bool":true},{"option":"Spinal cord compression on imaging","bool":false},{"option":"Normal nerve conduction studies","bool":false},{"option":"Low serum potassium levels","bool":false}],"id":548},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 6-year-old boy was brought to the outpatient department with complaints of frequent falls while running, and difficulty in rising from the ground. He had a positive family history of similar complaints. On examination, he was a young boy with an average build. Gait was lordotic. There was a scar mark over his right Achilles tendon. Powers were 4/5 in thigh muscles. Reflexes and sensations were normal. Which of the following is the most likely inheritance pattern of this disease?","answers":[{"option":"X-linked recessive","bool":true},{"option":"X-linked dominant","bool":false},{"option":"Maternal inheritance","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal recessive","bool":false},{"option":"Autosomal dominant","bool":false}],"id":549},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"An 18-year-old male presented with a history of frequent falls for the last two years. He had difficulty walking and due to imbalance became wheelchair-bound. He also had difficulty in carrying out daily household work describing a lack of precision. His family also noticed that his speech appeared to be drunken. He had no disturbance in memory and intellectual ability.  His sister also had a similar illness. On examination, he had dysarthric speech, truncal ataxia, and bilateral upgoing planters with absent ankle reflex. Regarding the above clinical scenario, what is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Autosomal dominant ataxia","bool":false},{"option":"Episodic ataxias","bool":false},{"option":"Vitamin B12 deficiency","bool":false},{"option":"Friedreich's ataxia","bool":true},{"option":"Ataxia telangiectasia","bool":false}],"id":550},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 50-year-old male presented with complaints of left-sided facial pain involving half-face only. The pain was aggravated with eating, chewing, and shaving. The pain was sharp, stabbing, sudden, and current-like. No associated complaints of hearing loss and tinnitus were reported. Neurological examination was unremarkable. What would be the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Chronic migraine","bool":false},{"option":"Multiple sclerosis","bool":false},{"option":"Cluster headache","bool":false},{"option":"Trigeminal neuralgia","bool":true},{"option":"Myasthenia gravis","bool":false}],"id":551},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A spinal cord injury patient having C6 American Spinal Injury Association (ASIA) impairment scale grade A, admitted to the ward suddenly complained of severe headache, flushing, dizziness, and disoriented. Her blood pressure was 160/100 mm Hg and her Foley catheter was clogged. What can be the most common diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Septic shock","bool":false},{"option":"Urinary tract infection","bool":false},{"option":"Acute myocardial infarction","bool":false},{"option":"Autonomic dysreflexia","bool":true},{"option":"Orthostatic hypotension","bool":false}],"id":552},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"An 11-year-old girl presents with a history of increasing headaches upon awakening for the past month. On examination, papilledema is present bilaterally. A magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of her brain reveals a 3-cm solid circumscribed mass within the fourth ventricle. There is a third and lateral cerebral ventricular dilatation. The mass is excised and microscopically shows perivascular pseudorosettes with round, regular tumor cells arranged around vessels. Which of the following neoplasms is she most likely to have?","answers":[{"option":"Glioblastoma","bool":false},{"option":"Astrocytoma","bool":false},{"option":"Schwannoma","bool":false},{"option":"Medulloblastoma","bool":false},{"option":"Ependymoma","bool":true}],"id":553},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 10-year-old boy presents with a complaint of persistent headaches for the past 3 months. A computed tomography (CT) scan of the head shows a 4-centimeter cystic mass in the right cerebellar hemisphere. On gross examination, a cyst filled with gelatinous material. The cyst has a thin wall and a 1-centimeter mural nodule. Microscopically, the mass is composed of cells that have long, hair-like processes. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Medulloblastoma","bool":false},{"option":"Meningioma","bool":false},{"option":"Ependymoma","bool":false},{"option":"Hemangioblastoma","bool":false},{"option":"Astrocytoma","bool":true}],"id":554},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 42-year-old male after a road traffic accident, suffered damage to the parietal lobe of his dominant hemisphere. What would be the most likely consequence?","answers":[{"option":"Unable to find defined places","bool":false},{"option":"Receptive aphasia","bool":false},{"option":"Denial of weakness (anosognosia)","bool":false},{"option":"Unable to appreciate three-dimensional sense","bool":true},{"option":"Neglect of contralateral limb","bool":false}],"id":555},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 32-year-old man was brought to the emergency room because he had been stabbed in the back during a fight and was bleeding profusely. He was taken for emergency surgery in the operating room. The surgeon realized that this patient had suffered a right lateral hemi-section of the spinal cord, at the level of C8, due to a stab wound. A brief physical examination of the patient was conducted when he arrived in the emergency room. What findings were most likely present in this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Flaccid paralysis of the right lower limb","bool":false},{"option":"Spastic paralysis of the right lower limb","bool":true},{"option":"Spastic paralysis of the left upper limb","bool":false},{"option":"Spastic paralysis of the right lower face","bool":false},{"option":"Spastic paralysis of the left lower limb","bool":false}],"id":556},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A neurologist while examining a 48-year-old patient noticed that he had lost the ability to discriminate between two points presented simultaneously on the skin of the left hand.\r\nAnatomically what is the most likely site of the lesion?","answers":[{"option":"Fasciculus gracilis on the right side of the medulla","bool":false},{"option":"Fasciculus cuneatus on the right side of the spinal cord at C2","bool":false},{"option":"The spinothalamic tract on the left side of the spinal cord at C2","bool":false},{"option":"Medial lemniscus on the right side of the pons","bool":true},{"option":"Dorsal column on the right side of the spinal cord at T5","bool":false}],"id":557},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 39-year-old HIV-positive man has received no antiretroviral therapy. A computed tomography (CT) scan of the head shows no intracranial hemorrhage, but there is a midline shift. A magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) of the brain shows a 4-centimeter circumscribed and solid mass. Cytologic examination shows large cells with large nuclei and scant cytoplasm that are marked with CD20, but not with glial fibrillary acidic protein (GFAP) or cytokeratin. What is the most likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Kaposi sarcoma","bool":false},{"option":"Medulloblastoma","bool":false},{"option":"Large B-cell lymphoma","bool":true},{"option":"Glioblastoma","bool":false},{"option":"Progressive multifocal leukoencephalopathy","bool":false}],"id":558},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 58-year-old man was brought to the emergency room by his wife, as he developed difficulty in speaking and weakness in his right upper limb. However, he was able to understand what was being said to him. His symptoms began around 1 hour ago. His previous medical history was significant for hypertension for the past 18 years. After doing a physical examination on the patient, the doctor ordered a computed tomography (CT) scan of the head as his provisional diagnosis was that of stroke. Which vessel is most likely to be occluded in the patient?","answers":[{"option":"Left middle cerebral artery","bool":true},{"option":"Left superior cerebellar artery","bool":false},{"option":"Left anterior cerebral artery","bool":false},{"option":"Right middle cerebral artery","bool":false},{"option":"Right anterior cerebral artery","bool":false}],"id":559},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Closed head injury resulting from an accident or cerebrovascular disease causing a stroke in the specific lobe of the brain may result in disruptions to social and emotional behavior. This can be produced by damage to which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Paracentral lobule","bool":false},{"option":"Frontal lobe","bool":true},{"option":"Temporal lobe","bool":false},{"option":"Occipital lobe","bool":false},{"option":"Parietal lobe","bool":false}],"id":560},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Which of the following is an intravenous induction agent?","answers":[{"option":"Nalbuphine","bool":false},{"option":"Lignocaine","bool":false},{"option":"Propofol","bool":true},{"option":"Atracurium","bool":false},{"option":"Fentanyl","bool":false}],"id":561},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Which of the following intravenous induction agents cause pain during administration?","answers":[{"option":"Propofol","bool":true},{"option":"Ketamine","bool":false},{"option":"Atracurium","bool":false},{"option":"Diazepam","bool":false},{"option":"Fentanyl","bool":false}],"id":562},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Which of the following is an ultra-short-acting opioid?","answers":[{"option":"Fentanyl","bool":false},{"option":"Remifentanil","bool":true},{"option":"Nalbuphine","bool":false},{"option":"Tramal","bool":false},{"option":"Pethidine","bool":false}],"id":563},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"What are the structures that get pierced during spinal anesthesia?","answers":[{"option":"Ligament, ligamentum flavum, and dura mater","bool":false},{"option":"Skin, subcutaneous tissue, supraspinous ligament, interspinous ligament, ligamentum flavum, and dura mater","bool":true},{"option":"Skin, subcutaneous tissue, supraspinous ligament, interspinous ligament, and ligamentum flavum","bool":false},{"option":"Skin, superficial fascia, and supraspinous muscle","bool":false},{"option":"Supraspinous ligament, interspinous ligament, ligamentum flavum, and dura mater","bool":false}],"id":564},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"In adults, the spinal cord extends to which of the following levels?","answers":[{"option":"S2","bool":false},{"option":"L3","bool":false},{"option":"L2","bool":false},{"option":"L1","bool":true},{"option":"L5","bool":false}],"id":565},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"While transferring a patient through an air ambulance which of the following occurs due to high altitude?","answers":[{"option":"High blood pressure","bool":false},{"option":"Increased pulse","bool":false},{"option":"Increased systemic vascular resistance (SVR)","bool":false},{"option":"Hypoxia","bool":true},{"option":"Low air in an endotracheal tube (ETT) cuff","bool":false}],"id":566},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"According to the World Health Organization (WHO) pain relief ladder, moderate to severe pain should be treated with which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Acetaminophen","bool":false},{"option":"Nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs)","bool":false},{"option":"Counselling","bool":false},{"option":"Acupuncture","bool":false},{"option":"Opioids Â± adjuvant","bool":true}],"id":567},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"An unpleasant sensory and emotional experience associated with or potential in terms of such damage is defined as which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Delirium","bool":false},{"option":"Depression","bool":false},{"option":"Behavior disturbance","bool":false},{"option":"Anxiety","bool":false},{"option":"Pain","bool":true}],"id":568},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 25-year-old female planned for elective cesarian section. The patient is planned to proceed in central neuraxial blockade. It includes which of the following?","answers":[{"option":"Spinal","bool":false},{"option":"Single nerve block","bool":false},{"option":"Infiltration","bool":false},{"option":"Topical anesthetics","bool":false},{"option":"Spinal + epidural","bool":true}],"id":569},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 10-year-old boy is brought to the emergency room by his parents. He has been complaining of headache, fever, and stiff neck for the past 2 days. He is also vomiting and has had no appetite. On physical examination, he is found to be febrile (102Â°F) and Kerning's sign is present. The rest of the examination is unremarkable. His computed tomography (CT) scan of the brain is normal. What investigation will be appropriate to perform to reach a diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) brain with contrast","bool":false},{"option":"Complete blood count","bool":false},{"option":"X-ray skull and paranasal sinuses","bool":false},{"option":"C-reactive protein","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) studies","bool":true}],"id":570},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 45-year-old man, a known case of diabetes with good glycemic control, was referred to the emergency room with a diagnosis of ischemic stroke. He developed weakness in his left upper and lower limbs 2 hours ago. His blood pressure was 130/80 mmHg and his blood sugar was normal. His computed tomography (CT) scan of the brain showed a right frontal infarct. He had no significant history. All laboratory investigations were normal. What would be the best treatment for this patient?","answers":[{"option":"Aspirin and clopidogrel","bool":false},{"option":"Tissue plasminogen activator (tpa) infusion","bool":true},{"option":"Heparin infusion","bool":false},{"option":"Clopidogrel","bool":false},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":false}],"id":571},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A young man is brought to the emergency room with a severe sudden headache within 2 hours after the onset. Which finding should be looked for in plain computed tomography (CT) brain?","answers":[{"option":"High density in cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) spaces","bool":true},{"option":"Low density in basal ganglia","bool":false},{"option":"High density in basal ganglia","bool":false},{"option":"Mixed high and low density in subcortical white matter","bool":false},{"option":"Low density in white matter","bool":false}],"id":572},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"When prescribing clozapine, which side effect is the most feared and should be closely monitored?","answers":[{"option":"Sedation","bool":false},{"option":"Agranulocytosis","bool":true},{"option":"Weight gain","bool":false},{"option":"Hyperglycemia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypotension","bool":false}],"id":573},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"What is the most common side effect associated with sumatriptan?","answers":[{"option":"Coronary vasospasm","bool":true},{"option":"Precipitation of seizures","bool":false},{"option":"Cardiac arrhythmia","bool":false},{"option":"Hypertension","bool":false},{"option":"Precipitation of psychosis","bool":false}],"id":574},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Which of the following acts as an inverse agonist of the benzodiazepine receptor?","answers":[{"option":"Lorazepam","bool":false},{"option":"Beta carboline","bool":true},{"option":"Flumazenil","bool":false},{"option":"Diazepam","bool":false},{"option":"Alprazolam","bool":false}],"id":575},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"What is the recommended medication for the management of acute opioid poisoning?","answers":[{"option":"Naloxone","bool":true},{"option":"Diazepam","bool":false},{"option":"Acetaminophen","bool":false},{"option":"Diphenhydramine","bool":false},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":false}],"id":576},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Which psychoactive alkaloid is primarily responsible for the effects of marijuana?","answers":[{"option":"Caffeine","bool":false},{"option":"Cannabidiol (CBD)","bool":false},{"option":"Morphine","bool":false},{"option":"Tetrahydrocannabinol (THC)","bool":true},{"option":"Nicotine","bool":false}],"id":577},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Which finding on clinical examination would confirm the diagnosis of transverse myelitis?","answers":[{"option":"Loss of proprioception below a particular level","bool":false},{"option":"Muscle weakness on one side of the body","bool":false},{"option":"Inability to grasp objects","bool":false},{"option":"Loss of all sensation below a certain level","bool":true},{"option":"Decreased tactile sensation in a defined area","bool":false}],"id":578},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 30-year-old female presents to the clinic with a sudden onset loss of vision, weakness, and paraparesis. A diagnosis was made of neuromyelitis optica affecting the dorsal columns, what would be observed on spinal MRI?","answers":[{"option":"Periventricular changes","bool":false},{"option":"Longitudinally extensive transverse myelitis","bool":true},{"option":"T-cell mediated immune response","bool":false},{"option":"Patchy changes in 1 to 2 spinal segments","bool":false},{"option":"Spinal cord tenderness","bool":false}],"id":579},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A child presents to the clinic with fever and left leg paralysis. What is the appropriate investigation?","answers":[{"option":"Electroencephalogram (EEG) for seizure activity","bool":false},{"option":"Blood culture","bool":false},{"option":"Stool viral antigen test","bool":true},{"option":"Magnetic resonance imaging","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebrospinal fluid analysis","bool":false}],"id":580},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"In a patient with a spinal cord injury at or above the T6 level presenting with hypertension in the upper body, what is the underlying cause of this phenomenon?","answers":[{"option":"Baroreceptor dysfunction","bool":false},{"option":"Renal artery stenosis","bool":false},{"option":"Somatic denervation","bool":false},{"option":"Parasympathetic activation","bool":false},{"option":"Autonomic dysfunction","bool":true}],"id":581},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A patient presents with symptoms suggestive of raised intracranial pressure (ICP), what triad of clinical manifestations is typically observed?","answers":[{"option":"Diplopia, ptosis, ophthalmoplegia","bool":false},{"option":"Headache, vomiting, papilledema","bool":true},{"option":"Seizures, focal neurological deficits, confusion","bool":false},{"option":"Hypertension, bradycardia, urinary incontinence","bool":false},{"option":"Fever, neck stiffness, altered mental status","bool":false}],"id":582},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"What is the most common complication observed during rehabilitation in post-stroke patients due to faulty positioning?","answers":[{"option":"Contractures","bool":false},{"option":"Muscle spasms","bool":false},{"option":"Pressure ulcers","bool":true},{"option":"Swallowing problems","bool":false},{"option":"Bladder incontinence","bool":false}],"id":583},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 50-year-old farmer has been exhibiting agitated behavior for the past few weeks. He appears restless, irritable and increasingly withdrawn from his usual activities. Over the last day, he has refused to eat or drink anything and has shown resistance to going outside for fresh air, despite previously enjoying spending time outdoors. Additionally, he has developed some motor symptoms including muscle spasms. Based on the clinical presentation described, what is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Delirium","bool":false},{"option":"Tetanus","bool":false},{"option":"Tuberculous meningitis","bool":false},{"option":"Rabies encephalitis","bool":true},{"option":"Acute bacterial meningitis","bool":false}],"id":584},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 32-year-old patient presents with recurrent seizures. On examination, there are no signs of meningeal irritation, and the patient's blood sugar level is within normal limits at 90 mg/dl. Imaging studies reveal abnormal findings in both temporal lobes. What is the most appropriate management for this patient?","answers":[{"option":"IV steroids","bool":false},{"option":"IV ceftriaxone","bool":false},{"option":"IV phenytoin","bool":false},{"option":"Supportive care with hydration and monitoring","bool":false},{"option":"IV acyclovir","bool":true}],"id":585},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A middle-aged male presents with a diffuse headache that has persisted for a few weeks. The headache has a gradual onset and is associated with weight loss, anorexia, and pain on jaw movement. Upon fundoscopy, the only finding noted is a pale optic disc. How can a definite diagnosis be reached in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Erythrocyte sedimentation rate","bool":false},{"option":"Lumbar puncture","bool":false},{"option":"Magnetic resonance imaging","bool":false},{"option":"Computed tomography","bool":false},{"option":"Biopsy of temporal arteries","bool":true}],"id":586},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A patient presents with ataxia along with a rash observed on the earlobes and conjunctiva. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Wilson disease","bool":false},{"option":"Friedreich ataxia","bool":false},{"option":"Guillain-BarrÃ© syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Ataxia telangiectasia","bool":true},{"option":"Multiple sclerosis","bool":false}],"id":587},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"What type of meningioma is characterized by a whorled continuous pattern of cells with psammoma calcifications, without distinct cell membranes?","answers":[{"option":"Atypical meningioma","bool":false},{"option":"Fibrocystic meningioma","bool":false},{"option":"Anaplastic meningioma","bool":false},{"option":"Transitional meningioma","bool":false},{"option":"Syncytial meningioma","bool":true}],"id":588},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"What is the most common cause of bacterial meningitis in a 22-year-old male?","answers":[{"option":"Hemophilus influenzae","bool":false},{"option":"Escherichia coli","bool":false},{"option":"Listeria monocytogenes","bool":false},{"option":"Streptococcus pneumoniae","bool":false},{"option":"Neisseria meningitidis","bool":true}],"id":589},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A young child exhibits difficulty walking, spasticity in all four limbs, poor feeding, and delayed milestones. Which condition is most likely indicated?","answers":[{"option":"Down syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Autism spectrum disorder","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebral palsy","bool":true},{"option":"Guillain-BarrÃ© syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Muscular dystrophy","bool":false}],"id":590},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"An 18-year-old male with a history of delayed milestones and anoxia during birth exhibits difficulty walking properly. Which condition is most likely indicated?","answers":[{"option":"Spina bifida","bool":false},{"option":"Parkinson disease","bool":false},{"option":"Muscular dystrophy","bool":false},{"option":"Down syndrome","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebral palsy","bool":true}],"id":591},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 5-year-old child presents to the outpatient department with loss of consciousness and a history of recurrent tonic-clonic convulsions over the past year. Birth and development were reported as normal. What is the likely diagnosis?","answers":[{"option":"Syncope","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebral palsy","bool":false},{"option":"Epilepsy","bool":true},{"option":"Stroke","bool":false},{"option":"Complex febrile convulsions","bool":false}],"id":592},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A child is brought unconscious to the emergency room with a history of seizures. The seizures started with twisting of the neck and eye deviation to one side, then progressing to jerky movements of all four limbs of the body. What is the true categorization of this seizure?","answers":[{"option":"Focal onset with impaired awareness","bool":false},{"option":"Generalized tonic-clonic","bool":false},{"option":"Focal progressing to bilateral tonic-clonic","bool":true},{"option":"Generalized myoclonic","bool":false},{"option":"Generalized non-myoclonic","bool":false}],"id":593},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Which of the following is the safest approach for brachial block?","answers":[{"option":"Interscalene","bool":false},{"option":"Axillary","bool":false},{"option":"Infraclavicular","bool":true},{"option":"Combined ulnar median radial","bool":false},{"option":"Supraclavicular","bool":false}],"id":594},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A hypertensive patient presents with a stroke while being treated for a disease. His blood pressure is 180/105 mmHg, the platelet count is 85,000/mmÂ³, fever is 101Â°F, PT/INR is 1.6, and dengue NS1 antigen is positive. What represents an absolute contraindication to tissue plasminogen activator (tPA) administration?","answers":[{"option":"Fever 101Â°F","bool":false},{"option":"Positive dengue serology","bool":false},{"option":"PT/INR 1.6","bool":false},{"option":"BP >180/105 mmHg","bool":false},{"option":"Platelets 85000/mmÂ³","bool":true}],"id":595},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"Which of the following drugs is used for dissociative anesthesia?","answers":[{"option":"Ketamine","bool":true},{"option":"Propofol","bool":false},{"option":"Thiopental","bool":false},{"option":"Midazolam","bool":false},{"option":"Sevoflurane","bool":false}],"id":596},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A child is scheduled for an ENT surgery. Which potent local anesthetic with intrinsic vasoconstrictive effects is considered?","answers":[{"option":"Lidocaine","bool":false},{"option":"Tetracaine","bool":false},{"option":"Procaine","bool":false},{"option":"Cocaine","bool":true},{"option":"Bupivacaine","bool":false}],"id":597},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A student enters variables into the SPSS software, such as marital status and groups like medicine used/placebo. What type of variables are these?","answers":[{"option":"Numerical","bool":false},{"option":"Scale","bool":false},{"option":"Nominal","bool":true},{"option":"Ordinal","bool":false},{"option":"Scientific notation","bool":false}],"id":598},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"What contributes significantly to the global burden of neurological disease?","answers":[{"option":"Alzheimer disease and other dementias","bool":false},{"option":"Parkinson disease","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebrovascular diseases","bool":true},{"option":"Migraine","bool":false},{"option":"Epilepsy","bool":false}],"id":599},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"More than half of the neurological burden in disability-adjusted life years (DALYs) is attributed to which of the following conditions?","answers":[{"option":"Epilepsy","bool":false},{"option":"Cerebrovascular diseases","bool":true},{"option":"Migraine","bool":false},{"option":"Alzheimer disease and other dementias","bool":false},{"option":"Parkinson disease","bool":false}],"id":600},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A 45-year-old female patient who is a known case of an autoimmune disorder visits the neurology clinic with complaints of fatigue, tingling, numbness, muscle weakness, and muscle spasms. CSF analysis reveals oligoclonal bands. Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis in this case?","answers":[{"option":"Perivascular lymphocytes and demyelination of white matter","bool":true},{"option":"Lewy bodies in substantia nigra","bool":false},{"option":"Loss of Purkinje cells in the cerebellum","bool":false},{"option":"Spongiform changes in the cerebral cortex","bool":false},{"option":"Tau protein aggregates in neurofibrillary tangles","bool":false}],"id":601},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"A woman who has been on medication for risk factors of ischemic heart disease (IHD) experiences leg cramps. She recently started treatment for secondary control of hypertension, but she subsequently developed pain in her limbs. Her creatine kinase (CKP) levels have risen to 10 times normal. Which drug has she been taking?","answers":[{"option":"Beta-blockers","bool":false},{"option":"Aspirin","bool":false},{"option":"Angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE) inhibitors","bool":false},{"option":"Statins","bool":true},{"option":"Digoxin","bool":false}],"id":602},{"info":["4th-year/neuroscience/compiled","4th-year/neuroscience/2023"],"question":"What is the recommended treatment for Guillain-BarrÃ© syndrome (GBS)?","answers":[{"option":"High dose corticosteroids","bool":false},{"option":"IV immunoglobulin","bool":true},{"option":"Interferon beta","bool":false},{"option":"Endotracheal intubation","bool":false},{"option":"IV acyclovir","bool":false}],"id":603}]
export default arr